<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Anna Maria Sichani</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on October 20th, 2021</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_AMS.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>ANNA MARIA SICHANI (Anna-Maria Chikhani | Άννα-Μαρία Σιχάνη) is a media and cultural historian and a Digital Humanist. Anna-Maria is currently a Post-Doc Research Associate in Digital Humanities at Digital Humanities Research Hub, School of Advanced Study, University of London, working on the AHRC-Towards a National Collection- funded project “The Congruence Engine: Digital Tools for New Collections-Based Industrial Histories” </p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Broadly speaking, when you think of terms like scholarly edition and scholarly editing, what do they mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Yes, I think that is, exactly, it is a quite broad term and I think it’s also quite controversial to be honest, even if it’s a historical term it’s quite broad and the history of scholarly editing would have too many definitions, to be honest, to just stick with one. But in my mind a scholarly edition is actually very, very simply like a presentation, like a critical, but not critical in the editing way, more scholarly to be honest representation of historical documents having in mind a specific goal so a specific, let’s say, scholarly purpose. This is why we end up with so many different schools of scholarly editing so the genetic, the critical, the documentary so you have a specific goal that drives this scholarly approach to the historical document. And to be honest when I’m dealing with scholarly editing as a theme and examples of scholarly editing I always have in mind, try to have in mind and keep in mind that we always pick for a tool that tries to mediate something to something else. It’s a mediation tool, you know, we have the historical document on the one hand and the scholarly edition is in the middle and we want to mediate the meaning where some aspects of the historical document to the user or to the reader, so I always try to keep this in mind.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	If you think about that in the context of digital editions or editions in general, not necessarily digital, what do we do well, what might be done better?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Having in mind the printed scholarly edition, I think right now we have achieved a good amount of scholarly, let’s say, rigour, so we are at the point that we have elaborated processes and tools. What I think we are missing as scholarly editors again, not as a digital paradigm so I think what we are lacking is we don’t have very clear instructions on how to use the editions that we’re building. So, we’re building actually final tools, books or broader sense of editions but not always with the necessary instructions. So, this is really useful I think to have in mind, you know. This is also, I think it also fits well with the digital paradigm but not only with digital, we have the scholarly rigour there, so we have a lot of information we have a lot of, you know, intellectual rigour but I think we lack, you know, the cleverness in the instructions, in the guidance to the reader.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	When you say instructions, what would that look like?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Yeah, this is really, really, I think difficult to conceptualise because I think that… try to open for example a scholarly edition, like a book, it always requires a certain amount of training to read this edition. So, you and me for example we are quite experts to be honest to read this book but, for example, if I’m going to give a scholarly edition to my mother who is a civil servant, 100% she can’t read this. So, I think that it’s a very specialised book, it’s a very specialised scholarly output that we haven’t yet made successfully the effort to communicate it to the average reader. So, I think this is really important and I think that this is where, for example, the digital edition could help. So, try to make the scholarly edition as a field, the scholarly editing as a field more accessible to the general public if you know what I mean.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And you…</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	I think it’s really difficult to conceptualise exactly. I mean, your question, you know, how the guidelines would look like, it’s really difficult because, you know, I know how to read a scholarly edition, it’s really easy for me so you need to go one step back actually and try… for example, I would do user groups with general public in order to understand what a guide would look like for the average reader to be honest, so, it’s difficult.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that tension between the scholarly edition and the general public comes from the content of these texts? I’m thinking here about introductions, for example, which tend to be written in jargonistic language, or do you think it’s something to do with the way scholarly texts are actually structured?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	I think it’s, from my point of view, it’s a disciplinary thing. So, it’s the scholarly editors historically they try, and they managed well to create a very, very specialised field so I think that was the very purpose. I mean, if you read historically scholarly editing was created also as a subfield of philology in order to, you know, with the aim to create a specialised field. So, they had historically, the scholarly editors, this feeling of we are unique, we are special, we don’t want other people to understand what we’re doing, we are doing something that is really exceptional, you know, come on, it’s ok (laughs). I mean, actually, now in 2021 we are in a completely different position, we want people to understand what we are doing. So, we don’t want to keep this ivory tower anymore I think, I’m just using this term because it’s very used actually and we know what it means so we don’t want this ivory tower we want the compete opposite, so we want to create accessible and by saying accessible we mean easily understandable so people can really understand what’s going on. And for example, you mentioned introductions, it’s not just introductions, it’s the entire book. I’m again having in mind a book of scholarly edition, the actual book, like, you don’t know how to start reading it, you know, it has for the classical text so it has the apparatus, how do you read an apparatus? It’s all Greek to me like, you know. How are you going to read for example an index, it’s really specialised tools, you know, we created these specialised tools for the sake of them actually. So yeah, I think that this is an area that we can definitely work on to be honest and I think in the digital paradigm there are ways to play around, yeah.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Some scholars contend that we’re still very much in the cultural and structural logic of print; do you think there is a future for digital scholarly editing that can take us beyond what we’re doing at present?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Yes, I do. I do think and I think that the way to approach this new reality is by actually looking in the newest texts that we have to deal with editing wise. So, we are for example, I am always having in mind, today as well but also in twenty years when we are going to speak about literary drafts, we are going to speak merely about hard drives. I mean, we are currently speaking about hard drives, you know, so the majority of writers of contemporary writers, I mean you are a writer yourself, where are you writing? You’re writing in your computer so you’re using your computer, you’re using your hard drive your using external drives, you’re using operating systems, so your using other means that we need right now to start preparing ourselves to deal with them from an editing point of view. So, I think this is the way for me to approach the future of scholarly editing. Try to imagine in ten years’ time what will be the burning issues and the burning issues will be your hard drive.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s a very interesting idea, I know you did some of your PhD research on it…</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	It was my masters.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Apologies! I wonder if you might speak a little more to that, to hard drive philology, in the context of future of editions and publishing?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	I mean actually in my masters I worked… it was merely a kind of historical overview of the encounters of like historical views of computers and computational technologies with literary drafts so the literary drafts they have a very unique materiality so from the very beginning there were like par excellence for scholarly editors to play with because they actually performed the very idea of editing as material traces of the past as well as the textual content that was there. So, in my masters I just, I studied the computational approaches like the historical computational approaches to literary drafts so I started with the genetic criticism so critics and critique and I saw different computational systems and tools that were created so it was also a bit of media archaeology and I applied there, so there were tools and programme systems and programmes that would help you to recreate, let’s say, the writing of an author. I also studied like at tools that were there for the, let’s say, more dynamic processing of the contents found in the literary drafts so there was also a bit of NLP there. And I concluded my master thesis with the topic of born digital data which is an area now in my research interest so the born digital is very, really like the moment that we are now. I mean we have been there the last twenty, twenty-five years to be honest and this is the heritage we need right now to be preserved otherwise we are not going to have any literary history of this period to be honest. And the very, very interesting bit about this specific part of literary drafts like born digital literary draft is that we need to as scholarly editors we need to open up the discussion and let’s say the engagement to the actual authors, to the authors themselves because the majority of the authors they don’t have what we used to call an author consciousness so you don’t actually realise that the moment that you’re drafting a poem and you sending an email to your publisher, you are creating a draft for your future literary historian this is all… or your future literary editor and this is really important for the author to have in mind. And I think that it’s also important to realise that in today’s world we need to have more than ever archives and libraries on board. So this is really, really important to make sure that we have cultural institutions that will be able to preserve, so this means that they will need to have trained archivist and trained librarians in issues such as digital preservation and digital archiving and stuff. And they will need to, not only preserve the born digital literary drafts, but they will need also to allow access and also, we as researchers and as scholarly editors let’s say of this new material, we need to probably train again or refresh our skills on how to approach and how to study the born digital literary drafts and how to edit them of course. I think there is… it’s a new space it’s a new place for scholarly editors, the area of born digital, definitely.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	There are two things I’d like to pick out there. Firstly, this idea of going back to hard drives and the literary drafts – do you think there is an ethical aspect to this idea of mining a hard drive? When someone sends a letter or when someone sends a handwritten manuscript to an editor or if they mark a manuscript, there’s an acceptance that that is a public act, whereas, when somebody deletes something on a computer I feel like their intention is for that deletion to be gone. So while we have things like computer forensics and technologies that allow us to uncover these authorial acts, is that something we should be doing?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Yeah, this is a really, really interesting question and it opens up a really, really interesting discussion James. So probably this is something that we should think again that you know, scholarly editing of this new assets, of born digital assets would be a very interesting cooperative place actually. So where we will be as scholarly editors but we will definitely need a studies and approaches from ethics or from law specialists or from people, as you mentioned, people specialised in computer forensics or people who are experts and specialists working on privacy and copywrite because copywrite or privacy is a historical foreign concept because as you mentioned, for example, a hard copy of a letter sent to a publisher, we are very much comfortable to accept it as a historical asset but we are kind of still struggling to accept an email as a historical asset. So I think that there is place there for a more, let’s say, comprehensive approach to the concept of what is a historical asset, what is a historical asset which is accepted to be preserved and studied as such. Also, as I mentioned because we definitely need the authors here, we are lucky enough that the majority of the authors that they are producing or they have produced born digital literary material, they are alive, so I think they will also need to be in this discussion and we really value their position so I think we currently find ourselves in the position or in the moment where we have the opportunity for a very safe discussion on scholarly editing for this specific material, for born digital literary stuff. Yes, I think it’s completely different, you know, the assets, the concepts, the procedures are brand new actually and I think it’s really, really wrong for us to try to use the same examples and the same processes and to try to transfer all the concepts to completely different material in our hands.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Thank you, and then on the subject of born digital; when you speak about born digital are you referring to print literature that is created on computers or are you referring to…</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Electronic.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Electronic literature! Perfect, so in the Catherine Hayles definition of the term. So there are massive issues around preservation of electronic literature and I agree with you completely that we’re in danger of jeopardising the literary history of electronic literature. But electronic literary practice is so broad, specifically in terms of the technologies and tools that practitioners are using, that it’s very difficult to envision how one would come up with a consistent framework for actually preserving this stuff. How do we approach this challenge?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Yeah, I think definitely as you mentioned it is really, really difficult to create a kind of one model fits all approach but, you know, there are specialists out there on digital preservation that they are working, for example, on approaches that has, for example, you have different assets, so you have a (?) or hard drive or you have, as you mentioned, a web only content so… so it’s a school of practice actually it’s a preservation working with this approach, they have kind of patterns, you know, how we approach different assets you know different procedures so preservation actually it’s a really vivid field because there are lots of things going on technology is constantly changing so I think that we should as scholarly editors refresh our skills having also digital preservation for example or digital forensics definitely in our purchase and I completely agree with you it’s difficult for a person to know all the approaches or be specialist in all kinds of for example retrievals or emulations or for every single format or for every single software or for every single, let’s say, framework and this is why for born digital material we definitely need and there is right now this kind of group of people working around this kind of digital preservation field, it’s a very kind of working together field because it’s a chaotic field so you can’t be specialist in every single yeah asset or format or software.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I’d like to chat a bit more about your work with DiXiT, which to my mind is one of the major endeavours in digital scholarly editions, specifically in relation to training and public-private partnership. I wonder if you could speak a bit about DiXiT, specifically in terms of the major outcomes.</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Yeah, definitely DiXiT was a… yeah, I agree with you was one of the major let’s say initiatives and network in digital editing in the last couple of years and I think its a great success to be found in this very nature of the network so it was a network, it was not an institution there were many institutions, there were a lot of experts involved there were a lot of scholars involved, as mentors, as supervisors. Another important aspect is that we had on board also private companies, we had institutions, libraries, museums who were affiliated and we could do our secondments so I’ve done my secondment in Gant in the Academy of Arts where they had a specialist centre for digitally scholarly editing. Also, the network also includes a lot of specialist more let’s say specialised fields such as, for example, we had collaboration with the creators of the data standards where they access the company. T created the software specialised for scholarly editing so this very idea of the network was one aspect of the success of the network to be honest so you know the creators of the funding proposal actually they managed to envision so well this you know this network so the players and the institutions but also the needs for example of us as researchers. They understood what will be our needs and another really important aspect of this network was that is was a training network and that was really, really important for us as, let’s say, fellows of this programme because we were trained in so many different aspects of scholarly editing so for, let’s say, traditional editing skills to also traditional digital scholarly editing skills encoding, x-technologies, xml, everything but then also more specialised skills like digitisation of rare books and rare materials or more advanced skills such as for example we’ve done, I worked with specialists in workshops about creative business models for scholarly editing for scholarly editions or for let’s say how scholarly editions could be maintained by libraries or other institutions so this idea of the training framework of the DiXiT was also one key factor of its success. And let’s be honest, behind all this successful network there are just people and the people were just great so we managed to, we were lucky actually and I consider myself lucky to be around a very talented and very generous people and scholars who were there for us to ask them, they were very encouraging, they were supporting us and yeah, we were lucky, we learned a lot, I think, as scholars, we developed a lot.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And was there tension between the agenda of the private enterprises and the scholarly ambitions that you might have had?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Yeah, you know, businesses are always businesses so they had products to sell and they had services to promote so this is this, you know, we can’t change this but I think this is interesting for, and we notice it within DiXiT, it was interesting to see how, for example, a business might benefit from a scholar visiting and for the point of view of a scholar on the other hand how we as scholars I think, I mean, I can speak for myself, I found it tremendously interesting to get involved in businesses and companies working for example in the publishing sector because they have this idea of the business model and they have this idea that we should maintain this but we should also have profit and the profit margins should be big enough for us to move onto the next enterprise so I think it was… yeah the tension was there, definitely, and you could notice it but I think it was really fruitful for both sectors.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I know your work in DiXiT was in relation to financial sustainability, could you speak to that?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Yeah I was involved in sustainable business models but my focus was bigger than the actual financial so I was working mainly in the area of sustainability for digital editing projects because the majority of digital editions were produced on a project-based scheme so the idea of sustainability is related to the financial aspect on the one hand, speaking, for example, of the human resources and let’s say the actual infrastructure that you need but on the other hand there is also the technological sustainability so the technical aspect of the maintenance which is really important when you speak about anything digital to be honest because there is the obsolescence of the technological and so there might be software systems, processes, framework supporting the output so yes pretty much its technology is in every single aspect and to be maintained. So, I worked mainly in developing and researching business models and for example the subscriptions, the co-op, the open access model for scholarly editing as well as best practices and tool kits for technological maintenance of scholarly editing projects that’s mainly related to be honest to funding availability plus to the stakeholders that are usually involved in the digital scholarly project. It might be, for example, a library that is willing to support the project and maintain it from a technological point of view so you know provide the server, provide maintenance etc or for example there are models they maintain for example the content, the data, but they are kind of stick to just one front end visualisation of the edition and besides this they just agnostic of the evolution of technology in terms of front end. So yeah, I think that is a really interesting field, the idea of sustainability in digital editions, anything digital to be honest in digital scholarly generally but it’s quite evolving and we can’t, that’s my conclusion, we can’t say ‘here is a prescription to fight against sustainability’ and ‘we have the solution to maintain our digital project to eternity and beyond’.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	My experience has been that when it comes to sustaining digital projects, the projects that survive are the ones that have a well-placed champion in the host institution, but as soon as that champion move on, the project is immediately in jeopardy…</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	I think, you know, you mentioned for example we might have a stakeholder that is fighting for the project and is working for the project you know this is, I mean, personally speaking for me this is a very wrong mindset. We are assuming that someone is there keeping the project, this is not the way to move forward you know. This might be a solution, an operational solution but this is not a solution that we can support actually and that we can be proud of.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think we’ll ever get beyond that?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	No, no I think we just need to accept that the digital project we will have eventually an end date, that’s it.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And we should just accept that?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	That’s it. Yes. Definitely. I think that’s it or we could find a way for example to secure the data or, you know, some basic functionalities but let’s admit technologies that they work ten years ago are not anymore working, they are not there. So we can’t assume there will always be resources or even willingness to maintain, to refurbish, to deal again, let’s be honest, with the same project. I think we just need to accept that we need to move on.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That seems like a controversial perspective… </p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	No, I think that this is from my point of view this is a fruitful tension, we should have these discussions and I’m here for me you know to be persuaded, definitely. And I think we are having the discussion about sustainability and maintenance because we are lucky enough to have twenty-five, thirty years behind us of really, really rich digital production, you know, production of digital projects, so we have a rich tradition of digital projects now that we are lucky enough now to discuss how we are going to preserve it and if we are going to sustain it and how. So I think we are at this point that we are going to have this discussion yes.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Interesting…</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Like Twenty years ago we were still building we were still fighting, let’s say, about which is the better tool to build this. Now that we have thirty years behind us of a rich tradition of digital editions or of digital projects in general we are now embarking to a different discussion, discussing about sustainability, discussion about maintenance, discussing about obsolescence, yes, this is the moment to have these discussions definitely.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned tools and building, do you think that, after those two or three generations of digital scholarly editing, there are dominant tools and platforms?</p></sp><sp who="#AMS"><speaker>AMS</speaker><p>	Ok yeah this is a really interesting question for me because together with Elena Spadini we are editing actually now we’re are doing the second edition of the RIDE you know it’s the review of digital editions so we are having a specific Issue on tools and environments for digital scholarly editing so we are actually reviewing, we are actually hosting reviews for digital tools and environments and frameworks that people are using for digital editions and I think that yes we are now at the moment that we do have…the list is big to be honest, yes, definitely there are few that are heavily used let’s be honest they are tools that are produced as specialised tools for digital editions and there are tools that are produced for general use or other use and we as scholarly editors or digital scholarly editions they use these tools, they customize it or they use the tools or environments for their own purposes. So I think definitely Oxygen is there for a reason because it was one the first editors that was XML and TEI compatible. There are transcription tools, there are alignment tools that people were using alignment tools for different purposes, but we see now that they are using these tools for also for visualising for example of variation and variance or for example there are tools for semantic enrichment which are used for different purposes, but we see that they are currently used for digital editing and digital editing projects. And of course, there are frameworks and this idea of an all in one environment such as for example the exist db, there are more comprehensive frameworks that they allow people you know to build the edition but also to add the functionalities or visualisation or publication frameworks to their edition. So, I think that there are a lot of tools right now. I think these two issues in RIDE that I and Elena Spadini are trying to capture at this very moment you know the kind of plethora of frameworks and tools but at the same time the necessity for ask to review the tools and to, you know, to be more aware as users of the tools that we’re using.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>