<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Elena Pierazzo</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  Michael Kurzmeier		 on April 14th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_MK_EP.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>ELENA PIERAZZO is Professor of Digital Humanities at Centre d’Études Superieures de la Renaissance, University of Tours where she directs the masters in Digital Humanities. She has a PhD in Italian Philology: her specialisms are Italian Renaissance, digital edition of manuscripts, digital editing, and text encoding. Her most recent publication is Digital Scholarly Editing: Theories, Models and Methods (2015). She has been the Chair of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) and involved in the TEI user community, with a special interest in modern and medieval manuscripts. Co-chair of the Programme Committee of the DH2019 conference, she was the co-chairs the working group on digital editions of the European Network NeDiMAH and was one of the scientists-in-chief for the ITN DiXiT.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	As an introduction, can we just talk about briefly what the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you in the broadest sense. </p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>	I wrote a book about that, so what does it mean in a broader sense, it means to make the text of the past, of recent past, available to modern readers in a sense that no text is coming straight from the author to the readers without the intermediation of an editor and there’s no text that isn’t the result of the dialectic interaction between the author, the editor, and the document, the materiality that concerns it. And so, this is the three actors that produces something together in a dialectic relationship that changes overtime, over periods and over methods to give it to the readers and different types of readers require different type of edition. And different periods time have different ideas of what the text is, which is the author, which is the document in the different way that they give to them. So scholarly editing is all about managing these different columns, that three columns I call them so the author, the document and the editor and the reader. This my view of that and the digital, of course mixes things up in a very nice way but maybe the question about digital comes later. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	It comes right now. What do digital editions do well? Is there something they do well in the context of what you just described? </p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>	Digital. What they do well is not the way I would put it, they just mix up things because as someone much wiser than me said, which is Willard McCarthy, that computers are perceptual agents so it’s not just a tool that makes things faster or better it simply reconceptualises everything. So, what the digital has taken into this situation is that the relationship of the editor with the document, with the author, with the readers has completely shifted and changed, it doesn’t mean it got better or worse, it simply has changed and therefore a new bunch of theory needs to be recreated, re-thought about. Reconsidered. And digital is a really powerful representational tool that allows us really to reconsider completely, for instance, what is on the page, what we intend, what we take for granted in terms of editing when we were dealing with paper because what we could put in an edition is what fits in a rectangular space, which is the rectangular space of the page, that’s not three dimensional apart from the thickness of the book itself. Otherwise, digital allows to do all sorts of wonderful things but that changed the way the relationship is built between the reader and the text because the reader becomes the user which is not the same thing. And then we have invented different types of reading thanks to digital or another type of reader, the reading that was very specialised out there, they have now become more common, like skimming and scanning that were done, you know, on newspapers and dictionary, now we use it for any kind of text which we kind of reading across and moving things with, our way for approaching a text is completely changed because of that and therefore digital is something kind of, is like a puzzle that we’re arriving, arriving to see things in such a way change to everything so we have to reconsider. So, we are putting together things and having a different picture coming out. So wonderful. Is that a better picture or is it worse pictures? That’s something we have to decide. But it is something that is changing and is even more changing now because in the past five years or even less the deep learning approaches and computer vision have come to be main actors in digital editing, something that were not the case before. Before we were, you know, transcribing, annotating on TEI and doing her thing. Now we have HTR and we do have computational methods, we do all sort of automatic things we can do. NLP approaches mixed with HDR and stuff that are about to make a second revolution on the way we do things and there are colleagues of mine here in France theorising about the computational philology, computational editing and not digital editing which is a completely different approach. And so, we have to understand these new methods that’s coming about in the past few years, and we, we won’t be shaken by it even more than we have been shaken by the representational methods that were the digital things. So yeah, I do distinguish digital from computational as you may have understood. So yeah, we have been using digital mostly these days, data modelling, structuring and presenting, mediation and things. Now computational coming about with artificial intelligence and deep learning and all sort of algorithmic analysis that is having a big impact in editing and will have even more so. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. And then I’d like to talk a little bit about one of the projects that you were involved in and I was thinking maybe we could talk about the Jane Austen’s Fiction Manuscripts digital edition. </p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>	If you wish. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Yeah, or if you have anything else at any other project that you’d rather talk about, but I’d like to talk about one of your projects and learn a little bit more about what the key decisions were with that. I don’t want to force the Jane Austen project on you if there is something else that you’d rather talk about.</p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>	It’s not that I don’t want to talk about Jane Austen because this was my pet project, to be honest, it is a project that has finished in 2010 so these days is a bit dated as well in the way we have approached it. I still stand for the choices we took on that but it is really and is being so important for my methodological reflection and that that has been a fundamental milestone on my reflection and I hope not on mine alone. It is true that these days I work on different types of approaches. We can start by that perhaps I open up to where I am now on that reflection. The key decisions where that we wanted to do a representation of as much as characteristic we could reasonably encode on TEI on that that has required has to some extension so that TEI for instance, the personalization of the model of the TEI which at the time was a bit rigid when it comes to representation of holographic manuscripts, photographic manuscripts, and that is actually the trigger that has pushed the TEI in evolving toward the source doc approach, namely the documentary editing that we have developed starting from the Jane Austen’s material, actually. I have coordinated the team on the TEI that has developed the TEI tool documentary editing because it was a bit rigid before. For instance, on the Jane Austen we decided to measure the length of the dashes. In her manuscript she doesn’t use punctuation or very little. There were a lot of dashes that were afterwards managed into proper punctuation by the publishers. We measure and try to see if there was any meaning on that, longer, shorter, intermediate, we did three different dimensions on that. We recorded all the long “s” so we recorded all her particular spellings and things, and trying to understand if there was any meaning, because what strikes us is that particularly in the Anglo-Saxon context Anglophone context studying the manuscript autographic manuscript was not really common, in particular in Jane Austen, in spite of being perhaps the most read author of English Literature apart from Shakespeare, even more than Shakespeare would say. I read somewhere that her books are the second most read book in English after the Bible or something like that. There was very little study about her photography, about her way of writing, about the way she composed, and so that was our preoccupation and try to do as much as we could to keep it that way and also to reunite these manuscripts that were scattered so there was a virtual reunion of that. In the editing process we privileged completely the documentary approach over the textual approach and our reason was that those texts are published thousands of times so there was no point for us to go toward what everybody has already done. And our improvement was to try to really see how we could represent her writing process. And that was the choice, and the other choice was to give access to our models to everybody, to explain our documentations, to be as careful as possible about documentation. And then one big regret I have this project is that was not able to convince my PI to publish the source files which nowadays seems to be kind of odd not to find the source file. Well, everybody speaks as though we should make the source files available but if you look around, there’s not many projects actually that does it. And so still this is the ‘oh what if someone is uses my stuff?’ No. Yeah. Isn’t it the proper purpose? So, anyway, so I was not able to do that and that is one of my biggest regrets on this. Another thing we didn’t encode was the layers, the relative time of the correction. We decided that we couldn’t disentangle in an appropriate way that. And that came afterwards so I was able to implement that in a project small I did about Proust and lately about Manzoni in which we’re trying to really to do the full-on genetics and evolution of the text overtime instead of simply trying to represent or do a hyper diplomatic approach that in which the manuscript and the transcription is in competition one with the other so that was a bit, as I said 2010 approach, which is a bit trying to compete with the manuscript in a sense. These days is more like the function of the manuscript and see how it evolves and how she was writing so first that and then that and then thinking back and look forward which is something that has been in place, very difficult, but it’s very fascinating as an approach, try to think the chronology and the timing of things. Is that what you want? </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Perfect. Thank you so much. Just to follow up on one thing that you said, you talked about the PI and you wanting to publish the source files and sadly it didn’t happen. My general question is, do you think that institutions are a bit more understanding of digital editions and the whole process by now? Was that maybe a factor back then? </p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>	To a point it is and to a point it isn’t in the sense that we have this idea of people stealing our research and putting our source files out there, it’s that issue of once you spend so much time in doing something you want to protect it and the lack of understanding about digital works and since they should put it out there, it’s out there and not protected because everybody can go back to the source and find where this comes from, you can demonstrate that this is yours much more than if you didn’t in a sense. What if someone find files somewhere, because they are somewhere, and uses it, how can you punish them for that? But I do think that some of my colleagues do have some resistance still on that respect and thinking for instance, now I live in France and digital editing has been a bit slower to pick up, let’s put it that way, and many colleagues still have this preoccupation of the source files as being in danger if they're out there. But it is changing. We do have an awful lot of push toward the publishing, also preprint and raw data, metadata. France has created this amazing platform for the old preprint which is really, really important, and so that is encouraging people to put out there as much as they can and it’s evolving with all this academia, whatever it is that people use every day, even if it is bad, very bad and a ResearchGate or this kind of cunning situation, but everybody uses so we have been much more confident. Still, I think that some researchers do hold back a little bit because they’re afraid of that and the other thing of course they’re afraid of is that we know that our encoding is never perfect, and we are always a bit scared that someone better than us can look at that. The point is that, you know, the editors, perhaps they are not that confident on the code and they demand the work to be done by some array or something like that and so they do not control as much as they can so when you know they publish the page, they do read everything and say I’m happy with that. Now, for the encoding since they do not master as much and so there is always room for improvement and the idea that something goes out on their name, which is not perfectly controllable by them, which they do not appreciate an importance or that because they are not fluent in that language, that is something that scares them a lot. But it is also one because it’s not just reading, but there is at a different deeper level the structure that needs to be correct and there’s always someone who says, ‘Oh yeah, you haven’t done that and that and that’, which is not really something people like. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you and I also want to talk about the book that you published, Digital Scholarly Editing, and obviously one of the key texts in the field and I would really like to hear what was your motivation on taking on this kind of project? Where did you see that this book was needed because it was needed, but how did you go about it? </p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>	Well, the fact was that I had the impression that whenever I was telling people what I was doing, I was not sure they would understand that it was a scholarly endeavour and that it’s not just, you know, techie. I thought that this is one of the motivations, the other is that I thought I discovered so many new methodological insights that while doing things and when I was explaining to people, they were kind of amazed about the world that the digital would open to them from a methodological perspective and so that was the two main reasons. There was, I saw that there was basically no publication apart from the previous one was Peter Shillingsburg’s 15 years before and knowing that how fast are they things have gone in 15 years, I said that seems crazy in a field where everything changes every six months and we have to wait 18 years before having a new book about the same topic as if nothing moves. So that was a little bit of what I thought, I thought that I could use my training as a traditional philologist into this new world to kind of create the scholarly reflections that were missing on digital editing on behalf of researchers and not just the people that we’re doing things I didn’t think at the time that digital editing was a technical problem, I thought it was a scholarly problem and it was something that needed to be reflected at a different level. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. Then finally, you also teach courses in digital humanities, text encoding and digital philology. And I’m very interested to hear what your teaching experience is especially what is the perceptions of people coming into your course and ideally what is the ideal learning outcome that they take away from these courses?</p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>	It’s complicated because you have to know that in France, where I am now, Philology is not taught, it is only taught in one institution which is the École des Chartes. And every other institution, they decided that that’s the business of the École des Chartes to do editing and so, basically, they don’t do it. So, I’m not at École des Chartes, I am at the University, I work with old text, and I said to them, listen, you cannot do that without doing a little bit of philology, it’s fundamental. So, I have taken over a few modules and I have remastered to present them the issue about editing. But I’m dealing with people that never heard about, my students, master students, they never heard about, I don’t know, what is a diplomatic edition or what is a critical edition, they don’t understand the difference between the two. They do not understand the difference between multiple witnesses or copy editing or what is a copy text and all sorts of things. So, I have to really start from that. I actually have to teach them codicology, palaeography, history of the book, transmissions and all sort of things that really, they have no single clue about. They don’t understand the idea of stemma for instance, what is a stemma and why it’s important when you have multiple scriber copies. So that is one aspect which is, and so they come out of my courses with not only an idea how to do these things digitally but really about what is a text because they think texts they grow like, I don’t know, dandelions on the pages just by magic, you know, they multiply by themselves perfectly, amazingly, without anything happening to them, so they don’t question the problem, the books are the books, the text is a text. So what’s the problem about? When I showed them the original and said this is the text as it comes out to us, they are like ‘wow, I never thought about that’ so there you are. So, we have this approach, so they come out from these classes, not just with an understanding of what digital can do for you and what is digital philology, but I hope, with idea of what is a text and how it comes to us from the past. It’s different things when I do these kinds of courses in trainings for researchers, for people that already are in jobs and which I have done for many years, and I keep doing PhD and researchers in general, and then it is mind blowing for them the idea because most of them do have some understanding of philology and therefore they do understand a textual scholarship in general. They do appreciate the methodological shift. What I do teach them, I do start from a collation which is a collation and how collation is fundamental. The management of the variants and why these variants need to be managed and how the digital can allow us to manage them in a different way with respect to the critical apparatus and this kind of thing. So, I do show them examples of editions in which the variants are not the variants are the text and where the text is without variants and then sort of things so that you know showing that I do present them the metaphor of the zoo and wildlife. So, a text in the zoo is a text that has a particular apparatus at the end of the book, nicely that you can forget even to look that, will read nice and clean, it is static, it doesn’t move. Or you are going on safari or you wait hours and days to see the little things that comes out and there you are. So, the texts in the wild are completely different than texts in the zoo. And then tell them how digital can help them to understand better the text in the wild and not just in the zoo and there you are. So, it’s a bit complicated because in Italy we do have such a strong text scholarship learning at the university. Our school is super strong and it’s compulsory, you cannot come out from the Italian University without having a lot of textual scholarship, if you do humanities, it's compulsory. I think it’s the only country I know that does it. It was a shock to even come in England and people didn’t do that. But there you are that’s something. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>      	Thank you so much. Then coming towards the end, I just want to ask, looking at the wider field of digital scholarly editing and publishing. Is there something that we are missing? Is there something you think the field needs or should have? </p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>       	We need publishers. The publishers are not on board. We know they’re scared; we know that they are fighting to find their position, but we can’t have them not part of this discourse. In France, we’re lucky, we have a few publishers that really are engaging on these discussions, particularly Open Edition approach and the Presses Universitaires they are really on that thing. But we don’t have them, not enough and this is scary because we cannot go on publishing our university server editions and make them with a different approach, only publishers can help us to develop the more generalised approaches, more sustainable approaches that are reproducible we can’t think that each edition has to reinvent the wheel or, you know, lukewarm water every time, we need things that can be reproducible and with the publisher that have a scale of doing things will help us to consolidate what we do, consolidate things that we have. We got it. We are at it. On the other hand, we can experiment on another things. So, I think we need this separation of the publishing, digital publishing and digital editing research. So we need to be able to take the preoccupation of the publication and make them available overtime out of the hands of the editors, we can’t be the responsible for editing, modelling, producing, preserving, disseminating, keeping and on and on and on, you know, it cannot be on us because we have other things to do. We cannot be the one that keep the edition available over time because we don’t have the time for one new addition. We need publishers, we need libraries, we need infrastructures that allow us, can be even commercials, not a problem, that’s why I say publishers. We need infrastructures that help us to keep this edition alive and take the burden out of editors. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>   	Thank you and then finally what would a future digital edition look like to you? What are some features that you would like to see?</p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>       	It’s difficult to say what the future will bring. I would like to see, as I have published a couple of articles on the idea of separating editions, what I call the haute couture editions from the prêt-a-porter editions. I’d like to see editions that can be done easily by an editor that does not have a big grant. I would like to see an edition that is done by a PhD student without having the need of asking too much help to their computer centre at their university. I would like to see young people experimenting on digital editing without having the need of becoming a computer scientist themselves or having a cousin that does it for them. I would like to see platforms that allow for minimal or middle type of configuration and make them available to people to publish. And I would like to see something more imaginative on the editing side as well. So, I would like, as I said, to see research that explores the time, research that explores the variation, that explores the transmissions in a different way, and not just the text of the author as the only goal of the editing, I don’t know, how much this text was read and by whom, which format and which period, how it looks like. I am Italian so Dante for me is important: which Dante people read in the 17th Century and how important that was which format was it read which Boccaccio was read in the 18th Century and stuff like that. So, I’d like to see the diachronic approach to the receptions of our books. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>      	Thank you. And then before I end recording, is there anything that you think needs to be talked about and we haven’t mentioned it yet? Is there anything you’d like to add? </p></sp><sp who="#EP"><speaker>EP</speaker><p>	I mentioned before the question of the Computational Revolution and I think that is something we need to have in mind as a warning in the sense that, not that it is bad, but it can be bad in the sense that it can be something that we do not understand fully because that will require computer scientists who work with us the point is are they working with us or against us which is not something that is very easy to see at this moment in time. There is a couple of researchers that do that but what I do think is that we need more editors, more editors that understand digital. We need more trainings and more digital in our master studies at least, as fundamental so I do think that there shouldn’t be, these days, any master course programme in which there isn’t at least one module in full digital understanding, just to better understand. I mean, we do teach mathematics to children in primary schools, it’s not because you want them to become mathematicians, but because we esteem that we see a society, that, that approach is fundamental for understanding our society and I do think we need computing these days fundamentally because we do esteem that computing is a fundamental part of our society and understanding what happens behind the screen is something that is fundamental for our future, not just because we want to become digital editors, I don’t care about that, we need understanding, that’s what we need.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>