<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Ian Maleney</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan, UCC		 on April 8th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_IM.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>IAN MALENEY is a writer, editor, and documentarian from County Offaly. His first book, a collection of essays entitled Minor Monuments, was published in 2019 by Tramp Press. It was shortlisted for the Michel Deon Prize and the Butler Literary Award. His writing has been widely published, including in The Guardian, Esquire, and the New Statesman. He was the Commissioned Writer at Temple Bar Gallery &amp; Studios in 2020, and a recipient of the Arts Council's Next Generation Bursary Award in 2019. He is the editor of Fallow Media, an interdisciplinary online journal, and has worked in collaboration on digital projects with numerous arts and literature organisations including The Stinging Fly, The Dublin Review, Tramp Press, Paper Visual Art, and Skein Press. He produced The Witness: In His Own Words, winner of Best Podcast at the 2022 Irish Podcast Awards. </p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Just to get us getting started, I wonder if you could tell me a bit about the history of Fallow?</p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	Yeah, sure. So, I guess Fallow started in 2015, summer 2015. I had sort of learned the basics of how to make websites earlier that year and I got very excited by the possibilities. I had already been involved at that stage in lots of small publications and record labels and tape labels and that kind of stuff. So, I was already involved in like indie publishing, I suppose, in a broad sense. And then doing stuff online just seemed like a kind of nice way to do things. The more I learned about it, the more I saw maybe the limitations of the way things were being done in terms of like relying on, you know, standard themes and templates and stuff like that. And how limiting that was, I think, for the types of work that I was interested in, in literature and digital music and visual arts more broadly. I just wanted to think, what if you didn’t have any of those limitations? What if you went about it in a completely different way where everything was built and designed for a certain project or piece or whatever you want to call it. Again, at the time, I think it would have been sort of peak kind of BuzzFeed, clickbait-y stuff going on at the time and it just felt like it was a real race to bottom happening in terms of people’s attention and stuff like that and I wanted to do something that was a lot slower. To just not engage with that world at all. And this was pre-2016 so the race to the bottom got a little bit faster over the next few years. At that time it just felt like, what if you only did like one piece of month and the piece just stayed there at the top of the page and anyone who came to it in that month that would be the thing that they see and you give it that time to sort of have the focus of your attention as the person and the people involved in making it, and then hopefully for the people in the involved in reading it and coming across it and discussing it. So yeah, that was kind of the genesis, I wanted to do longer form writing myself that I was able to do for newspapers or stuff like that, which is what I was mostly doing for work at the time. And so I had some essays and bits and pieces that I wanted to write and it didn’t really feel like they had a home anywhere and I felt that no one was going to pay me to do them so I might as well sort of find some way of putting out, I think it was a 12,000 or 14,000 word essay, on a small Irish essay documentary made by a friend of mine. I just needed a home for my own stuff and my friends’ stuff and that’s what Fallow grew out of. Those kind of different impulses I suppose. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	When you were starting this up back in 2015, were you aware of people who had done work in digital poetry, both in Ireland or beyond? Were there people or projects that influenced you? I’ve read Minor Monuments so I’m conscious that you are someone who is very much interested in technology and interested in experimenting with technology, so did it come out of that or did you situate yourself in kind of a broader school of digital poetry and writing, for want of a better expression?</p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	Not digital poetry at all, I have to say, just purely out of ignorance, that was the main reason. I guess, for me, again at the time being very much interested in longer form, non-fiction, I was looking at stuff that say the New York Times was doing or that ProPublica was doing so coming much more from a news, longform, reporting background, in that they were doing things with charts and graphs and maps and all this kind of stuff that would add to stories, that would animate or develop as you read through them. For me, Snowfall is the ultimate sort of example, in New York Times from whenever that was, 2013 maybe or 2014, which was the legendary thing in the news circles. Like this is what digital media journalism could be and then in brackets – if you have lots of money and time – which obviously most people don’t have so you can’t make incredible pieces of work like that very often. And you also need material. You need the material that will sustain it as well. So obviously I was coming at this from a much a more DIY background, not having a clue, you know. I think what you were saying about wanting to experiment with technology, I mean, that’s exactly what it was. I like seeing how things work, I like making things and it doesn’t matter what the thing is, you know, I’m just happy, with a drill and a saw as I am writing code. It’s the same impulse. I’m not good at any of it but I enjoy the process and Fallow has been that process for me of learning how to code, like learning how to present things online in lots of different formats. And it’s been the place where I’ve tried things out, the place where I’ve had the freedom to, you know, maybe make things that aren’t polished or perfect but are at least trying to do something a little bit different. I’ll see something somewhere and I’d think, that could be useful, and I’ll make my own version of it or whatever it is, a different piece of technology or a different type of animation or just different ways of writing code. And I’ve learned so much through it, like on a personal level, it’s been super, super valuable for that reason. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You’ve published a range of authors that obviously would be regarded, primarily, as print authors. Do you work with them as collaborators, do they come to you with a vision… how does that process work? </p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	In lots of different ways basically. Some people have come to me with a thing that they just feel like Fallow is the right place for it, because they feel like maybe it just won’t fit in print or they might be a poet or writer or whatever who wants to work with the musician and they have this collaborative relationship already and they feel like Fallow’s a good platform in which they can realise something. To me, that’s the best-case scenario – that you have two or more, or even just one person I suppose, with a vision for what they want to do and they see Fallow as a place where they can make that happen in collaboration with me. That’s terrific. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	There’s a real mix of aesthetics in the Fallow catalogue, I wonder if you could speak to that? </p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	Yeah. I remember when I first described what this website was going to be to a friend of a friend who’s an academic and writer in London, and he was like, ‘so will there be any kind of… there has to be some sort of like through line, a continual through line’ and I was like, ‘no there won’t be.’ And there isn’t, there really isn’t. I mean there’s only my changing taste and abilities and inspiration in the time that I’m making, I’m working with someone on a piece, that’s kind of all there is. In some sense, that is frustrating to me. I like things to be aesthetically cohesive. I don’t generally like things to be so all over the map. But this is something that I’ve had to just accept, like, this is a thing that grows. I think the work, the quality of work, is always what is paramount and then the work is what suggests how it looks and how it feels on the site, you know what I mean, so I kind of have to be guided by that and because, like I say, I’m bringing in quite different people and my tastes are as diverse as anybody else’s, so I want to have very strange electronic music from Australia next to like just you know something like Doireann’s piece where it’s just pure beauty, like it’s very lyrical, very accessible. Obviously then this music kind of stays in the background a little bit, but it really contributes to it and those are two different sides of the things that I like. I like the difficult things. I like beautiful things. And you know, Fallow just has been forced to represent all these different sides. It is frustrating though. I think like if I could change anything it probably would be figuring out some way to maintain that character, a consistent kind of character, throughout but it’s too late now.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	How is how is Fallow sustained from a financial perspective? </p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	So at the start there was no money at all, it was just me. I made a decision at the start that I was always going to everybody for their work and I tried to pay them as fairly as I possibly could. At least the same as they would get at a more established journal or publication. So at the start you’d be paying maybe a couple of hundred euro for piece. And then I think, what 2019 maybe, so three or four years in, we successfully received Arts Grant Funding so that’s been the main financial support, basically that’s paid for most things, since. There is a subscriber base. There has been one since the start, pretty much. I’m terrible at that side of the business basically so it’s never been huge, but it pays for all the infrastructure costs like just hosting and you know, small things like all the little bits of software subscriptions and things that are kind of required to keep the show on the road. It doesn't pay for the work itself, but it does pay for all the kind of background costs, the core costs I suppose of the project really. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And why do you think more publishers aren’t doing this kind of thing? </p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	I think there’s a couple of reasons, probably. In Ireland I think most literary publishers are supported by public funds through the Arts Council and other grants and things like that that may be available to them. And I think there may be a little bit of hesitancy there to put in applications for things like this, where it’s not in their normal wheelhouse, it’s not their normal sort of thing that they do, and that they are good at, you know. And so it can be difficult if you’re asking someone else for money in the way that you do have to with those applications to, you know, explain why and how you’re going to go about something that you’ve never done before. So that could be a little bit off-putting I’d say. And also I don’t think there’s too many people in the literary world or in the arts world generally who do have, you know, working relationships with people who can develop these kinds of projects on a technical level. Those two worlds don’t crossover as much is as I would have hoped. So, it’s hard to get people to do the work. I think that’s a big part. For someone to do it, it’s kind of like, well, you have to go to an established web design agency and that’s going to cost you a lot of money straight out of the door and on something that might not really generate any money coming back the other way because, again, people aren’t set up to monetise this kind of stuff. So I think it’s a very difficult leap to make. If you haven’t started from there, it’s hard to get there, if you know what I mean. If your job and your business is putting out 2,3,4 literary journals a year, that’s enough. I think most people don’t really need the extra headache of having to figure out how to do all that in an innovative way online. If they put it online at all, it’s kind of like a job in itself. I think people just aren’t aware of what can be done as well. That’s a big, big problem. Just, if you don’t know, how would you know to ask? If you can’t see, if you don’t have enough kind of grounding, technical grounding in it, it’s very hard to like fire the imagination in that respect and know what can be achieved and what can be done. And then I suppose the final reason, that may be the reason that we bumped up against most often, is that writers in general don’t think about it. They write for the page and if something appears online in a nice way they’re very happy about that, but only in very rare cases does it influence the form of the work in the first place. And I think that’s like something that I’d love to see develop and I think in the last of couple years have started to see more than I had seen at the start, and I think that’s a positive sign. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Fallow’s published works are all presented on your web page, is it still chronological?</p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	Yes. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think of this site as an edition? </p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	As in?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	As in the Fallow collected works, the Fallow Anthology, contextualised in various ways? </p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	Yeah, I guess so. I guess it’s kind of more to me like an archive than a collected work, if you know what I mean. I’ve been trying to think about this recently actually because I’m putting off redesigning the website as I always am, but like, what is it? Like what is the collective noun here for what’s going on? And you know ‘laboratory’ seems like a sensible kind of word, ‘workshop’ feels like a sensible kind of word for what’s going on. I’ve always had to call it a publication, even though it doesn’t really feel like one most of the time. It doesn’t operate like one. I enjoy the fact that we’re in like some ambiguous place as to what exactly it is, I think that’s a productive place to be, fruitful. But at the same time, yeah, trying not to rely too much on the existing language and metaphors for what it is as well, not wanting to be like, not being a journal or not being a magazine or anything, certainly not being a blog. I’m just finding some of the words that are there to be fairly inadequate or uninspiring in some way, so I’ve been thinking a lot recently about how would I present it in a perfect world, how would I present this thing. Should it be Fallow Workshop or Studio or something like that, something that implies an ongoing experimental set up, a place where work is done and the outcomes are sort of maybe not quite so polished or whatever, but they are, it’s a place where work is sort of explored and avenues are gone down. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You say archive – do you think about preservation of these works?</p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	To a certain extent, yeah. They are built in such a way as to be fairly resilient. Maybe some of the early pieces, slightly less so because I didn’t really know what I was doing in that respect and I was more likely to pull in a third-party script or something like that. But these days because the nature of the site is static, right, pretty much the entire site is static, there’s very little dynamic work happening in terms of pulling from a database or a server except the front page which could be made static anytime I want really. Everything else is pretty much standalone and can be moved and can be archived and rebuilt at any time. So, it is easy to just zip up the whole site and move it if and to back it up in that case as well. So I think I’ve been pretty good about that. There are obviously some things that might break down the line, again, if I’m relying on a third-party script or library or something like that, but that’s rare enough – usually it’s all done in house and in place, so it should be easy enough to back up. I don’t have any kind of strategy for how that is going to work but I will at some point have that figured out. I think in general, yeah, like you can’t really do this kind of work on the web and not be aware of how fragile and easy to break all this kind of stuff is. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Have you ever thought about depositing to an institutional repository, or to the Digital Repository of Ireland or something like that?</p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	To be honest I haven’t even looked into it. I wouldn’t even know where to start. So maybe when I’m ready to sign off you know, maybe that would be the time to do it but up until that point, yeah, I think I’ll just keep it on my hard drive.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	In your capacity as a publisher of digital fiction and poetry, is there some tool, technology, or platform, either real or imagined, that you would like access to? </p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	Em. Not that I’m aware of really. There are sort of interesting, certainly there have been over the time that I’ve been doing this, interesting ideas have popped up around how this works, but I think for the type of work that we do, it’s very hard to impose a structure which I think any kind of publishing programme or platform would. I thought about this because I think understanding the CMS is kind of like the, maybe a place where there are opportunities for sort of radical rethinking and stuff like that. That’s always been the case, people do all this stuff all the time with their own sites and things like that, which is brilliant. But there isn’t anything that I’ve come across that really reflects the flexibility and the sort of evolving nature of what we do. On a lower level there is stuff like the Svelte framework for JavaScript, that’s been very helpful over the last year or two as I’ve got to know that, just allowing me to build things very quickly and responsively that I couldn’t really build before but that’s very low level, I mean you could use that for anything.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do you think the wider field for digital publishing – the kind of publishing of born-digital creative works that you do – what do you think that field needs? What do we do well? What are the barriers?</p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	I guess the main thing that’s sort of been on my mind in terms of what would improve things, what would be an actual accelerant for this kind of thing is education. I guess by being in the literary world I am privy to a lot of workshops and writing groups and reading groups and all this kind of stuff and it would be nice if there was some way of developing, I guess, pedagogical methods for getting people to think about their work as a digital-first product. I get that that’s very difficult, being a writer myself, I can see why people don’t, I can understand that very, very well but I think there are you see someone like Joanna Walsh who’s been who has been able to adapt her practice into a digital-first thing and that’s been some of the most exciting work and Joanna is consistently pushing herself and her work in new ways and I think that’s just amazing to see. But you know, something like Seed took a lot of money and time to make, it’s not something that anyone can do. It took a lot of people and a lot of support to get that thing to look the way it did and to function how it did. So, I prefer to work on a fairly DIY level myself. I don’t think we should take a PhD to do this stuff. It’s very, very accessible if you can breakdown those barriers for people and then open it up. And I think maybe something that on a personal level, I’d probably like to explore in the future and I hope other people want to explore the future is teaching people how to make this stuff themselves and be like here’s a course for 12 weeks or something like that where you are splitting writing and creating side of it as half of that and the publishing side, whatever that might look like, as the other half and you’re kind of attempting to bring these two things together at the same time or you bring different people from different trades or crafts or whatever together in some sort of collaborative environment in order to work on these things together. So they’re not just writer/artist comes up with something, throws it over the wall, developer puts it up on the internet, like how do you have those two people working together from the start? And I think if you can find workshop environments or learning environments where we can do that and get people excited about it, I think that would be such a step change.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It is such a challenging thing... You know, when literature students say to me ‘I want to get into digital fiction’, I often respond, well then ‘you’re in the wrong degree’…</p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	I can remember still the feeling that I had, you know that first day, just leafing through literally HTML and CSS for Dummies that my partner had taken out of the library for a college project that she was working on. It was just sitting there at the table, I just was reading through it and I was like ‘this looks easy enough’ and then by the end of the day, by the time she had got home from work I had like, you know, a little page. To me, that’s the seed. If you can feel excited about that and you can see the possibilities in it, you might have the energy to go on and do it. Whereas, I actually did a year of computer science in college, as well as my degree in music technology, so I ended up doing a lot of stuff there and I just hated it, I had no interest in it whatsoever and I think partly that’s probably because I’m a practically focused person – that’s kind of how I learn, I need to be able to go in and muck around and make things. So, you know, if you can find the right approach to get people into it and excited about it quickly, where they can iterate on things quickly and sort of see results quickly, as opposed to learning to count to twenty in binary like, I don’t know, that might be the way forward with it. Where you’re seeing things on the screen straight away and you’re like, change this line and it has this effect and gradually build it up to a point where they know what responsive design is and they know what accessibility is and these kind of more technical things in terms of presenting work. I think the fundamentals can be taught very, very quickly if you have the right path for people to be on I’d say.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And have you considered ever going beyond web-based HTML works to pieces based on platforms like Unity, or, you know, more game-like engines?</p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	No, never have. Just not where my head is, I think. I like the, again, just the ‘view source’ mentality of things, you know, it’s all there for people and it’s kind of part of the project I think to be able to reveal that to people. Like there’s nothing obscure about it, like nothing is hidden or whatever. It’s kind of, you’re on the page, if you want to see how it works, you can open console and have a look and I think that’s how I learned a lot and I think it’s a useful sort of ethic, I suppose, to have. I don’t know much about Unity or anything like that, so kind of doesn’t really fit with my mental graph of how this stuff works so. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think there is a disconnect between cultural institutions – universities, galleries, funders, larger literary organisations – and this kind of work? </p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	It’s hard to say. I think obviously we’ve been very lucky the last few years with the funding that we’ve got like it’s small funding in the grand scheme of things but I think even five years before it would have been difficult to get that, it could be because we are between stools in a lot of ways when it comes to the Arts Council. We apply under literary funding, but we are publishing short films and music and all sorts of things. And so, you know, we are relying on a little bit of constructive ambiguity, to use a political term, on that. I think the museums or the galleries, it’s hard to know. Museums are one thing because they are more archival things, but with galleries, galleries need to sell things, that’s kind of their main function and that’s not really something that works well on the web. It’s very hard to get people pay for anything.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What about libraries? Should there not be digital fiction in, say, the National Library?</p></sp><sp who="#IM"><speaker>IM</speaker><p>	Yes and no. I mean, I guess it’s, I’m a little bit more cynical about this now than I was when I started, but I think perhaps one of the points of doing things online is to just kind of slightly supersede institutions like the National Library as much as they are priceless and should be defended at every single opportunity. Something like this, why should it fit? You know its library is the Internet Archive, it’s the Wayback Machine. You are kind of relying on that. I mean, obviously we should as a society be having a much broader conversation about that kind of preservation and its necessity but yeah, it just doesn’t seem to enter into this world that much, you know, the National Institutions, not to get all ‘Wired Magazine 1996’ about this, but like they’re just operating on two different levels and that’s fine, they shouldn’t necessarily feel any need to integrate with it. I do think like, I’ve seen some projects, certainly over Covid, people have to adjust things to be more online focused, obviously, in lots of aspects of their lives, but that’s been true in the Arts as well where people were able to get funding for things that would live online that they might not have been able to get before, or they might have had larger institutions or organisations pursuing projects online that they wouldn’t have done before. Some great results and some less great, but the more familiar and okay people get with it, I think the more kind of stuff will happen like that.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>