<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Dene Grigar</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on January 12th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_DG.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>DENE GRIGAR is Professor and Director of The Creative Media &amp; Digital Culture in the Department of Digital Technology &amp; Culture at Washington State University Vancouver whose research focuses on the creation, curation, preservation, and criticism of born-digital literature and net art. She has authored 16 media works such as "Curlew" (2014) and "A Villager’s Tale" (2011), as well as 71 scholarly articles and six books. She has curated exhibits at the British Computer Society and the Library of Congress and for the Symposium on Electronic Art (ISEA) and the Modern Language Association (MLA), among other venues. With Stuart Moulthrop (U of Wisconsin Milwaukee) she developed the methodology for documenting born-digital media, a project that culminated in an open-source, multimedia book, entitled Pathfinders (2015), and book of media art criticism, entitled Traversals (2017), for The MIT Press. Her recent book, co-edited with James O'Sullivan (University College Cork) and published by Bloomsbury Press in 2021, is entitled Electronic Literature as Digital Humanities. Grigar served as President of the Electronic Literature Organization from 2013-2019 and is now the Managing Director &amp; Curator of organization's The NEXT. Since 2003 she has been Associate Editor of Leonardo Reviews. In 2017 she was awarded the Lewis E. and Stella G. Buchanan Distinguished Professorship by her university, where she also directs the Electronic Literature Lab.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I just wonder if, to get us started, you might offer a definition of what is meant by electronic literature?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Yeah, so there is a lot of discussion about it, and I think Scott Rettberg in his book Electronic Literature captures all the various definitions of the term but essentially, I see it as works with a literary bent, perhaps with a literary perspective, literary flavour, that are generally experienced through a computing device in a way that it can’t generally be printed. I see them as requiring or having some elements of participatory, interactive and experiential qualities, what I call that PIE. There’s a sense of liveness to them, and they lend themselves well to virtual environments. They’re not flat, like email but offer much more rounded experiences. I draw upon Vince Dziekan’s definition of virtuality, which hits the nail on the head as to why this kind of work is so different than something like a pdf.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And as a conservator of electronic literature, when you think then about a scholarly edition, what comes to mind?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	A scholarly edition is a publication that provides in-depth, detailed information about the production and the reception of the work as well as the content. It contextualises it, helping to make sense of a work for future generations. My lab produced a scholarly edition of Figurski at Findhorn on Acid, and the first step has been to get it into the web-based, open access environment so that everyone can access it. I mean, what’s the point of having a scholarly edition if scholars aren’t able to get the work? So, step one has been to get the work accessible. Step two is to build the overlay of information that explains to scholars what Findhorn is where is it located. People probably know what Acid is but to contextualise it in terms of its more contemporary perspective as opposed to the 1970’s or ‘90’s perspective presented in Figurski, that would be important.</p><p>So, we’re developing this mechanism for being able to allow scholars to tap on the screen or click on a button and pop-up windows or modules would appear. For example, clicking on Figurski would explain that the character is based on Theodore Streleski, a real life character who bludgeoned his graduate advisor to death. So, this particular scholarly edition will provide kind of information. This project will set the pace for scholarly editions for electronic literature.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Are there digital scholarly editions of electronic literature? We’ll talk about your Pathfinders project in a bit, but generally, are there many digital editions of electronic literature?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	No, I never thought of Pathfinders as a scholarly edition as much as a way to document works for scholars because that are no longer accessible and under copyright. Eastgate Systems, Inc. published 48 titles from 1988 to 2016. While over the years, Mark Bernstein, the owner of Eastgate Systems, Inc.  has been very generous in allowing my lab to reconstruct works that he published, like Holeton’s Figurski. We also reconstructed Stuart Moulthrop’s Victory Garden and Sara Smith’s King of Space. Mariusz Pisarski was allowed to work on Michael Joyce’s Twilight, A Symphony. So, I think step one is that we have to think about is getting those works back in circulation?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s interesting that you don’t see Pathfinders as a scholarly edition, why is that?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Because the way I’m envisioning a scholarly edition is that the Pathfinders was meant to be a methodology that focused on the documentation of works that were no longer accessible but under copyright. I’m not going to tell people not to view it as a scholarly edition, but that’s not what we intended to produce. The intention was just to get the works back in circulation in the best way we could so that people could just experience them in a way that we could legally and ethically do so. </p><p>Now, I don’t have to do necessarily a Pathfinders of Figurski, although we did years ago, because today we have reconstructed it. What is needed now is for scholars to access works we have documented with the Pathfinders methodology and write about them. That’s what Pathfinders doesn’t do. So, what can we do with Figurski to enhance an understanding of it for this generation of readers as well as future generations because as we move forward, the Findhorn community might not exist in a 100 years, right? or in 50, but somebody needs to know that Findhorn really existed and it had a mission that compelled Holeton to highlight it in his hypertext novel. Does that make sense?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	One of the interesting aspects of Pathfinders I think was the inclusion of authorial perspectives, is this something that you think critical editing should look to replicate more broadly?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	I do, the interviews I thought were extremely helpful. It is the thing is we have the luxury of doing this right now. These authors are still with us. This has been my argument for quite a while.  We’ve lost people like Millie Ness, Randy Adams, Adrian Miles, and others but most of our authors are alive, And while they’re here, let’s have them tell us what they were trying to achieve with their work. I mean I would love to hear Dante tell me what he was trying to achieve with the Commedia. I can get a sense of it by reading his letter to Can Grande, but it might be different if he were able to talk directly to me. </p><p>I’m working right now on the chapter for the book that I’m doing with Mariusz for Cambridge on Michael Joyce’s afternoon, a story in which I lay out the versions and editions of the novel. I have identified 18 editions and 15 versions of it, most providing a different reader experience. Some are just cleaning up typos and issues like that or streamlining some things here and there, but a lot of it are significant differences driven by the technology––moving from a floppy disk to CD-ROM, moving from Mac to PC, and they cause big changes in the way readers receive that work.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Looking at a piece like that, which obviously has cultural significance because it’s considered one of the first commercial works of electronic literature, it just brings me back to my question, why aren’t there more scholarly editions of this type of work? </p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Not a scholarship on digital editions?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Not scholarship on digital editions but actual editions – why is there no critical edition of afternoon, a story?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	If you think about that work, even though it’s now available on a flash drive, it’s still not available for Windows computers. Now Mark has worked really hard to keep Shelley Jackson and Michael Joyce’s works available, and those were the two most popular. That said, for you to do a digital critical edition of works of electronic literature published pre-Web, you’ve going to need access to legacy computers. You be able to see my computers all around this room––I’m working from home during my sabbatical––so I brought computers home to work . But I’ve got 61 computers at the lab that I use for reading floppy disks and CD-ROMs.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So technically it’s not really feasible?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Well, that’s one reason. What I’m hoping to see happen with the book that Mariusz and I are writing is that people will be moved to re-explore these works. Knowing the edition and version of afternoon, a story will help scholars understand exactly what kind of computer they need to read the work. Matt was especially interested in people being more specific about they were writing about. Instead of simply saying they were talking about afternoon, a story, for example, they should specify that it is the 1992 Macintosh Editon on floppy disk or the 2007 CD-ROM Edition.  </p><p>It’s hard, though, to get your hands on the tech to do this kind of criticism, but also I don’t think people have been trained to do it. The further we get away from this kind of work in the humanities the more these works will be lost to future audiences. Also lost is the cultural context these under which these artists works. </p><p>Judy Malloy’s work is a prime example. When we began putting our work on the Web, we had to change content to be more accessible to a broader range of people. Early editions of Judy’s Uncle Roger was intended for an educated adult audience, but when she created a version of the work for the Web, she had to tone down some of the adult content because children had easy access to the Web’s content. So, having access to the various editions of her work and writing about the differences between them provide important information about the period in which she was writing the novel. We can also look at Figurski. It speaks to a time when hallucinogenics were illegal but still used by members of the public. It documents a commune, people were living together in harmony, which is quite unique today (laughs). I was saying in the salon that Deena Larsen held yesterday via Zoom that the general wisdom in translation studies is that you need a new translation of a work every 17 years because every new generation needs a new perspective of a work. A scholarly edition would provide that; it gives us a starting place. I’m imagining that with the Figurski project.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s an interesting idea, this idea that every new generation needs a new perspective on a work and even a new kind of way of delivering that perspective. I think you are uniquely positioned to speak to that because of the current Figurski project and I’d like to go back to that again in a bit but given a magic wand scenario, what do you think the future critical digital edition of electronic literature would look like? How would we get over the technical challenges, the infeasibility? </p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Well, it would be open access, web based, written in semantic markup in ARIA so people with disabilities can access it, so widely accessible, Number 1. Number 2, it provides a space, kind of like a Wikipedia where people can be an editor of a work, and someone else can come behind them and add content––and someone is ultimately looking at this and checking the sources and making sure that information is correct. I think the Wikipedia model is a good one.  Let’s imagine we get a digital edition finished for Figurski and it’s completed by 2025. Now, and let’s say I stop doing that project myself, maybe I oversee it, but then other scholars come in and add other information. Now let’s imagine in ten years somebody else adds some other content, and let’s say, you know, Richard Holeton adds some more content after he goes through his archives––and he adds some more information. Imagine in fifty years a very large compendium of information that connects to other scholarly editions about this works and genres like it. What I’m imagining is a library, a scholarly edition library, in which these editions talk to each other. </p><p>So, let’s imagine Figurski here, afternoon, a story here, Victory Garden . . . here’s this scholarly edition that makes a reference to Bernstein and  Eastgate Systems, Inc., that then talks to the other two works all of them are connected. It’s almost like a Wikibase where information spreads across the various scholarly editions that pertain to that. Does that make sense?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s interesting that you would privilege the idea of a social edition.</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Wikipedia has shown us that they’ve gone to great steps to ensure scholarly information. Information needs to be vetted. So, when I say open access, I mean open access to the public, but we do need to have a critical eye on the output of the public. Am I making sense?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Tell me about the Holeton project; it’s a critical edition of Figurski at Findhorn on Acid?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Yes, so the work was originally published on CD-ROM, which most people can’t play on their computers any more without an external CD-ROM drive. So this means this work really has not been accessible for almost twenty years.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yeah…</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	That’s a long time, and it’s really sad. When this work came out, I was working at Texas Woman’s University when I ordered it. This is the very one; you can see the case is cracked. The work spoke to me because I’m a child of the 70’s, the dazed and confused generation.  In fact, Richard and I are contemporaries in terms of age and experience, both come from the computers and writing communities, both from English departments––so I really like this work a lot.  The idea that this work is not accessible just didn’t sit well with me. It made perfect sense to do a Pathfinders of Figurski, which we did as part of Rebooting Electronic Literature. My lab applied the Pathfinders methodology, conducted a Traversal of it, which Richard fly in for. He gave an interview. He then turned over his archives to the lab, which then went into The NEXT, which the lab built and oversees for the Electronic Literature Organization. So, I’m holding boxes of Richard Holeton’s personal papers and his personal library of electronic literature. I gone through the papers and organised them. We did the same with the archives that Deena Larson, Stephanie Strickland, and others sent.  As I was organising Richard’s materials, I realized that there are numerous editions and versions of Figurski that needed to be documented.  The first version of Figurski, for example, was part of his master’s thesis for his MFA. It was also a short story that was flash fiction piece. There is just so much to write about in this field. My goal is to keep the work accessible so that people (and me) can do so. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Tell me about the technical side, what are you actually building?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Yeah so, we took the work that was produced in Storyspace and we reconstructed it in open Web languages.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	This isn’t public yet?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Yes, it is! God yes! Oh my God, it’s been available since summer.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Ah excellent, can you give me the URL?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	It’s figurskiatfindhornonacid.com! Richard commissioned us to get this first step done. The next step, I hope, to write a grant proposal to support the scholarly overlay I mentioned earlier. Do you see it?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So talk me through who built this?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	My lab did. So, I had an undergraduate researcher in my lab specializing coding, named Betsy Hanrahan, who began the work. Holly Slocum, who serves as the lab’s Project Manager and Senior Designer and UX/UI expert completed the coding. Kathleen Zoller, another undergraduate researcher, did the content development, including the animations we included in promotions. Holly’s husband, Tyler Brumfield, created the illustration of the mechanical pig. Greg Philbrook, the lab’s tech guru, also made sure the tech was working well. We did a lot of testing. The project started in January or February of last year and finished in the summer.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	The way you can switch between the contemporary and the classical edition is wonderful…</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	I know, I’m proud of that, that was our innovation. We wanted to capture the classic feel of a Macintosh when you read it in 2001, then we wanted to update it for a contemporary audience.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is what you’ve done here not a solution to the problem we were talking about earlier, where you’ve got thirteen different versions of something across thirteen different systems? I appreciate you lose some of the materiality in terms of the system aesthetics, but the ability to switch between these sorts of different looks and feels can allow the interface to act as a surrogate for these different systems?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	It is, but we had to give the team building this the Bubble––Apple Bubble and copies of Figurski––to use at home for them to do that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Ah yes, I see…</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	This is the argument I had with Stuart this week. He was telling… because we’re rebuilding Victory Garden  . . . on Monday, we had our kick off meeting with the team, and he said ‘oh you don’t really have to know the works’, and I said ‘today, I’m giving them the computers to take home’. He said ‘oh they don’t need that, they don’t need to see the old version’. I said ‘shut up’, (laughs) ‘it’s my lab’, ‘it’s my research process and yes, they are going to wrangle with the original version because they have to understand that sensibility and imbue that into the work as they rebuild it for the new audience’. So I disagreed with Stuart, whom I adore, because I believe in order to translate a work into a new work, you must understand the source. We are scholars who are translating works for a new audience not unlike linguistic translators do.  In the programme that I oversee, The CMDC , we train our students to think this way. Everybody in my lab, including Holly and Greg, have come through my programme, they’ve been trained in electronic literature, they’ve been trained in scholarship of not just electronic literature but also what it means to do this work.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is there a problem here with reproducibility? What you’ve done here is wonderful but obviously you have these resources that, say, an independent scholar or an institution that doesn’t have your programme might not be able to access? </p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	We should be replicating this is my argument. Lori Emerson has a wonderful lab with a specific mission. Nick Montfort has a lab called the Trope Tank with a specific focus. As does Eduardo Kac, who has built a lab where he’s able preserve his art. Labs are emerging, but we need to encourage more and embrace them and train for them.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think it’s feasible that we could ever get to a place where there is, to a degree, a standardised platform, set of tools, guidelines, and that people outside of these labs and pockets of expertise build a small, minimal, critical edition of a piece of born digital writing? </p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Well you know I use Scalar for the documentation projects. I love Scalar, and I’ve not experienced Manifold until this past week at MLA when I sat on a panel about OER with people who are experts in the topic. There is also WordPress. There are a lot of platforms we can be using, right? But I’ve been using Scalar because I like the interface that Erik Loyer created for it and it is very versatile. It works well for the documentation projects that we do in the lab. But I think when we produce the scholarly edition for Figurski, we will hand code it so that we have complete control over its functionality and aesthetic.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Am I right in thinking that the guidelines that you will be producing out of this will be the first in its kind in the field of e-lit?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	As far as I know, unless somebody is doing it and I don’t know about it. I see the Figurski project as a form of translation––it’s media translation––and when the lab went through that process to move Figurski from Storyspace into open Web languages, we had to think about lots of details that you wouldn’t think that you need to think about. For example, typography. Apple owns the fonts used for Figurski, and we were not going to pursue getting licences for them, so we had to make an artistic decision about what typefaces we were going to use that looked a lot like the classic style––but couldn’t be the original. It seems like a really silly thing to worry about…</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Not at all…</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	But we wanted to be faithful. I mean the whole point of translation is to try to be as close to the source material as possible. You know you’re going to be betraying the source material, you’re going to be cheating on it at some level, but how much are you going to allow yourself to cheat and where do have to cheat and where you not have to cheat . . . and so we had to cheat on the typography. What we didn’t have to cheat on was the colour scheme. We use this blue, and we used that pink. We couldn’t use the original pig because it belongs to the publisher, so we made our own pig. As I mentioned earlier, Tyler Brumfield, Holly Slocum’s husband, created it for us, and then Holly used it for the overarching design of the opening page/opening screen. The contemporary mode provided us with more freedom, but even so, we wanted to stay somewhat close to the feel of the work while at the same time contemporising it. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	In terms of maintenance and longevity, where does this live now, where is this project hosted?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	It’s hosted in The NEXT with all the other works there, and because it is a work donated by Richard, it is part of The Richard Holeton Collection.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s good…</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Have you seen the Amnesia Restored project?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You showed me it once, before it was live if I recall…</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Look at that one too because that one comes a little bit closer… is also close to what we do with Figurski because there is historical information, you know. We even created a 3-D model of the floppy disk.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What is the link for that?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	I dropped in in the chat it’s amnesia-restored.com. We just delivered it in December. The beta testing will be finished on Friday.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And what was the copywrite situation like with that, because obviously it was a much bigger publisher?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Well yes it was EA, but the Thomas Disch Estate owns the copywrite to the work. The estate reached out to us and asked if we would restore it for them. They gave us all the materials that we needed, but what we didn’t have was Thomas, because he died years ago. But we did have his writings. So, the students studied––this is the scholarly part of it––they read the 450 page manuscript that Thomas wrote for this piece, they had commentary that he had made about the sections that EA left out (like in the chapel episode). The students studied the manuscript, studied what Disch said, and then added that content into this version.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s much more of a critical edition in the sense than it has a lot of historical contexts added to it…</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	I wrote the web page content, so I did all of that writing myself, so it did come from me.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Are they any other examples that have been constructed in this way, very intentional, critical treatments of older digital texts?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	I would think if you are going to talk to other e-Lit people, ask them. Maybe I’m missing something, but I’ve gone to every electronic literature conference since the first one, I go to salons, the first Fridays. I mean I’m pretty… I was president for six years and on the board since 2006. I try to keep abreast of what’s going on in the field, so that I’m aware. But I think we are doing unique things in the lab, not replicating what people have already done. Mariusz is doing this work, too, but there may be others. I’ve love to know. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	One of the people I’m speaking to soon is Andy Campbell because I think what he’s doing with Alice Bell with the Curios project is really interesting…</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	I just think it’s brilliant. I know Astrid Ensslin is also involved in it. I’m looking at some Flash works now, and I’ve been talking to Astrid about how we’ve been saving… we’ve saved something like seven hundred Flash works since last January. That’s a lot of Flash work, but then that takes looking at the original work on an original computer and looking at how it plays out in Ruffle and in Conifer. So it’s a lot work this team has done on saving that work.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do we just need to just accept that this is all, from a technically perspective, hugely challenging when compared to print?</p></sp><sp who="#DG"><speaker>DG</speaker><p>	Well I think so, I think about something like James Joyce’s Ulysses. I remember when the Random House edition came out ,and there was such a big pushback on that edition because the editors took some liberties on what they thought Joyce was trying to do with the novel. And so I think it’s always challenging. It’s really challenging when the authors are gone, and you’re having to work without them. I think one of the things that we can say right now about this moment, this zeitgeist, is that most of our authors are alive. But we’re all getting older, you know, and how much longer will we all be here is the question. So, my goal, my scholarly goal, is to get as much work done as possible in the next decade and leave it behind for the next generation so that they can pick up and move with it. The lab is meant to continue even I’m gone. It will be funded beyond me. Richard Snyder, my Associate Director, has been trained to take over. He’s young with a lot of years ahead of him. Holly’s in her thirties, so is Greg. We’ve got a generation of people trained to take over.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>