<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Aodhan Kelly</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan, UCC		 on February 17th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_AK.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>AODHÁN KELLY is Postdoctoral researcher at the Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences at Maastricht University, where he is also a co-founder and coordinator of The Plant (Playground and Laboratory for New Technologies). He has a PhD in Digital Humanities from the University of Antwerp conducted as a Marie Skłodowska-Curie Fellow within the DiXiT network, on “Disseminating digital scholarly editions of textual cultural heritage” supervised by Dirk Van Hulle. His research looks at the role of digitalisation in scholarship, education and cultural heritage, with focusses on digital scholarly editions, technological innovation in higher education and a broader interest in digital inclusivity. He currently lectures at Maastricht University on the BA Digital Society and MA Digital Cultures programmes.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Scholarly edition and scholarly editing, in the broadest sense, what do these terms mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	Well yeah, that’s the golden question, I spent a lot of time discussing this when I was in the DiXiT network and it is an interesting thing because it’s ambiguous, there’s not a universal definition out there and I think that’s one of the challenges of the field, but also you could argue to some extent that it is one of its strengths. A scholarly edition to my mind is a text that’s been curated, edited by someone with expertise in that area, and represented in a way that’s usable and links to further information. The transition to digital then is of course the question - with the paradigm shift to digital and I guess I’ve always followed what Patrick Sahle would say is - that if it’s a digital edition it can’t be printed without a loss of information, it has to offer some level of functionality that is not representable in the previous medium otherwise it’s essentially just a digitised scholarly edition, so I guess that’s roughly how I see it.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do you feel it is that digital editions do well and what might be done better?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	I think there are so many affordances that the print medium doesn’t have, I mean you’ve got the ability to represent multiple versions of text simultaneously so you can have things like the versioning machine, you have fluid text, you could have comparison tools, full text searchability can be very powerful given that texts can be quite long.  I mean there are also other affordances, including the ability to potentially reach a wider audience, cost effectiveness as well compared to print scholarly edition which were kind of expensive and not easily accessible. Of course, the capacity or the potential to reach wider audiences doesn’t mean that it happens but at least there is that potential. Some editions have achieved that, I remember doing some studies into user numbers and I remember the Walt Whitman archive getting some crazy statistics and the Jane Austin archives as well in Kings College. But there are some that probably don’t get any, I remember seeing a study a few years by LAIRAH that 30% of digital products were not actually used even once, it was a really disheartening statistic and that’s probably like ten or more years ago that study was done. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Why might audiences be drawn to one edition over another?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	I guess sometimes it’s timing, you know, sometimes it’s due to something in the media or something like that. I think the Jane Austin thing coincided with some significant event that generated media interest in it but, I mean obviously user friendliness, accessibility, there’s a lot of other factors to consider. My PhD thesis was about dissemination of digital scholarly editions and I investigated that in two veins, one relating to the distribution of them, to where the audience would find them but also the diffusion of knowledge that they contained. I came up with a conceptual model of how to do that in more diverse ways because I had the feeling that editions were reaching primarily a scholarly audience and not so much a wider public audience. I called it a ‘satellite model’ with the digital scholarly edition at the centre and various other outputs around it. So you might have an exhibit for a museum, you might have your metadata that goes into data aggregators, an eBook, you get a separate print edition like the Beckett Manuscript project, separate printed editions as well as the digital, or like a MOOC or something public facing that would be connected to it.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do enough digital editions do that, do they have that level of public engagement? Do they even attempt it?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	No, I don’t think so, I haven’t been following it as closely the last couple of years but from my experience of what I studied then, there wasn’t a huge amount of engagement. Editors would publish their edition and that was it to a certain extent, the public promotion of it afterwards, to seek wider user engagement, is very limited.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Why do you think there is that lack of emphasis on wider user engagement?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	I’d imagine some of it is infrastructural in terms of finance, like it’s a costly thing, to get a grant, to get the people in to make an edition, the infrastructure for all that but then there might not always be the kind of the funding or the skills to do all the extra publicity as well. I mean maybe it might be good to make it more centrally organised, with say, university libraries who have more expertise in comms and the kinds of distribution channels. I think due to the shift to digital, one of the things I talk about in my thesis is that you lose that publisher agent in the process, and so the editor is now the publisher as well. But the publisher did a lot more than just produce the object, they had to market it, they had to distribute it, there was a whole kind of chain there and I think that side of it hasn’t really been replaced.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	This disconnect between digital scholarly editing as a practice and digital publishing as a practice, I wonder if you could speak more to that?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	Yeah I guess they exist in two different worlds to a certain extent. I mean, I worked commercially in digital publishing for a while creating digital collections, so like thematic research collections, we did collections from different archives on one topic and the digital versions then produced in a digital archive that was subscribed to by university libraries but the whole model was quite different than scholarly editions. I mean it was less text focused for a start, it was very much interested only in the top level of the documents and producing a wide selection of things that would be relevant. But then the scholarly editions are a little bit more specific, a bit more specialised and catering probably to a particular audience, quite a small audience a lot of the time because there’s a limited number of experts on certain topics, or people who want to go deep into researcher one writer. The objective of creating those editions is not to have necessarily revenues or something like that so it doesn’t mean that the creators are really looking to maximise user numbers, they’re probably typically looking to have the best quality rather than the best quantity and I think that’s probably the big gap between the publishing world and the scholarly world, this kind of quality-quantity difference.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is that part of user engagement as well? Is there a sense that scholarly editions just don’t have public appeal or is that a very defeatist way of looking at it?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	I think if you look at a scholarly edition in the way that we would normally use them ourselves as scholars, they almost definitely don’t have a wide public appeal with some small exceptions like maybe Walt Whitman or something. But that doesn’t mean that you couldn’t also produce spin off publications or outputs that have wider or different user appeals. Like if you engage in a space, for example like a museum, that is connected to your topic, created some sort of digital exhibit or even physical exhibit connected to the scholarly textual work that you’ve done. I think there’s venues and avenues everywhere to do more engagement but the sort of research edition that we use with all of its functionalities and layers of text probably not. Yeah inevitably I don’t think that’s going to have a wide audience.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So the thesis for your doctorate, ‘Disseminating Digital Scholarly Editions of Textual Cultural Heritage’… One of the things you discuss is how digital scholarly editions are threatened because of obsolescence, largely because of what you call an identity crisis… I wonder if you could explain this crisis?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	I find what you’re doing very interesting in this regard because I mean there’s no consensus even among scholars on how to define the digital edition on a scholarly level, nor on an intellectual level, even on a bibliographic level there isn’t really consensus out there on what it is a scholarly edition is, I’ve looked at how different institutional libraries have catalogued different editions and there’s such a wide variety of what there can be, they can be called an archive, they can be called a book which is available through digital access only or just generic electronic resources or something like that. I think that’s a challenge because even if you look at the different bibliographical ontologies there isn’t really a clear way to classify them. And I think to a certain extent, to be honest, users typically don’t care, or at least they don’t necessarily care what the definition of it is, as long as it serves a function, a purpose for them. And equally among the librarian world, the people that are cataloguing things don’t necessarily know the answer, there isn’t really a clear guidance for them on what to call it or how to catalogue it. </p><p>So I think there’s just sort of an ambiguity on both ends of the scale and I think that this classification issue is a challenge. and it’s maybe something to a certain extent holds it back but I think actually opens up a lot of opportunities as well because the sort of definitional ambiguity gives space to be a bit more decentralised and try different things like these sort of spin-off satellite publication that I mentioned. I know you guys are looking into Tweets like how people on Twitter might look at a critically curated list of Trump Tweets. I’ve just been thinking about this since I looked at your website and it is quite a challenge but it makes it interesting I think having that kind of definitional ambiguity leaves space for different experiments, you know, but I do think that scholarly editions, whether digital or print, do also serve a function in transmitting text through time and it’s good if there’s some sort of stability somewhere in the model. I think the TEI encoded text, for example, which is the most common markup that people use, is in my opinion at the core of the sort of the conservation/preservation stability in the model whereas everything else is a bit changeable. I mean obviously web technologies change over time so your public interface might also change or become less usable so I think it’s good to also have that one kind of stable thing within the model.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that the TEI provides that stability?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	Well I’m not an expert on text encoding, the only model I’ve ever used is TEI, I haven’t really tried anything else but I think having a framework is key and I think applying such a widely accepted framework also is super useful. TEI is also used outside of the academic world it has quite a broad usership and I think it gets updated regularly, maybe not always at the speed that people who are doing more experimental things would wish of course but yeah I think having something central like this is good for stability.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Other than the TEI, do any other tools and platforms come to mind?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	There’s so many different approaches and it seems as if in the world of digital editing a lot of people are developing new tools all the time. I don’t know if that will continue but I got this feeling that there was always many tools being developed to do the same thing that other tools can do, often because of grants and funding stipulations. I don’t believe that there are other tools/platforms out there that are as pervasive as TEI is in the digital scholarly editing world. Maybe in terms of how many people use something like Oxygen editor or some shared database systems there might be some commonalities that frequently appear, but no I don’t think there is anything quite as prevalent as TEI.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And you came through DiXiT, didn’t you?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	Yeah, I was in Antwerp with Dirk Van Hulle and I spent some time with Elena Pierazzo in Kings College and Ray Siemens in Victoria.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So you went through a programme that was designed very specifically to train researchers and support research in this area. So in terms of training, what do you think are the key skills, expertise, and ideas that we should be cultivating for the next generation of digital scholarly editors?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	I think while it’s important to train editors in both the core knowledge of editing and in current tools that it is also important to build into the training some considerations for the enabling wider use of editions, i.e. not just thinking about the scholars but thinking about how build editions as a teaching resource, can they have a public facing thing, what’s the accessibility like, digital divides, what’s the global perspective on the things we are creating. I think the need for training in the tools is inevitable and this set up will evolve over the years. It might also be good to get some perspectives on editing from people in different fields so for example if the editors is from literary circles it might be good for them to mix with linguistics, history people, different areas of the humanities. I mean you get a lot of that now because of digital humanities and how much it’s grown due to its interdisciplinarity. Within DiXiT I definitely saw benefits from the fact that we were coming from a kind of diverse, different humanities backgrounds, everyone was from humanities of some description but we definitely benefited from being stopped in our tracks sometimes and thinking ‘oh yeah there’s a different way to think about this’ you know, it does help.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is digital scholarly editing too focused on disciplines that privilege text?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	Yeah I guess so, I mean I’m starting to see a little bit more of spatial, temporal things appearing. There’s a project there, PURE3D in Maastricht there where it’s just started and they’re looking at a bit more of digital scholarly editions, the 3-D variant of this and I think that’s quite interesting to give temporal spatial interpretations of things because in certain topics it’s extremely relevant, the Battle of Mount Street Bridge I think is one of the projects. Up until this point scholarly has been almost completely text focused, but there’s space now because of the digital to do much more and I guess that’s starting to happen we see these 3D things. But yeah I mean I still I think there’s still a value in being text focused but I guess it’s with the born digital stuff is where it gets complicated and I guess that’s what you guys are going to be looking at but it’s how do you document that, what does a TikTok video get classified as, at some point it might be of historical relevance but it’s a challenge.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And what are you working on now?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	Now I’m after just moving back into the humanities, so I was in Technology Enhanced Learning for the last three years in Open University of the Netherlands and now I’m in a Humanities Department in Maastricht. I’m helping to set up a digital studies lab for the faculty so that’s going to be a physical and virtual space for researchers and students at the faculty to do experimental studies, workshops, that kind of thing so it’s trying to create an innovative environment where digital research can be performed.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, if you were to summarise the key takeaways from your dissertation, what would they be?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	It’s mostly a message to scholarly editors to try to seek more diversity in the audience you’re addressing and how you address them. Embrace this sort of ambiguity in digital scholarly editing because I think, as I said, there’s space in it to be innovative. Obviously you shouldn’t throw away the historical role of the scholar but there are a lot of new ways to diffuse knowledge that can be embraced with this space that’s been opened up by digital technologies.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And when you say diverse, who you are addressing? You’re speaking about scholar versus public?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	Yeah but also all types of diversity so think of the scholar, the student, the public but furthermore thinking of the different social demographics, different nationalities, socio-economic groups, race, gender, all of that as well.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Have you thought through some of the ways in which different socio-economic groups could be better served by digital editions?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	Well, I’ve looked at it in terms of the digital divide globally speaking. For example I have some experience working on some projects in East Africa and when you’re confronted with the reality of technological access and internet speeds it makes you reconsider some things. It’s ok to have a digital edition that has lots of fancy bells and whistles but if it can’t be accessed in a usable way in certain contexts then it presents a challenge to consider how you account for accessibility in how something is designed.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, magic wand scenario, if I gave you unlimited tools and resources, technologies both real and imagined, what would a digital edition of the future look like?</p></sp><sp who="#AK"><speaker>AK</speaker><p>	I’m trying to come up with a word for it but I got introduced to something in Educational Science called Seamless Learning and I think it’s something I might try to write about for your book but I would like to try to talk about “seamless editions” in a way where there’s less barriers, and more embracing the technological affordances that are there but like putting out mutiple types of publication output from the central text or materials. So I think it’s maybe yeah it’s purely magic wand because I think no one project has probably got the capacity to do that but I think even trying to do one or two alternative outputs would be great for projects you know.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>