<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  JuEunhae Knox</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan 		 on July 8th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_JK.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>JUEUNHAE KNOX is an early career researcher who recently completed her PhD thesis at the University of Glasgow, the first of its kind to examine Instapoetry and poe(t/m)-tagging. She led the inaugural global conference #Reading Instapoetry with James Mackay, and they are now publishing the first collection of critical essays in response to Instapoetry, as well as a special issue on global Instapoets beyond linguistic and cultural borders. She also recently published “United We ’Gram: Scrolling through the Assimilated Aesthetics of Instapoetry” with with Poetics Today, which scrutinizes the hypertextual practices and effects of consumerist Instapoetry trends. </p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Tell me about Instapoetry.</p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	Instapoetry is highly interesting because it’s been going on for a while now but is continuously changing, and has been growing ever since I started looking at this kind of artform. My background into this was actually kind of jumpstarted by my students, and I think that’s part of the thing that makes Instapoetry very powerful. It is very common amongst young people, who are looking for new forms of communication of emotion and themes that matter to them. I first was introduced to Instapoets by my students, who were 16, 17, 18 at the time. I myself had actually intended on doing my PhD on Dylan Thomas and some other modernist poets, but thanks to my students’ introduction to Instagram, I kept noticing on this new trend on Instagram, where people were tagging poets like #DylanThomas, #ElizabethBrowning, etc. The tag #EmilyDickinson got quite famous because of the TV show dedicated to it. And I started noticing that sometimes users were tagging “classical” poets to put with a pretty picture, but at other times people were using it in a very consumerist way, selling coffee and yoga and other random objects. These users often just put a catchy quote so that anyone searching a tag of their favorite poet will click the hyperlink and then accidentally be redirected to the post, even if the topic was virtually unrelated. These users are technically a separate category from Instapoets, which is why I call them poe(t/m)-taggers: people who tag poets and poems to use them for a variety of purposes. Sometimes it’s because they enjoy the poet or poem but in other cases, tagging is a clever way of selling their goods or products or services. Additionally, these poe(t/m)-taggers would often share tags of current Instapoets as well, meaning they would tag not only #EmilyDickinson, #WilliamShakespeare but also #RupiKaur, #Atticus or whichever famous Instapoet was going on at the time. This is a really fascinating trend because it’s starting to link people who are coming out in the 2010’s with people who came back centuries ago, even if they’re… &lt;drop in connection&gt;</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Sorry, JuEunhae. I don’t know what happened there.</p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	No worries. I was just giving a bit of background on the synopsis of how I got here and the place where Instapoetry led me to. I was starting to see all these posts where people would be writing a very short, minimalist quote and pairing with a really pretty picture or a background and they would, in the hyperlinks, list a bunch of poets that were not necessarily, related to each other in form, style, or time period except that they were “famous”. These poe(t/m)-taggers seemed to differ from the Instapoets themselves. But as I went on to try to define what Instapoetry itself meant, the term became really hard to define because on the one hand, it could literally mean any poetry posted on Instagram. In that case, I guess I would be an Instapoet because I’ve put some of my poems secretly on a different account on Instagram. On the other hand, however, Instapoetry has really become associated with a certain sort of theme and minimalist style which is good in some ways and bad in some other contexts. Instapoetry has been going on for a while, even in 2011, really; before that it was on Tumblr where there would just be little short quotes of bite-sized poems often paired with an aesthetic image. However, the movement started to get more famous with Rupi Kaur, particularly with her collection of poems Milk and Honey. From there, it started to take off with other Instagram poets copying her style, copying even the exact same look of the illustrations that would go with her poems. This begins to raise issues of hierarchy, as initially all people were doing was criticising Instapoets for its apparent poor quality. The brevity of the style was certainly producing quips like “you are like my last slice of pizza” or even as short as simply “you.” So people were having discussions like is this poetry? Or are these just users trying to sell their products? Because even though Instagram is free, the more likes and followers you get, the more likely you can make a brand for yourself and make really good money. So, there was a lot of criticism that was going on for these capitalist leanings. And of course a lot of attention gets thrown at Rupi Kaur just for the fact that she was one of the first Instapoets to become quite famous. I don’t know if you have heard much about Kaur, but in the beginning she was actually more famous for her post on her menstrual cycle. When Instagram tried to censor it out, Kaur became viral. From there she got so many followers, so many likes that users also started checking into her poetry as well. And indeed, a lot of her poetry is fantastic and interesting, appealing to readers and writers who have felt marginalised whether by ethnicity or gender, so it has been amazing that her work has opened a voice for a lot of new writers. But then critics have also seen that one of the difficulties of Instapoetry is that it’s so easy to plagiarize on a digital platform because it’s essentially independent publishing. Different poets, such as Nayyirah Waheed, have even accused Kaur of taking their words without crediting them. The problem is that there’s not really any way of proving this because users can just re-share, re-like, re-follow posts without linking or attributing the original author. So from this, it became clear to me that on the one hand, Instapoetry has really made a platform for so many new, amazing writers from all over the world, which is why my colleague and I are looking at how Instapoetry even differs globally. But then there are certainly difficulties in that it has started to be associated with a style of minimalist flippancy, to the point that certain Instapoets refuse to be called Instapoets because it’s become kind of a bad name. Of course, others will use the hashtag quite liberally like #Instapoet, #Instapoetry, #poetsofinstagram, #wordporn, and they have this huge list of hyperlinks because it can really help their algorithm and boost their visibility. So, I know that’s my entire thesis boiled down in a few short minutes but it’s just a really fascinating field that is only continuing to grow.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Thank you, that’s very comprehensive. How important do you think that forms like this are to contemporary literature and culture?</p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	I think that any time that there’s such a giant movement, with so many users on Instagram reading poetry, writing poetry, that I think that it’s impossible to ignore, regardless of whether there’s supposedly “ideas of quality” surrounding the poetry. It’s not just that these are completely new styles in forms of language that no one has ever seen before. There’s always been minimalist writing, there have always been short poems, there have been haikus for hundreds of years. So in a sense, Instapoetry is not completely new. However, an Instapoem is different because of that digital aspect. You might have a short, minimalist poem, you might have an objectionist poem. However, there has not been a platform that displays a poem where any user can like something and then respond to the comments, and then in those comments the author can comment back. The interaction between the poet and the audience members (or the readers amongst themselves) makes a digital marginalia that’s more extensive than the poem itself, with Instapoets explaining what they were really going for in the motions of their poem, interacting with the audience. Sometimes this may be for “genuine reasons”, sometimes because the more a user interacts with their audience, the more likely their poem will show up on the Instagram platform. There are ways of filling up the feed and boosting visibility by reposting the same poem multiple times, instead of waiting for an anthology to finally publish your collection after several years. There is this one poet that I was following who posted the exact same picture of a poem and his hand over 500 times in a single day under the hashtag #authenticpoet. He essentially flooded the feed with this single link so that anyone who looked up #authenticpoet would only see his stuff. No other literary form has had the opportunity to have special apps designed to control their commentary either. For example, if someone posts a critical comment like, “I think this poem is trash” or anything like that, one could use the app “Deeptext” which will automatically delete that critical comment so only positive comments are visible. Of course, the issue with Instapoetry is that it really is a broader form and there are longer poems out there as well. There are poems on completely different themes; it’s not just all love and depression. This is why there is a lot of debate whether Instapoetry is a specific movement or genre. I would say that although there are familiar echoes of things that have gone beforehand, one thing that makes it unique is that digital interaction between the audience and the writer.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do think that all of this is reviving legacy debates around aesthetics and taste?</p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	I don’t know if these questions have ever completely left us, but yes, I would say that people are thinking about this. On the one hand critics are asking “Do Instapoets really deserve to be in “hall of fame?” Yet the poets themselves appear to feel justified in tagging poets from their canon with their own poem. It’s like saying, “Oh #PabloNeruda fits exactly with my poem, even though we have nothing alike in terms of style or taste. He was a poet. I’m a poet. Like, I may be 16-years-old but I can make my voice be heard and so long as I have the guts and the stamina to brand myself and get my poetry out there, I can publish”. That being said, there are people who are quite upset at the fact that Instapoets have risen in fame quite so quickly because when you go through traditional publishing means, it can take a really long time. Yet suddenly Instapoets are making a lot of money if they can become influencers. My colleague just shared an example of an Instapoet named Bridgett Devoue, who is getting published by Simon Schuster. If you were to take a look at her site, it would kind of look like a soft-core porn profile peppered with cliché phrases about her heart being torn by men and that sort of thing. Yet she is getting a really good publishing deal, as she has 145k followers. This example definitely draws up more questions in terms of the speed and rapidity that an Instapoet can get famous. It's not necessarily the poem itself that builds popularity but the way that a user brand themselves as a person. And poets have always had to brand themselves; I mean, consider Jack London, you know, fashioning himself to be a self-made man. But it hasn’t been to the current height and degree now that a digital face can be shared instantly. I think Instapoetry’s speed of sharability, with a audience that can be reached at a global scale, is much different. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned that this is essentially independent publishing. Is there a need for publishing practices and the publishing industry at large to start accounting for this kind of work?</p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	Oh I would definitely say so. And one interesting thing is that many Instapoets are still seeking out the traditional form of publishing in book form as soon as they get enough followers. But like I mentioned earlier, there’s just not much accountability. This whole theme of digital poetic plagiarism. Is it wrong? Is it okay to be inspired? The trouble with independent publishing on this kind of platform is that it makes being able to find poetry really difficult, on account of the way that the feed works. It’s not just chronological. For example, if I wanted to go back to yesterday’s top post, it would take me hours upon hours. When collecting data for my pieces, it was also extremely difficult because I could only scroll so much before the page refreshed, so I’d just have to keep going as long as I could. But the feed is just so filled that there's no way to really find a poet’s post or a feed’s post from a couple days ago. Instead, the only thing to do is just take screenshots. But then what makes it even more difficult is even if you take screenshots, there’s no telling when a user might change their profile name or when they may delete a bunch of their poems which are then lost forever, like what’s happened to R.H. Sin pulling his poetry off his account. So, it would be amazing if there was a way to begin categorising these poems. Again, it’s also difficult because even if someone were to search the hashtag “#Instapoetry”, that is not going to account for all the Instapoets that there actually are. This is partly because some Instapoets are refusing to use the title, but also because others know that that name is too common to use nowadays. To avoid getting lost in the feed, it is better to categorize yourself under a niche hyperlink. As a result, much of the platform has become this enormous black hole where plenty of amazing poems (as well as in-between ones) are all getting lost. Currently there’s no way of organising or even re-finding poems the way that we have been able to do for years and years with traditional publishing where something could physically get lost, you know, but it’s less common than digital lostness, if that makes sense. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think about the ways in which your own work might be lost by sharing it on a platform like Instagram? </p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	Originally I was writing more poems on Instagram, but now I guess I have kind of backed off a little bit from that just because it takes so much effort to get followers, that I would notice that I would be spending a lot more time trying to reach out to make my profile more noticeable than actually getting to sit down and write. I did this project with the Hunterian Museum in Glasgow where I was not even producing my own poems but writing posts where I would take a classical poem and then pair it with one of the Hunterian’s. Whether they were paintings or photographs, I used the artifacts paired with poems to engage with a wider public audience with likes and follows. And in order to just get the account’s profile to be seen, I had to contact either by messaging, following, or liking hundreds and hundreds of profiles a day. Then, of course, I had to respond to messages and respond to their likes and follows, since this is what helps generate the algorithm more. I would write my post in the morning and then spend most of the day responding to likes and follows. From this experience alone, where I’m not even writing poetry, it became clear to me how much more exhausting it was to be an Instapoet where you are not being paid, at least in the beginning. Seeing how so much time gets directed in being an entrepreneur, in being a #girlboss, in engaging all of these marketing strategies, it makes sense that many Instapoets don’t get to spend much time on the language. Instead, a lot of time is spent on the picture itself, filtering it, editing it, making sure that the angle is just perfect. Even when you see those users who tag themselves with #nofilter, which has become a little movement itself, it’s clear they have performed a lot of labour just to get that right angle. So I think that, as a practitioner, I’ve backed away from posting my poems on Instagram. And again, there is that issue that even if I were to get it out there, people could take ideas from it or kind of twist it to their own… which in a sense is all exciting for poets to be inspiring other people, but if their words are not protected by that traditional means of classical publishing then it seems like all of their efforts could potentially disappear. So, I’ve deferred from publishing on the platform myself, but I think that there are other Instapoets who are dedicated enough and have enough time that they can make a name for themselves and a style for themselves that's not “copyable” by other users, but it demands a lot. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What is your understanding of a critical edition? </p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	I’m not sure if this is exactly what you’re asking for, but my colleague and I are publishing one of the first critical collections on just Instapoetry, in that we are taking essays from both practitioners and those who study different angles of Instapoetry. I myself am looking only at poe(t/m)-tagging and how some Instapoets use this trend to boost their visibility, while others are just normal users tagging poets and poems. The study examines not just the effect upon Instapoets’ writing but on the audience's reading practices as well. Critics may be saying that the supposedly decreased quality will discourage poetry reading, but from my experience in teaching, more young teenagers are reading poetry than ever before online. These digital poems are just so accessible now, and a lot of my students who maybe were not necessarily initially engaged in older traditional poets like Shelley or Keats were very interested in Instapoets. Eventually, reading Instapoets transferred into helping them make connections across time periods as well. That’s just a sample of what I have been focusing on in my piece, but we have others. For example, one of my colleagues at the University of Glasgow is writing a piece about how she as a practitioner uses Instapoetry as a kind of cathartic art, now that she has had a child. She explores what it means to try to juggle the worlds of academia and motherhood at the same time, and she connects to other Instapoets who have done that as well. This is a fascinating theme on how many women and mothers have been using Instapoetry, whether to share via oral poems or written poems, using them as an outlet as well. And then in the same collection, we have others who are looking at how Instapoetry is affecting gender norms. On the one hand, many Instapoets have claimed they are broadening the movement for young women writers of different ethnicities and backgrounds. Yet the problem is that a lot of writing itself can deteriorate into victimising women in order to get more followers. For some poets, the young, suffering woman in their narrative can never triumph. The poetic subject has to keep going through trauma every single day because there will not be any more relatable content if she suddenly finishes her arc and emerges victorious, healthy, finally whole. So another one of my colleagues is critically analysing how Instapoetry can be a very powerful movement for women’s stories but, in another way, can also serve to just bring this cycle of victimhood rolling around again. Because there’s so many themes, with so many different writers and distinctions between countries and languages, I think that there’s a lot of room for critical analysis, of different forms and of the language itself, and of course traditional studies of individual poets, seeing how they’ve changed in their practices over time.</p><p>There’s this one poet that I studied in my thesis who was really interesting in that I actually have works of his since 2011. This is very unusual because most poets update their profiles after a time. They want to change their theme or their look, and they’ll actually delete their old posts so you can’t find them again. However, even though this Instapoet has deleted some since I started studying him, he still has some of his posts since his origin. It’s really fascinating to watch how his style changed from using a lot of metaphors and allusions. The poems were generally a lot longer and had rhyme and other traditional techniques. Eventually, however, they became short, using different neutral colours and using typewriter Courier font. The poems’ themes also became a lot more vague and applicable to everybody, as opposed to his unique, personal experiences that he had written about in the past. Over the years, this Instapoet adapted his style and copied other more famous Instapoets like Atticus, r.h.Sin, Tyler Knott Gregson, and by doing that, he increased more followers. So all that to say, there’s just so much work that can be done, I think, in this field and we could go anywhere with it. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	One of the things we’re interested in with the C21 Editions project is like the creation of born-digital critical editions, so editions of work that provide various critical apparatus to make texts more accessible to users. Do you see a space for something like this? I’m pretty sure such editions don’t exist, but should they? Why don’t they?</p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	It does not exist as far as I know, and part of that is definitely because accessing information from the platform itself is hard. You’re not allowed to data scrape. Instagram has made it virtually impossible to collect information except through manual scraping, which takes a long time. They will provide limited data to purchase if you have the funding for that. This was actually something I’ve been discussing with Mike Pidd for a while now – the possibility of making some organised digitalisation, like a digital anthology for this. As far as I know, such a collection does not exist but I do think that it’s very important. I also think that people would perhaps be less resistant or more open to the idea of looking at Instapoets if it was easier for them to read a wider selection. Unless someone directly says, “Oh checkout this Instapoet” and gives a specific username, you’re going to have a really tricky time finding other Instapoets than the now famous, branded ones. If you type Instapoet, even in Google, you will either find Rupi Kaur or maybe Lang Leav, and a few more top names. But if you type Instapoet into Instagram’s search option, you’re just going to get this huge feed of unfiltered content, and it’s very difficult to find whether you like something or if something appeals to a particular experience, and even harder if you want to study a certain theme. It’s just really challenging for both academics or just normal users who are interested in finding out more. So, if there was a way to categorise, maybe by style, maybe by chronology, that would be extremely helpful. I’m sure in the beginning one would have to offer selections from poets who are currently famous, so Rupi Kaur would also be amongst them, you know. But as we progress, there could also be a way to categorise the “middling poets”, poets who maybe don’t have access to stylists and a photographer. I mean Rupi Kaur’s stylist is the same person who styles Demi Lovato and Brie Larson, people like that. But what about these supposedly “amateur” poets who are also producing really fascinating stuff, but no one can find them? There are of course other rising poets as well, like Paul Millicheap, a former academic from Oxford, who goes by the name of Brian Bilston. When I first read his works, many of which are quite humorous and witty, I was fascinated by the fact that he’s even bringing back rhymes into his Instapoetry, and many of them are much longer works too. Bilston did not originally show his face, but has begun to do so lately during his tours. Yet there are other poets who continue to capitalise on this namelessness or this lack of face. They continue to maintain complete anonymity. Atticus for example, even uses a mask to hide himself. So again, you can’t find the full profiles of these people in traditional searches. I think if there was a way to make it easier for people to find them, to read their works, but also to study them, I think that would just be much more helpful as opposed to blank rejection of Instapoetry, or even just blank acceptance of Instapoetry that just because it's new and different than it must be good, right. I mean, that’s a whole other issue itself. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I think that is an important issue. In the Instapoetry movement is there a sense of the diminishing role of the critic? Is there even a desire for critical intervention here?</p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	Well, it’s difficult because on the one hand, the writers who would want to be taken more seriously by academics often tend not to call themselves Instapoets – they just want to be called poets who publish on Instagram. Yet the thing is that there’s no denying like this is a movement in the sense that it cannot escape its platform. An Instapoem is not truly an Instapoem when it has only been published in book form by an already famous Instapoet, as opposed to a poem that was published on Instagram and now is reprinted in book form. Nevertheless, I think that such an edition is also really important in helping academics take the movement seriously, affording the opportunity to analyse it more deeply, looking at these poets and working through both common trends and individual practices. In 2018, when I first discussed Instapoetry at the British Literary Convention that was here in Glasgow, I think only four people at that convention even had Instagram accounts, so no one had heard of Instapoetry. We’ve come a long way since then in terms of more academics using Instagram now, but still, I think that Instapoetry as a genre and as a practice is still relatively unheard of amongst current scholars. At our first Reading Instapoetry Conference I invited many, many people, but most academics still hadn’t heard of it and this was just a couple of years back. The pandemic, though, heavily affected Instapoetry and its reception. People began realizing that so much of everything was fully shifted online, including performances that would usually be live. At a critical time period when you were physically forced to stay locked down inside your house, by yourself,  there was no option to go to traditional poetry slams or book clubs. So even those who were not initially on TikTok and Instagram were now turning to these mediums for reading and listening to poetry, platforms that made this option so easily accessible. All that to say this is a challenging question that you’re asking because on the one hand, many people who just enjoy Instapoetry for its own sake are not necessarily searching for a critical edition but just want instant, free access to poems that they can identify with, that can inspire them. However, this doesn’t mean that such an edition is not necessary for academics, as well as for those Instapoets who do want to be taken more seriously but have found resistance in making their voice heard. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Are there problems of literary quality to be considered? Matters of consumer culture aside, are there Instagram poets where you would say, yes, I would create a critical edition of them because this is good literature and people need to better understand it?</p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	Yes, there are many poets, actually, that I would consider as candidates for a collection, although they are extremely divergent in their styles. There is a young Nigerian poet, I think in his very early 20’s, who writes fantastic poems on sexuality, mental health, his Christian faith. We were trying to get him in our collection, but he was doing so many different poetry readings in his own country that he was unable to set aside enough time. In addition to Brian Bilston, there’s another poet that I really enjoyed whose handle is “Depressing Fridge Poems”. He arranges his short bitesize Instapoems in the shapes of those bright neon children’s magnets that you would see on your fridge. All his poems, despite their cheery alphabet format, are really biting satire on contemporary themes, whether on Boris Johnson or Trump. In addition to a lot of politically themed pieces, he does other different pieces on literature and current events, all quite distinct from each other, and I think that’s really exciting. This shows there is all the more need for an anthology because you cannot simplistically categorise those three poets. They are nothing like Rupi Kaur or Lang Leav, nor are they anything like Bridgett Devoue, who I mentioned earlier. Personally, it is sometimes difficult for me to say things about the quality of certain Instapoets because who am I to say that I’m the ultimate judge of what is true quality or not? But that being said, I would not include Devoue in a critical edition on account of the fact that her aphoristic writing is not very different from multitudes of others, whereas I definitely would for any of those three, just off the top of my head. I think that their works are really important because they are so on the nose. They will write on something that happened today and then you will see it today, right there on Instagram’s platform. Their poetry actually is current, discussing Boris Johnson’s resignation or something like that the day that it occurs. Whereas if you waited for a typical poem to be anthologised and published via traditional publishing, you could be waiting a few years, you know, and it’s no longer speaking to the people right there, the way that you have with Instapoetry. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s interesting. When I think about digital literature, I think about the computation as an inherent part of the aesthetic. Whereas with Instagram poetry, the poetry itself is essentially print, it’s just using a platform that publishes with some immediacy. Is there something inherently digital in Instapoetry? </p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	That’s so hard because it depends on Instapoet. For example, take Brian Bilston – I keep talking about him, but he is one of the most prolific at the moment. His poems are more like printed poems that happen to be posted on Instagram. While he uses some of the general techniques of Instapoets in putting his poetry out there and generating followers, the feeling is still vaguely similar to that of someone simply slapping a bunch of Emily Dickinson’s poems on the platform. However, like the poet that I mentioned earlier, the one who used the link #authenticpoet, his poems are definitely tied to the digital interface. There is technically more substance in the paratext than the actual post, which is virtually indistinct from other posts. He sometimes will repeat the same words just with different images so it makes it look like the poem is different. Another of my colleagues in our collection created an algorithm to produce poems that sound like the traditional kind of aphorisms of Instapoetry. The application was just generating these phrases by itself, some of which were nonsense but some which made a lot of sense, things like “Empty your mind. Love wins”. AI development has increased to the point that it can feasibly sometimes produce an essay, right? So a lot of the poetry that’s on Instapoetry is becoming indistinguishable from that. This is why it’s tricky because there’s both kinds – there are poets there who are essentially just using the platform to get more traction for their already-printed material. But then there are also writers who are using the special features of Instagram, generating work specifically for their ‘gram followers, and then just putting it out there on the platform as fast as possible, multiple times a day, because they can get more followers that way. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Imagine that I said to you, here’s a magic wand, and you can use it to build something that will allow you to create a critical edition of a particular Instagram poet, making the work more accessible to its public. What would you build?</p></sp><sp who="#JK"><speaker>JK</speaker><p>	I would love something that would be able to, with the permission of the poet of course, be able to look at the gallery chronologically, seeing how they’ve changed. It would be great to easily find a poem from a given date, or as far back as when they started writing to see how they’ve grown. It would also be helpful to see, because Instapoetry is so visually based, to see how they changed visually – why are they now using this particular background or font or style? As an academic that would be extremely helpful. Why are some Instapoets still writing in a way that makes them look like traditional printed books? What’s the difference between using sans serif or serif font on this particular digital platform? If there was just a way to categorize Instapoetry by fonts, rhyme, free verse, or even length – I’m not saying that you would have to have catalogues for one line, three lines but at least a way of organizing poems that are extremely long versus one-liners. Theme is of course really hard because a poet could cross multiple themes, but at least it would make it a lot easier to sift through between different poets who have primarily made their brand to be about political tropes versus romantic heartbreak. I’ve read far too many heartbreak poems during my time, so I think that would be extremely helpful. This kind of edition is especially necessary in our current environment, where poets are being forced towrite so many poems , at least if they want to stay on top of the radar. A method of categorizing some of these general categories would be really helpful, but even a method of chronologically organizing and searching poems by date would be great too. That way scholars wouldn’t have to sift through and scroll and scroll and scroll, yet never be able to find something again.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>