<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Marie-Louise Coolahan</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  Michael Kurzmeier	 on March 8th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_MK_MLC.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>MARIE-LOUISE COOLAHAN is a personal professor of English at the University of Galway. She is the author of Women, Writing, and Language in Early Modern Ireland (Oxford University Press, 2010), and her work has appeared in journals such as The Seventeenth Century, Criticism, Critical Quarterly, Huntington Library Quarterly, Early Modern Women, and Women’s Writing, as well as many essay collections. She edited ‘The Cultural Dynamics of Reception’, a special issue of the Journal of Medieval and Early Modern Studies (2020), and is co-editor (with Gillian Wright) of Katherine Philips: Form, Reception, and Literary Contexts (Routledge, 2018). She is the Principal Investigator of RECIRC, funded by the European Research Council (https://recirc.universityofgalway.ie). Her most recent publications are in Early Modern Women (2022), the special issue of Irish Historical Studies, ‘A New Agenda for Women’s and Gender History in Ireland’ (November 2022) and in the Oxford Handbook of Early Modern Women’s Writing in English, 1540-1700 (2022). </p></div></front><body><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	I probably think of editions and editing maybe in terms of my teaching rather than my research. So, although I’ve done a fair bit of digital humanities research, it’s skirted around digital editions rather than producing digital editions. The kind of editing that I’ve done has been the more traditional form of print editing; so, two anthologies I’ve worked on and different anthologies of women’s writing. And scholarly editing, I suppose to me, would have all of the annotations and scholarly apparatus around the edition of a text. The job of scholarly editing, I would associate with kind of deep archival kind of work and very detailed kind of work. So yeah, and most of my experience of what I would call scholarly editing is in traditional print format rather than digital format.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Okay and then that’s interesting as you’re talking about print formats, do you see anything that digital editions do maybe better than print formats or do differently than print formats?</p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	Yeah, yeah ‘differently’ is a good way to think about it. Well, I think the nonlinearity of a scholarly edition can be a really liberating thing, especially for students. Just the kind of nonlinearity of annotation and of follow-up information, the added value of being able to link through to meaningful rather than just explanatory notes, to be able to link through to meaningful resources that can add value for students is a real advantage. And the other advantage, although I’ve yet to see in my field an example that’s done it well, is the idea of… I’m trying to think of examples here now… I think Mary Wroth’s Poetry: An Electronic Edition [https://wroth.latrobe.edu.au], which I can give you the reference for if you’re interested in. It’s produced by a guy called Paul Salzman about ten years ago, it’s freely accessible. And one of the things about Mary Wroth who’s an early 17th-century poet is that there are multiple surviving editions of her work in manuscript rather than print, although there are some print editions. And one of the advantages of the electronic edition that Paul Salzman did is that it allows you to see the different transcriptions of the different versions of her text side by side, which is really, really useful in terms of trying to piece together the genesis of her writing and the stemma of which version of a poem came first in the variants, that’s all really useful and interesting. And so, I suppose that’s one of the main advantages of a digital scholarly edition and it’s also reminded me that somebody that might be worth talking to might be Danielle Clarke in UCD. I don’t know if you have already, she is just beginning [a new digital editing project; she has been bringing together a group of scholars in the last year or two to work on another 17th-century Irish, not Irish, well, she has connections with Ireland, another 17th-century woman poet called Anne Southwell and so she’s got scholars from all across the world together to think about how one might do a digital scholarly edition of Southwell because the only edition of her writing is one from the ‘90’s. That’s a print format edition and it hasn’t captured the complexity of the manuscript publications she was involved in. So I guess where I’m going with this is that the examples I can think of are those connected to female authors of the early modern period whose textual legacy is very complex; and a lot of scholars have been trying to think about ways in which digital formats and digital platforms might help us present the complexity of those manuscripts in a way that yields fresh insights, as well as just being more accurate in relation to the real material reality of sitting down with those manuscripts in an archive. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Just following up on that, you’ve obviously been involved in projects that deal with large data sets, particularly of women’s writing, my question will be to what extent do you think these projects were well served by existing practices in digital editing and publishing? </p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	Well, those projects, so the most recent one is RECIRC [The Reception and Circulation of Early Modern Women’s Writing, 1550-1700; https://recirc.universityofgalway.ie], which was an ERC project which compiled a relational (open-access) database as the basis for a quantitative study containing data relating to the reception and circulation of women’s writing rather than digital editions or even examples of women’s writing. What we were trying to capture was evidence of people engaging with women’s writing. So, in that sense, that’s kind of a dataset that really didn’t avail at all, I would say, of digital editions because we weren’t looking at women’s writing. You know, we weren’t looking at primary texts; our primary materials were the places and examples where people of the period had engaged with those texts. So, I’m trying to think now, so I mean the work that we did involved going out to archives and hypothesising about where we would find evidence of the reception of women’s texts. And there was a whole host of sources. I can talk in more detail about that, if you like. So, I think the only digital edition that we used for that work was the Hartlib Papers Archive in Sheffield [https://www.dhi.ac.uk/hartlib/]: the collection of letters associated with Samuel Hartlib’s circle in the 17th century was at the centre of an intellectual, epistolary network, and we did use that/ So: Sheffield have all of those papers and they have digitised them. You can search a transcription or a date or a title so let’s just say… right, so they have transcriptions and they have a digital facsimile of all the letters and the transcriptions are searchable via a number of different routes, I think full-text as well as date, as well as person. It’s a while since I worked with this database, so I’m just playing around with a bit as we speak, yeah, you can search for people as well. So that would have been the only one that actually was particularly useful to us because we were able to use that corpus as a source for people responding to letters by women. The other activities involved researchers going into specific archives and trying to kind of dig around in the primary materials and manuscripts themselves. So that’s the story with RECIRC. The NEWW [New Approaches to European Women’s Writing; https://womenwriters.resources.huygens.knaw.nl – which will be hosted by Radboud University in the next year or so] database was a crowdsourced, similar kind of thing, crowdsourced by scholars across Europe working on reception: whenever they came across examples of the reception of a woman writer, they put it into a database. And then Perdita [Perdita Women’s Manuscripts, available open-access at https://web.warwick.ac.uk/english/perdita/html/, and as the Adam Matthew subscription database, Perdita Manuscripts, 1500-1700], which would have been the project I worked on when I was a PhD student and I’ll just get a link for you there. Perdita was trying to do recovery research to find out – [starting again] so there was a growing interest at the time in the 1990’s in manuscript culture of the period and there was an understanding that women were more likely to circulate their writings in manuscripts than in print. The Perdita Project was trying to recover all the manuscripts that had women writers associated with them. And again, this wasn’t done as a digital edition; we were gathering information about each manuscript and each unit of text in each manuscript and so, what you have in the open access version there, is a database you can search for a woman [author], or you can search for a manuscript and if you go in to any of the manuscripts you have an itemised item-level description of each textual unit. If there’s a poem, the first line of each poem and the last line of each poem are provided and there’s also lots of information on the context of the manuscript. But again, this isn’t really a digital edition. The Adam Matthew version, which is of course behind a paywall, further complicates all of this and Adam Matthew have recently gone through a second iteration of that digital edition. What they did was they got permission to make digital facsimiles of a select number of the manuscripts and map them onto the contextual and bibliographical descriptions that Perdita had come up with. So that’s a more useful digital edition I suppose; it’s quite a useful combination of facsimile with the added value and rich descriptions that we did for Perdita. So that’s a long kind of answer I suppose, based on three examples I’ve been involved with, but I guess that probably the headline point is that they haven’t necessarily been [editions]; they’ve taken advantage where possible of digital editions, but haven’t necessarily been focused on the production or the manipulation of digital editions. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	OK, great. Thank you though. Maybe to dig down on that, especially when you’re dealing with those large data sources, do you think that anything like machine learning or algorithmic analysis might play into this? How would that relate to digital editing or publishing?</p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	Well, I mean with RECIRC one of the original ideas had been to do data mining of text to try and kind of come up with a corpus of words that would be trigger words or indicator words for reception. So phrases like ‘read by’, ‘understood by’ – that kind of keyword; and we did do a pilot project on it here but the pilot wasn’t entirely encouraging because a lot of the verbs that are associated with reception, it’s very hard to isolate them in relation to reception alone. For example, the verb ‘read’ operates in a whole bunch of different contexts, not necessarily ‘I read Margaret Cavendish and I thought she was really good’, which is the kind of stuff we were looking for. So that’s the extent that we went to with text mining, which is a different thing to what you’re asking about machine learning and I suppose the truthful answer is I don’t really know. I would be interested in training an algorithm to be able to identify evidence of reception, of engagement with a text. In terms of digital scholarly editions, with my own interest in reception, my own research interest tagged on, in terms of teaching, I think there’s a lot that you could do with editions like that. Let me see, training to look for particular kinds of tags maybe is probably where I would see it going. And you know, the flipside of that is it would be great to get students involved in designing the tagging and in running the machine learning. But do I have a big vision for machine learning? Probably not, is the honest answer. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thanks. I’ve done similar work and I ran into similar problems. </p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	Ah ok that’s interesting, that’s reassuring. Well, it’s not reassuring, it would be lovely if there was a great silver bullet. I think at the time when I was doing it, I thought you know, this would be great, we can just do a huge data trawl of all kinds of JSTOR material and of course it just didn’t work out. But yeah, I mean, I think there’s a lot of possibilities for kind of semantic tagging with digital scholarly editions and I can see how that would be both embeddable in pedagogy for students, but also usable by students without them having to be involved in the production of it. So that’s probably as far as I can go with that. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	You are a member of the RIA’s Languages, Literatures and Culture Committee. Does this committee consider matters such as the role of the digital in future editing and publishing?</p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	I should qualify what I say about it by saying I’ve served one term as a member of the RIA’s Languages, Literatures and Culture Committee, which is coming to a conclusion and it was during the pandemic. So, you know, what the committee were able to do was quite limited for those reasons. But my experience of that particular committee is that it aims to have a diverse range of disciplines and geographies and diversity in all its forms on the committee. And so, you might want to mention to James, that they’re looking to roll it over and I think the official deadline may have closed but it may not be completely gone yet. So, the RIA LLCC: my understanding is that it’s up to the members of the committee to determine what’s going to be on the agenda in terms of activities. So, the members of the committee generate ideas for outreach events and they’re usually informed by the research interests of the members of the committee, and I suppose the particular drive of those members at that time and the time they have available to them. And so the way it works is that someone comes up with an idea and usually there’s a working group of interested people formed and then there might be a one- or two-year lead-in to the event itself.  I think that in terms of digital, they would be very open to somebody joining the committee. But what they’re focused on is outreach and events and the production of events rather than being a standing committee. I’m sure there are other committees etc. in the Royal Irish Academy that are standing committees for the business of particular disciplines – but you’d need to consult the RIA or a current Fellow for details on that. This one is kind of an outreach committee, you don’t have to be a member of the Royal Irish Academy to be on it and I’m not a formal ‘member’ of the Royal Irish Academy. I think they would be very open to someone like James or Orla Murphy devising a project or an outreach event. It might be a symposium, it might be a celebrated speaker – it can be a whole host of different ways to focus on the question of scholarly editing and digital scholarly editing but it’s generated by the people that are on the committee. If you think James would be interested – in fact, I might just send you on the link after I’m done. So, the only, in in my time there, there was a ‘Future of Media’ event (in May 2021 – report and archive here: 'The future of media: experience, models, practice' | Royal Irish Academy (ria.ie)). The members working in Language disciplines are very active and their events are often kind of policy events where they’re trying to influence the way that policy is going in terms of [non-anglophone] languages and government. So, I would say outreach and policy are the two things that they are focused on but they kind of aim for it to be from the ground up so it’s really about having representation from the field on the committee, rather than the committee determining a programme of issues of concern. Does that make sense? </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Yeah, absolutely. Thank you.</p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	But the other organisation that I think might be more directly of interest would be the Irish Humanities Alliance, which has a DH working group. I’m on the board of the Irish Humanities Alliance and there would be reps from Cork; I think Chris Williams is currently the chair. There is definitely a digital humanities working group and I’ll just give you their website address here now as well. The IHA board had determined four or five areas of emerging concern to the humanities: one of them is environmental humanities, one is digital humanities, and they have specific working groups in those areas, and that might actually, I think, be a more effective but also more sustainable way of trying to get something like what you’re working on, onto the agenda nationally. But again, you might follow up with me and I’ll see if I can find out where the detailed information is. It's always the way when you're on the spot and you're looking for something, you can’t find it. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Yeah of course.</p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	But anyway, so in terms of those, in my experience of those two committees and they are the only two I have been involved with, I would say that actually the Irish Huminites Alliance would be the more sustainable body through which to promote an interest in this field. The RIA, I think, is there to be used but it would be up to somebody like James to get onto that committee and to forge ahead with it, if that makes sense.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Yeah, absolutely. Great. Thank you. Just one more open-ended question before I let you go. So what ideally does the future digital edition and the future publishing platform look like to you? If you could make a wish what would be your ideal future edition?</p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	Well, my ideal future edition would actually be one that could handle an enriched digital facsimile I suppose, is actually what my ideal one would be. I think what we have at the moment is we have lots of editions that have full-text transcriptions alongside digital images. An ideal one would marry the two. With something like … and just before you go, I will get the Mary Wroth Electronic Edition. I could find that quickly there and you can see I guess what I mean which is side-by-side parallel electronic transcriptions but they’re all transcriptions. Ah there we go; that’s more useful. So: this is the electronic edition. Mary Wroth would be a pretty canonical woman writer of the period now; she’s one of the prolific writers in prestigious forms like the sonnet, and she wrote drama, so she’s one of the major authors that makes it onto undergraduate curricula now. And what Paul has done here is, there’s a very messy textual legacy, but he’s managed to have parallel full-text transcriptions with glossary notes underneath each of the poems. And that’s all really useful, and I’ve used it for my teaching. But something like that or that could be embedded into digital images as well, would be super useful But something like that, I think, could enable that kind of parallel experience of the different versions of the text. I mean, there is Susan Schreibman’s ‘The Versioning Machine’, there’s a whole bunch of different ways of doing it. There’s the Devonshire Manuscript which I don’t know if you’re aware of? Ray Siemens &amp; co did a ‘social edition’ of a particular manuscript which, I’m sure, which again is all digitised, it’s all text. So I have the link for that here now as well. It's all text on a screen so it’s all kind of transcription-based rather than giving you any kind of material sense of what the actual manuscript or the actual early modern printed text would have looked like. So yeah, that’s what my ideal would be, would be kind of something that marries the two, but I think that’s probably pretty ambitious, so. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. That’s all for my questions. Do you think there’s anything that you think we should talk about do you have anything you’d like to add? </p></sp><sp who="#MLC"><speaker>MLC</speaker><p>	No, I don’t think so. I mean, I think, yeah, I think it’s been an interesting conversation. I’m not sure how entirely useful I’ve been to you, but hopefully it’s been kind of some kind of a different perspective on things anyway, with some ideas of ways forward. But it’s very interesting what you’re doing.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>