<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Elena Spadini</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  Michael Kurzmeier	 on March 29th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_MK_ES.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>ELENA SPADINI is currently a Research Navigator at the University of Basel, collaborating with DH and in particular scholarly editing projects. She has been working in digital philology as a Marie Curie fellow (ITN DiXiT) at the Huygens Institute of the Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences and as a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Lausanne. Her background is in romance philology (PhD) and her research interests span from medieval manuscripts to born-digital literary sources.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you? </p></sp><sp who="#ES"><speaker>ES</speaker><p>	I would say that scholarly edition to me is a statement about text. It is composed by a critical and established text (and that’s already something that the editor is saying about this text) and then you have all the materials that are there to support this statement. So, I would say that all the commentaries and all the additional materials that you have there –like apparatus and introductions and information, annotations, semantic annotation structure, linguistic addition, whatever you might want to say about the text– is all these additional information that is there to support the statement of the editor. I come from Italy and in Italian textual criticism there is an authoritative editor named Gianfranco Contini who was saying that the edition is a working hypothesis and that all these materials are there to support the hypothesis, which should be a scientifically based hypothesis.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. And in the light of what you said, is there something that you think digital editions do well? </p></sp><sp who="#ES"><speaker>ES</speaker><p>	Yeah, I think they can do pretty much everything: all the features of a scholarly edition I can think about can be there in a digital edition, definitely. And one big plus is not only the possibility to have a data driven approach to the scholarly edition but also, if you have that kind of approach, the possibility to reuse the data. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you and is there something that you think is missing in digital editions when you compare them to say more traditional print editions?</p></sp><sp who="#ES"><speaker>ES</speaker><p>	No. There are things that can be done better or differently, but I don’t think that intrinsically a digital edition lacks some features. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	And obviously I want to talk a little bit more about digital editions. So, when you think of digital editions and digital editing, I’d like to know what tools and platforms come to mind and what you think are the affordances and limitations of those tools and platforms. Really, in the widest sense, so we can talk about XML, if you want to start there, but it is up to you. </p></sp><sp who="#ES"><speaker>ES</speaker><p>	I changed job recently. I went from doing research to supporting researchers and so now we are thinking a lot about what kind of tools, platforms and infrastructures researchers need to produce digital editions. Also, I’m curating a special issue of the RIDE Journal, I don’t know if you are familiar with it. The journal is devoted to reviews of digital editions: the idea is that you write a book, you have it reviewed in a scientific journal, and that means that it has value in the academic ecosystem; and that is kind of missing for a lot of the digital resources that we produce. The idea of the journal was to cover that aspect and then together with a colleague I’m curating a number of special issues on tools for scholarly editing. There we have a very broad approach, as you said: anything that can be used in any step of the process can be considered an editing tool. For example, methods for linguistic analysis are not considered, strictly speaking, tools for digital editing, but they can be part of the process. It really depends on what the focus of your edition is, but definitely the digital media makes it possible to have more approaches to the same object. </p><p>  Let’s start from the beginning: maybe you might want to collect and describe the sources and for that you might need a database to organise the information, any sort of database. And then you might want to transcribe the text and for that you have OCR tools and Handwritten Text Recognition tools, now we are working with Transkribus for example. Of course, it’s different, if you are working with print materials, you have more options. Then I would go through encoding and for that of course XML TEI is the standard. You can annotate the documents further, semantic annotations that you can do in TEI or you have some forms of RDF linked to the text, for example, or let’s say you want to annotate the data linguistically, then you have tools for that. To me, you have this XML TEI transcriptions that can be considered as master files and then you can perform some analysis on them and you can record the data that are the output of the analysis back into the TEI. What kind of analysis you can do, that really depends on the interest you have. For example, you want to compare them using collation, you want to do some other logical analysis, you want to do linguistic analysis, whatever. Then you would need something to publish the data, and you need something for long-term preservation of the data as well. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Maybe just for an example, can we talk a little bit about the digital editing project that you were involved in? </p></sp><sp who="#ES"><speaker>ES</speaker><p>	That’s kind of a special one because of some of the technical choices, but yes. In the case of Gustave Roud, the idea was to publish his complete works and there was (I’m switching between past and present because the project is officially finished, but of course we’re still working on it), there is a print edition and a digital edition, and the main focus of the project is actually the print edition. All the texts are in the print edition and some materials are in the digital edition. It sounded at times like a retro digitisation project., even if both were made at the same time. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	The print edition was the main thing?</p></sp><sp who="#ES"><speaker>ES</speaker><p>	Yes. And then there is another kind of peculiarity to this project. The project was based at the University of Lausanne in Switzerland and there is a national infrastructure called DaSCH, that is the Swiss National Data And Service Centre for the Humanities. When I arrived at the University of Lausanne, they proposed me to use the DaSCH framework and to me it was an interesting challenge because the DaSCH framework is based on RDF, so it is not the most common workflow. TEI can play a role, but it was not all TEI, as it is in most editions. The first phase was modelling all the information around the text, more than the text itself. The data model was organised in an ontology. The data model covers the manuscript descriptions and then the persons, places, the bibliography and all this information around the text. After this first phase, we started to populate the database, we had around 1,200 manuscripts that were described in detail. And then another thing that was very important for this project was the genetic approach. But not in terms of what happens in the single document: for example, phenomenon of rewriting, of substitution and the like. But more the genetic relationship between the documents and publications, because this author reuses a lot his own writings, so he would, for example publish an article, a poem in a literary journal, and then reuses that poem in a collection while mixing up with others writings. There was a lot of reuse and we wanted to study that reuse, to map it. One of the things that took a lot of time was modelling the genetic relationship between the documents and the publications. And in terms of the text, the texts are encoded in TEI and then to import them into the DaSCH framework we had to create a mapping between the XML structure and the RDF ontology, there was this additional step. So then everything was in the database and then we developed a customized web application for the presentation of the data, but the data are also available through a generic web app which works for all the projects and the data stored within this DaSCH platform. The project website is not public yet, it will be in spring 2023, after the print edition will be out as well, and we are also still working a bit on it.</p><p>  Something I found quite interesting was the collaboration with designers for producing data visualisations. The genetic relationships between the documents and between the documents in the publication really created some complicated networks and we were thinking of how to display and present those. Of course we have lists, but we also wanted a more graphic way to display that. I had previous experiences working with some colleagues at the DensityDesign Lab, which is based at the Politecnico in Milan, and they have also worked with other scholarly editions and other scholarly projects and so that was very interesting. The most interesting part about that was probably the workflow itself, how they proposed us to work: we needed to explain them what we were talking about, and for that we used interviews; they would interview the different project members and then they proposed us different metaphors that would guide their design efforts. We choose together one metaphor to represent networks. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	You were also involved with a lot of training in DiXiT and just as one question, I’d like to know how can we better train people to engage with digital editing? Or do you think we need to train them better? What are you experiences in terms of training?</p></sp><sp who="#ES"><speaker>ES</speaker><p>	In terms of training, if there is one thing, I think, that’s important is again the centrality of data. Think about what you’re doing in terms of data: that’s a little thing, but if you switch your mentality about that, it will help a lot also when it comes to digital scholarly editing. Because people often say ‘I don’t have data, I have a text’, so when you talk about data management, data preservation, data curation it does not make sense; but if you start thinking about data, that data should be curated and preserved, etc., that makes all the rest much easier, I think. And also, there is always this comparison whether digital editions are better than print edition or if there is really an improvement of the scientific result: in the training, I don’t like to stress the idea that digital editions are always better. On the contrary, I tend to think that the scientific part is important and that you have different means to achieve what you want and digital is one of those. I prefer to have some sort of continuity, also because most of the training that we offered were to beginners and it’s much better to have some continuity with their background. They will be more open to new things if you don’t tell them whatever you have done so far is not good...</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	That would have been my next question. What is generally the attitude of people towards digital editions, especially in training? </p></sp><sp who="#ES"><speaker>ES</speaker><p>	I don’t know. People say young people are open to digital, but it’s not true. I think young researchers are so concerned about their own career and I totally understand that, that what they need sometimes is just a book and they don't have the time or sometimes the flexibility to think about anything else. So, I would not say that being young researchers, young in the sense of early-stage researchers, means being open to digital scholarship. Sometimes, but not always, it’s kind of the contrary. </p></sp></body></text></TEI>