<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Alyssa Arbuckle</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on January 26th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_AA.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>ALYSSA ARBUCKLE is the Associate Director of the Electronic Textual Cultures Lab at the University of Victoria, Canada, where she is Operational Lead for the Implementing New Knowledge Environments Partnership and a co-facilitator of its Connection cluster. With her colleagues Randa El Khatib and Ray Siemens she is a Co-Director of the Digital Humanities Summer Institute. Alyssa holds an interdisciplinary PhD from the University of Victoria; her dissertation focused on open social scholarship and its implementation.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	The terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing, what do they mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	For me, a scholarly edition is really an edition of anything that a scholar or a group of scholars have taken interest in and have decided that they’re going to bring their own expertise to bear on; that they’re going to shape it and present it from their own theoretical frameworks.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And so in that context, what do you feel that digital editions do well and what might be done better?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	I would say first and foremost digital editions have an access possibility that a lot of print editions don’t have. That is for a number of reasons, but not least of all because a lot of scholarly editions are not picked up by libraries in the same way that a monograph is. So when you have a monograph that is from a scholar who might be pretty well known and has a vast network, that network will go to their libraries and say ‘hey we really need this research, we really need this monograph.’ In my experience this happens a lot less with scholarly editions. So if you are only doing a print run of a scholarly edition you’re really having to rely on getting it out in the world at very specialised conferences, or having a publisher who is very, very, very good at getting this book in front of people, or in yourself doing that leg work and really promoting it. When you’re able to create a digital scholarly edition, if it’s done well, then we should have a much higher potential access level so it can circulate among many more readers—not just those who are intimately connected with the field or with a set of certain scholars. That would be the number one thing for me: access and ideally open access. I think the second thing would be mutability. We really saw this working on A Social Edition of the Devonshire Manuscript a decade ago, which is a Wikibooks edition of the Devonshire Manuscript. I should say this was Ray Siemens’s brainchild and I was brought on at a very junior point in my career, but I’m happy to speak about it from my own experience on the project. Changes can be made over time and in our experience changes could be made by whoever wanted to, by lots of different people. So it opened it up in a way that a print edition just can’t because once you hit that print button it’s done and it’s out there and the object is no longer changeable.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mention access and openness quite a bit, and you have obviously written quite extensively on the topic of open scholarship, I wonder if you could explain a little bit what these terms mean?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	Absolutely. First of all, I would say this is my definition and a lot of people have different definitions. But to me, open scholarship is the umbrella of open access, open knowledge, open data, and open education. It’s sort of this broad term that encompasses a more open way of creating and sharing and remixing knowledge. Where our Implementing New Knowledge Environments (INKE) Research Group takes this is one step beyond to what we call open social scholarship. Our understanding of that is, ok, open scholarship is great and open scholarship is important, but what happens when we purposefully create, share, and collaborate on knowledge products in ways that really forefront public engagement, that forefront working in different disciplines, that forefront working with a lot of different people regardless of their relationship to the university or their institutional status?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Could you speak about that in the context of digital editing and publishing, specifically in relation to the social edition, and how you’ve put your ideas into practice in the Devonshire Manuscript project?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	When we were working on A Social Edition of the Devonshire Manuscript, the theoretical framework for it is this understanding that specialised research and academic knowledge should not just stay in the university and it shouldn’t be cloistered in the university. That we need to undo this learning and this assumption that the work we do as humanities researchers is only interesting to ourselves and that other people don’t care about it, aren’t interested, that it’s our little strange area of interest. What we found with the Devonshire manuscript—which is, in a sense, a very esoteric text, it’s a 16th century verse miscellany from Henry VIII’s court—but what happened was right around the time we were releasing it on Wikibooks the Tudor mini-series came out. So all of a sudden there was this kind of flurry of interest in everything Tudor and that included the Devonshire manuscript because the Devonshire manuscript had some of the same characters from The Tudors who are writing poetry and sharing poetry in this manuscript. So we were able to, by being on a platform like Wikibooks, have people from all over the place engage with the edition and that worked in a lot of different ways: sometimes that was just reading it and then talking to us on Twitter, sometimes it was sourcing images to be included in the book, and sometimes it was offering edits and commentary. We saw this really vast array of interaction with the book that we really wouldn’t have seen if it was just a print book, we wouldn’t have known that was happening and it also wouldn’t have been in these spaces like Wikipedia and Twitter where there are lots of people who aren’t necessarily academics. One of the people we interacted with the most was a massage therapist from Florida and she just loved the Tudors so much and was so passionate and, to her, got to engage in this world in a way that in her day-to-day life she didn’t really have access to. To us that’s sort of the beauty of the social edition, it is engaging with people and circulating knowledge in a way that we wouldn’t be doing if we were only working in a more conventional modality. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What would you say, generally, is the value in social knowledge?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	That’s such a good question and I would say that objectively, yes, there are things that just happen with social knowledge creation: there is an increased circulation of our output, we are able to tap into a crowd. Those things are important, but to me are less important than what I find really interesting and fascinating, which is what happens when we create knowledge with lots of different people? What happens when we stop thinking of ourselves as being in these enclosed spaces and these dedicated arenas where we are only talking to other academics? What happens when we start to do something a little bit broader? And what can be created and what can be made in those spaces that are less bounded by the rigidity of the academic institution? That’s where my interest really is; it’s in the creative possibility. Social knowledge is also valuable from a knowledge as a public good framework; I think access to knowledge is incredibly important for everyone and access to vetted knowledge and access to real information is so core at this fraught moment in our own history.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is there an important political dimension to this practice? Should open scholarship not just be the norm or are there pragmatic barriers that are difficult to overcome?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	There are definitely some challenges. I would say that in a sense we’re our own worst enemies because we have created this kind of calcified academic system that has increasingly become so neo-liberalised that we are really depending on metrics in order to gauge what good work is. It’s like, ok, valuable work is work that has been put in this many libraries or downloaded this many times or cited this many times and we’ve really fallen into this trap of measuring things and then using those measurement as the only ways to advance a career—and not only to advance a career, but to keep a career. I think that this really challenging, bureaucratic system that we’ve set up has gotten in the way of us doing more interesting and more creative things. For instance, with the Devonshire manuscript we didn’t have two hundred and fifty people on the site everyday, but we had a small group of people who we really engaged with. I don’t want to say we made a difference to their life or anything like that but I will say we did have true relationship building going on and true community engagement going on, but that’s not measurable and that’s not in someone’s tenure and promotion dossier. So, I think that’s a big barrier to open scholarship: that it’s not rewarded in the same way and it doesn’t fit as well in the hamster wheel of tenure and promotion that those who are on the faculty route are chasing. I think that’s a challenge for open scholarship. </p><p>The open scholarship movement itself is also doing a lot of self-reflection right now about what, thirty years into this, the outcomes have been and how in some ways open scholarship and open access have reified a very western system. With all of this academic infrastructure being open, we’re seeing the same research becoming very dominant and that is primarily research that is written in English. So right now, the open scholarship movement/open access movement is looking at itself and saying ok, how do we develop further? How do we evolve as a movement and ensure that open access to knowledge means open access to everyone’s knowledge, not just open access to knowledge that has been shared in English and published in Europe, North America, South America, or Australia?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What are the tools and platforms that support open scholarship and social editions and the kinds of practices that you’re speaking about?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	Social editions are so interesting. One of the things that we did with the Devonshire manuscript, for instance, is develop a few different iterations. We had a static website, we worked with Iter press but found that, at the end of the day, we had to be in a space where non-academics were in order to meet our goals of connecting with other people. We realised that if we made just a stand-alone website and said ‘hey everybody come join us over here’ it just wasn’t going to happen. That’s a problem for some other reasons, as well, not least of all because the Wikipedia universe is not always a pleasant universe to be in and it’s not always pleasant for marginalized groups. It was great in a lot of ways, it was challenging in other ways. </p><p>I’m really buoyed by where open publishing software is now. For example, Manifold is doing quite interesting things. Of course right now they’re not really focusing on editions, they’re focusing on monographs, and so I think it would be interesting to see if there was a broadening out of these open monograph publishers into open edition publishers. I think that will really depend on scholarly editors themselves rallying for that, asking for that, wanting that—wanting to create open digital editions rather than these more conventional… or, not rather but perhaps in addition to the more conventional editions.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Thank you. I know you’re currently Associate Director of the Electronic Textual Cultures Lab and one of the leads on the Implementing New Knowledge Environments Partnership; I wonder if you could tell me about your work on these initiatives?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	Yes, absolutely. Ironically, as I say ‘wow, we really need to have some open digital infrastructure for digital editions’, one of the things we’re working on at INKE is starting something called the Open Scholarship Press. We’re wading into the digital publishing world but we haven’t really thought about editions in that context, and so that’s just showing me my own blind spot in not thinking of digital editions as something else that we should be involved with. I’ll think about that a little bit. </p><p>We have also been working on something called the Canadian Humanities and Social Sciences Commons which is a national scale research commons for Humanities and Social Sciences researchers in Canada. We are very much working with the Humanities Commons model, who we are partnered with, but in a different legal context. We have been working on another project called the Open Scholarship Policy Observatory which is a website where we track, aggregate, and comment on policy developments on open scholarship around the world. A few years ago we also founded and have been working with colleagues on something called the Canadian-Australian Partnership for Open Scholarship, which is a group of scholars in Canada and a group of scholars and librarians and technologists in Australia trying to work together to develop open scholarship more in each of our respective locales. At the lab we are gearing up to run the Digital Humanities Summer Institute for the 22nd year and of course there’s a lot of challenges with the pandemic. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s interesting that you draw a distinction between editions and monographs. From a technical infrastructure perspective, do you think there is a difference?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	From a brute technical perspective I would say no, they’re both large form, they’re both, at the end of the day, a longform text file with potentially some images here and there. But I don’t really see a difference there… it really depends on the edition, right? And it depends on the style. But there might even be more possibilities when you look into open textbook creation—something like Pressbooks, for instance. I don’t know if you’re familiar with Pressbooks?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	No.</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	Basically it’s like a WordPress overlay that pumps out open textbooks. We have something called BCcampus here in British Columbia (Canada), which is a technology group for the core universities in BC. They have really supported this as part of their open education push. It’s a plug and play system for creating text books, something that could be adapted for editions really easily because that will have your sidebars, all of the layout changes that you might be looking for in an edition that you might not want in a monograph. I guess that’s horribly reductive of me, but I don’t think that would be that different.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Thank you. You mentioned the Digital Humanities Summer Institute; one of the popular topics across DHSI workshops would be digital editions, TEI, and other tools and practices that go into building editions of all sorts. I wonder if you have any perspectives on the current pedagogical situations in this field? Do you think that digital editions are accessible from the perspective of learners who might not know anything about digital humanities but are interested in building a digital edition? Do you think that people without advanced technical skills are suitably supported by the digital humanities community and its resources?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	That’s such a great question and I’m afraid I’m not super plugged in to the TEI community. I respect it from afar but am not really deep into it. I could really only speak from the DHSI perspective which is that we’ve been working with Jennifer Stertzer and Cathy Moran Hajo for years now and they’ve been offering a very popular course on designing a digital edition, but I don’t really know what’s available beyond that?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, magic wand scenario, if I gave you unlimited resources, technologies both real and imagined, what would the future of digital editing and publishing look like to you?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	Well first of all, thank you so much for that gift of unlimited resources. I think that ideally we would be living in a linked open data universe and so anything that we created, any object or artifact or unit that we created would be linked in a findable, searchable, comprehensible, and contextual way to all of the other information sources that we have. I know, for instance, that here in Canada there is a funded project called LINCS which Susan Brown directs and Kim Martin is very involved in and they have been working on this and pushing for this for so long. But it takes a whole other level of encoding that just hasn’t taken off universally yet and so in my future world, my future magic world, if we were able to create things that were all robustly interconnected, searchable, and with context attached to each unit within a larger edition, I think that would be really incredible.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think we might ever feasibly get there? Is that dream of the endless link, an interconnected data universe, really possible?</p></sp><sp who="#AA"><speaker>AA</speaker><p>	I think that it could be possible for what we create now and in future. I don’t know how it would happen retroactively unless people were very, very invested in a project; I don’t see them going backwards and re-encoding projects in order to be more integrated in these systems moving forward, if that makes sense? So yes, I think we’ll get there, and this is how it goes with standards right? We develop standards and then from that point forward everything is more standardised and everything is better and then we develop more standards and from that point forward things are standardised anew; but I think we very rarely go back and update our projects. And sometimes we can’t, right? Sometimes the encoding that we were using or the platform we were using or the software we were using doesn’t allow us to bring these old projects into a standardised and a more useful format. So I think we could get partway there.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>