<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Alice Bell</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on February 17th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_AB.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>ALICE BELL is a Professor in English language and literature at Sheffield Hallam University (UK). Her research specialisms are cognitive stylistics (including empirical approaches), narratology, and digital fiction. Throughout her work, she develops systematic approaches for the analysis of (mostly digital) texts, examines interactivity and immersion in digital literary environments, considers how digital technologies affect fiction and fictionality, investigates how readers cognitively process digital fiction, and opens up digital fiction to new and established audiences. She has led numerous projects that have expanded the audience reach of, increased cultural participation in, and influenced professional practice around digital fiction. This includes the AHRC-funded Reading Digital Fiction project (AH/K004174/1) which comprised a series of public engagement workshops, exhibitions, and reading groups; and the Digital Fiction Curios project (with One to One Development Trust/Dreaming Methods) which resulted in an interactive archive in which digital fiction originally published in Adobe Flash software, now rendered technologically obsolete, is preserved and reimagined in Virtual Reality. Her publications include The Possible Worlds of Hypertext Fiction (Palgrave 2010), Digital Fiction and the Unnatural (with Astrid Ensslin, Ohio State Univ Press, 2021), and Reading Digital Fiction: Narrative, Cognition, Mediality (with Ensslin, Routledge, forthcoming).</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	I feel like I’m relatively new to this really and when I think about what that kind of work that I’ve done, I mean the Curios Project was my first foray into that really. I’m just trying to think, was it? Yeah and I suppose I hadn’t sort of framed it in that way as a digital scholarly edition because we, you know, we saw it as a preservation project, a kind of curiosity shop, as a small kind of version of a museum collection so… but then I had this invitation, you said you wanted to talk to me about this and I thought, ok, I’ll think about that some more and yeah I can see actually how this is a version of a scholarly edition in so far as you’re sort of bringing something to the fore and you’re framing it with all of this paratextual material of, you know, where has this come from, how can we understand it, what’s its heritage, those kind of things so that was very refreshing to me to think of it in that way. So thank you James for helping me to kind of think about it in those terms because I hadn’t thought of it as a scholarly edition, I mean maybe partly that is because of the wider remit of that project as well in that, you know, primarily we really wanted that to be something that brought in… save the work right, so we wanted to save the work which was about to become obsolete really that was very important but we really wanted it to also engage new audiences and open it up a little bit so that people who weren’t necessarily aware of those works in the first place could also use that resource because of course I know of that work because I’ve been researching that work and when it disappeared, I can probably find other ways of accessing it because I’m in that community, that scholarly community but you know if you’re not it’s quite an intimidating, potentially, area to move into isn’t it, it’s like you don’t even know it exists so how do you know where to find it. So maybe that’s why I’d not seen it in that way but you know of course we want it to be a scholarly resource but we’d also really thought a lot about how it could be an engaging resource for the public more widely so I think a lot of my attention was also on that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	For future readers who might not be familiar with the concept of digital fiction and the Curios project, would you mind just giving a summary of what they are and how they relate to each other?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	Yeah ok, so yeah, so digital fiction is fiction that’s born digital so it’s written and read from a computer of some kind, it might be a PC, a tablet, smartphone and it can include, I mean it’s written in all sorts of software as well so your hypertext fiction which is produced on CD-ROM, you could get hypertext fiction online, virtual reality fiction is a new, relatively recent thing, app fiction on your phone and the Curios was developed because a lot of early hypertext fiction online or digital fiction online was made in Adobe Flash and this was a cool software because it really allowed people to produce quite highly interactive and really aesthetically rich stuff relatively easily and so a lot of digital fiction in the ‘90’s and 2000’s was made in Flash. And then in December 2020, Adobe removed support for Flash from all browsers and basically you can’t access Flash content now unless you find an alternative way of doing that so loads of digital fiction made in Flash just completely disappeared off the web and this is like… ‘What!’, ‘Oh my goodness!’ It’s a complete disaster as far as I’m concerned and it’s like, it’s gone, how do we get hold of it again! And I was working with One to One Development and Dreaming Methods on a previous project and we’ve worked together since 2014 in various projects, exhibitions and such and so I was really pleased when they invited me onboard onto this Curios project which is designed to save Flash work and it started with three of Dreaming Method’s seminal pieces and saving those in this amazing immersive space which is designed to look like a curiosity shop where you enter through… its rendered in virtual reality so you put the virtual reality headset on and you walk through this amazing ‘olde curiosity shop’ and you can pick up objects that relate to the works but you can actually access the works, you can access the Flash works in that space so it provides access to them but the idea is that they’re very kind of immersive space in itself so that the access to the Flash work is as interesting as the Flash work itself and within that I provide some context to the work, I analyse what those works are about and explain to readers how the structure works, how the form works, you know, what they mean in a literary way. So that’s what the Curios is, sorry I shouldn’t have assumed.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Why a curiosity shop?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	Yeah, yeah, we talked a lot about that you know actually because the original idea was for us to have a museum right and we have actually put in a funding application to have a much bigger museum but this was going to be a smaller piece, we got some funding from Sheffield Hallam’s impact acceleration account scheme and it was a modest amount so in some ways that restricts the scope of it but yeah I guess we could have still made it like another kind of concept but I think we really wanted to get this idea of a curiosity shop as something that holds old and interesting objects and obviously something that is produced in the ‘90’s or the 2000’s to me is not old, I don’t consider that to be old although it is a relative concept, time, but you know in the history of fiction that is kind of some of the earliest stuff so we felt that that could kind of tie in with this idea of olde worlde kind of the olde worlde concept but not only that also this idea that it could be placed in that concept within that concept and you could pick up objects around the shop which related to the work so there’s a sense in which you could kind of have a dig around and I guess that’s to do with archives and yeah kind of collections of materials, that seems really important, not just… I mean it’s playful in a way but it relates to this idea of archiving work and what that has traditionally looked like and how we can make that intersect with what is a more modern technology, a digital technology as compared with the non-digital as the very material kind of space. So yeah, that would be my perspective on it, I think Andy probably will have talked about his own but I do remember that conversation very clearly and we spent ages trying to think what do we call it, do we call it a Curiosity Shop and what do we call it and we came up with the Curios and we were quite pleased with that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And was it always the intention to set the project in a place, as opposed to just to offering an emulation of the Flash works?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	Yeah, definitely! It absolutely had to be in a place and for me this is kind of a really important aspect of it. I was talking about this being something where we wanted to open it up to other audiences, this should not just be like an academic resource although that is an important part of it but I think you know if you are not familiar with digital fiction that could be quite a baffling area to go into like where do I start, right and I think it’s very useful in those instances in life where we don’t know much about it is like, ok, where can I find this stuff out, where is it all brought together, you know, a museum is somewhere you can go and you’re taken on a sort of narrative around something where somebody has put together collections and also they’re explaining along the way what these things are so you know in a museum or a gallery you get the text what are they called, text walls or… They have a name, information boards which are the texts next to the piece of art and it explains it for you and I think that is really important because it’s kind of explaining why is this piece of fiction important, what’s its heritage, what is it about and it’s also picking pieces and placing them in particular spaces. I think, you know, I can use an emulator because I know where to find it but that’s another barrier, that’s another step, a potential barrier to accessing the work whereas if you put it in the museum or curiosity shop or something that seems to me to be more of a gateway to somebody going in to it because they don’t have to mess about with having to emulate something. I do think there is absolutely a place for emulators, I’m so grateful that they are there, I’m so grateful that people are cataloguing stuff and putting together these places where I can go and making huge, very extensive, very thorough lists and that’s so, so important. I think this is not competing with that, this is just an alternative to that which has a potentially different audience as well, so that space is so important.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	There’s a real sense of engagement here. You mentioned that you see awareness as being a major part of the project; do you see this form of virtual curiosity shop, or indeed, virtual museum, as a future publishing practice?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	I mean, yeah, why not? Absolutely why not? I guess… and I’m thinking to… we already have you know electronic literature collections where anthologies of work where things are collected together and I think again that they’re fantastic for bringing something into one place where there’s some context to them and you can search them according to what criteria you are interested in, you know, I suppose the Curios and the museums that might come from that, I like that but they are more of a three dimensional space which might have other kind of paratextual material in them, I suppose in terms of whether this could be another production practice, yeah why not, that would be amazing. What I’ve been thinking about recently and this is not my academic area of expertise but that the idea of preserving things in a technology, at what point then does that then become difficult because that technology becomes obsolete and then where do you go and where do you stop and that’s not, as I say, that’s not my academic area of expertise but I’ve been working with some people who do know about that stuff and I suppose that’s just something that we have to think about because then the museum becomes lost if we don’t future proof that and then where do we go?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I was going to ask you about that because Curios is obviously an important record of cultural and literary heritage, but it’s also a creative work in itself; how do you now preserve this preservation project?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	Yeah. I’m not sure.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I mean, in the field of digital fiction there are so few projects like this. Not even like this, there are so few preservation projects in general. Are we in danger of losing our digital literary heritage? Have we already lost much of it?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	I mean I wouldn’t say, maybe I have a different perspective on this but I wouldn’t say there are so few projects. I feel like Dene Grigar’s work is like so amazing, so important, so significant so you know she’s been working on this for so long I just feel like there is a lot of preservation, you know, preservation of hardware so certain works can be accessed, it’s really extensive databases, translating Flash into other software so that can be accessed. I mean, for me, I don’t… maybe I’m being naive about the scale of it but I already feel that there is a significant amount of that done and she, for me, has pioneered that tirelessly and made us all very aware, I say all, us, people working in the field of digital fiction and electronic literature more widely that this is a problem like we need to be aware of this and I’m so grateful to her for bringing that to my attention. So, I think there is now a community around that, of digital preservation, I think it is so important because otherwise it's lost and then it’s gone and then where are we, you know so I think the risk is there, fortunately people are working on that now and hopefully there will be more of that work on there. Yeah, I’m just very interested in this idea of future proofing things and where that goes and how that happens but I guess this is where we have to collaborate as well, there has to be huge collaboration between people who are experts in digital fiction like me and I do understand digital technology to a certain extent but I’m not a software engineer and I’m not somebody who can build virtual reality, you know, like Andy can, we’re collaborating because we’re bringing different things together and I just think that has to be the way really. So, I’m quite hopeful, I’m quite positive, maybe I’m being over optimistic.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That sense of collaboration is reassuring. Who do you think is ultimately responsible for these things, is it publishers, is it artists, is it scholars, institutions?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	Yeah, that’s a good question, who is responsible? Yeah, I mean, I guess we all have some responsibility for that but I think, for me, the artists have to be involved, it’s there work, right and I wouldn’t dream of trying to preserve somebody’s work without being in contact with them and talking to them about how we would like to do that. I mean that’s not always possible to do, sometimes people aren’t around or… but where possible I would think it’s vital to include authors in that conversation, it’s their work, it’s their vision so I think they have to be central to it and then there has to be a trust around that, right, I would have to have conversations with those people and we would have to trust each other to be able to… for them to be able to trust me that I’m going to do it sensitively and I’m going to listen to them. So, I think scholars have a big role to play in this but I also wouldn’t want to see it as me kind of going in and cannibalising their stuff and I don’t see it as that kind of endeavour I see it as their work… I would want their work to be preserved, right but maybe people don’t want their work to be preserved so I think it has to be a wider conversation really.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	One of the things that is interesting about Curios is that it illustrates one of the major challenges faced by digital creative practices. With print books you’re dealing with a consistent medium, whereas preserving digital fiction requires engagement with such a broad range of forms and media. Acts of preservation are always going to be outdone by the fact that technology develops at such an exponential rate. From an expressive perspective, this is wonderful because we get to experience so many different types of works that have been created using different media technologies and systems and platforms, but that is just inherently anti-preservation. Curios is an exemplar of how you can preserve Flash pieces in a more current platform to which they don’t automatically port, but not everyone can develop a Unity project like this, and eventually, maybe even in the not-too-distant future, Unity will go the same way as Flash. The hallmark of preservation of any sort is consistency in its guideline and models, practices that can be replicated across institutions and by whoever it is who wants to do the work of preservation. Is that just not possible in this space? Do we need to accept that, because everyone is using different digital technologies to produce different kinds of digital writing and art, we are going to lose a lot?  </p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	Yeah, I mean I don’t know, it’s a conundrum isn’t it; I don’t know. I mean again from my perspective I think that is something that people work on a lot you know and I’ve been collaborating with some people who work in preservation and this is current debate, you know the British Library have this huge project about… what is it called, what is the title of it, the Emerging Formats project is a huge project about how do you archive and preserve complex digital objects, and there’s international conferences all over the world trying to figure this stuff out, I don’t know, it freaks me out that I can’t sometimes access an app anymore because my iPhone is updated too much that I can’t open it like even that and I’m conscious that I’m paranoid about losing access to stuff, I constantly screen shot stuff, I screen record certain things just to make sure I have access to it. So I think it’s a massive issue, technologically is it possible, I don’t know, I guess that’s were expertise and preservation research and you know talented software engineers and people like Andy, he’s amazing at figuring these things out and I guess that’s where the collaboration comes in, I don’t know. I don’t like to think it is too complicated, it’s going to be doable but it’s like, how?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s interesting that you screen record to ensure access, that’s very much the methodology that Dene and Stuart employed with Pathfinders; they accepted that they can’t recreate pieces of digital fiction, so instead they captured the experience of the works by recoding authorial traversals, reading traversals, and so forth. Is that possibly the best methodology that we have? Should we let go of any ambitions of allowing people to actually experience works for themselves, but in doing so, at least we can preserve a sense of what a piece of fiction was, that it was there, what it was all about?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	Yeah, definitely, and again I really admire that project and the foresight that like we need to capture this, yeah, I mean obviously you don’t get… if you’re screen recording you’re not getting that experiential activity, even haptics, you’re not getting that but it’s better than getting nothing you know and for me but then this is maybe the difference in the pathfinder methodology and why I do it, I have experienced these interactive things as they are so I’ve already experienced them in their original form and then if I screen record stuff that I’m worried is going to go, I can remember at least what it felt like to do that originally whereas I guess if you’re coming to a recording and you haven’t had that original experience with that you haven’t had that and that’s missing but then at least you get a very good sense of what it was like to interact with that but yeah I’m paranoid about these things disappearing.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	One last question, if I gave you unlimited resources, technologies both real and imagined, what would the future Curios look like?</p></sp><sp who="#AB"><speaker>AB</speaker><p>	It would be a museum; a big, huge, three-dimensional museum that you could access in virtual reality, you could also access it desktop and on phone like you could access it on any device so it wouldn’t have to be a VR piece I mean the Curios you can get on desktop for example but the immersive experience in VR is a different experience. So it would be a huge museum and there would be a collection of you know, story space, hypertext stuff on CD-ROM that you could put onto a machine, there would be Flash stuff, there would be… moving forward there would be, I don’t know, other kinds of digital fiction, narratively driven video games, there would maybe be bits of VR fiction, app fiction you know the range, this beautiful museum, aesthetically really pleasing and within that there would be support and resources around that so you might have authors talking about their work there would be like those text panels that I was talking about which kind of explain that work or somebody who researches this kind of stuff unpicking it and seeing how they see how this work works and also some sense of a trajectory in terms of historical development, how authors have responded to new technology and experimented and always played around with different tools, that’s why it’s so rich, it’s when new technology comes out and somebody starts playing around with it and making these really amazing pieces it’s just sort of really capture that energy of the field and the community and the people that make it and the diversity of work. I’ve curated exhibitions on digital fiction before and tried in the real world if you like, in a gallery and I really enjoyed the aspect of trying to trace the lineage and seeing people interacting with the stuff and really getting to understand it, you know, it was a privilege, it was such a pleasure to do it and I’d love to see that rendered in a big visual space that people could explore, that would be amazing, I would love to see that.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>