<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Bartlomiej Szleszynski</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan, UCC		 on January 21st, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_BS.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>BARTLOMIEJ SZLESZYNSKI is a professor in the Institute of Literary Research, Polish Academy of Sciences, head of New Panorama of Polish Literature and deputy director of Digital Humanities Centre.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#BS"><speaker>BS</speaker><p>	In Poland when we talk about the scholarly edition, it is a set of practices that we do to create the best version of a text. My first field of involvement in the scholarship business was the second half of the 19th Century so I know a lot about editions from the 19th Century and it is actually more on the side of scholarly practices not editing, making text available for broader audiences, I’ll get to this but of course it is connected. In New Panorama of Polish Literature we have two sites, one is for something we call digital collections, scholarly collections which  you might say  are digital monographs and it is for publishing results of research in the digital, modern, audio-visual way Surely there is also the aspect of popularisation there but most of those collections are serious research projects, popularisation isn’t their main goal although we are aware of that New Panorama of Polish Literature starts to be used in schools. For example quite often we can see when school starts the numbers of users are going high and of course during the lockdown even higher because it was quite important then to get professional knowledge from the internet. And there are not so many sites which give such scholarly knowledge with the sign of quality This is one aspect of what we do and the second one is the platform for digital scholarly editions in TEI standard and this is much more for professionals only. Of course when we edit some texts that are quite popular it could be used by a wider audience but that’s not the main goal and most of our cases we work on right now are for professionals. So we are using TEI Markup and making texts available for researchers with different tools on this platform to perform their work better, to search. So that’s generally what we do in that digital environment and how it is treated. There’s of course a connection between this scholarly editing, setting this best version of text and popular editing for example, the problem is that there are many texts available, novels for example, Polish novels from the 19th Century available on the internet but very often they are not in the best version. It’s of course for those who publish it there is a degree of cautiousness for responsibility of publishing the right or best version of a text. Of course, that is connected with legal problems because you cannot publish openly something that was just published by some publishing house, they wouldn’t allow it of course but that’s to make an example. This is very famous Polish 19th Century novel ‘The Doll’ by Boleslaw Prus (probably the most important Polish novelist of the 19th Century) and it had many editions but most of the versions that are in the digital environment are the editions from 1920’s and it is far from best - there are a lot of things that were found after then and in the 19th Century there was censorship involved so for creating the best version the editors had to check the censorship archives because usually we want to publish the best text that was intentionally written by the writer but when censorship is involved it is not his intention to publish this version because he is just allowed to do something with the text, so that’s the problem. What we are trying to do is to make people aware that there are better versions of editions and worse. And of course, when we work with scholarly editions, we assume that later when someone will be making popular edition of this novel for example that it will be based on the latest scholarly edition but it’s quite complicated. Of course, there is also one factor that is quite important in our work, in how we make those editions - that is the problem of evaluation, Probably many European countries have quite similar problem because when we talk to other editors, they also have problems with that. Basically scholarly digital editions are not in an evaluation system so to have points, you know, you can not do only digital editions. That’s why we usually do it in parallel, we create book in paper and we create digital editions and it has also other advantages because usually the printed book is for slightly different audience, it has quite a different purpose. It is the same with those collections on the first platform for example when we had a project Postmodern Sienkiewicz (Sienkiewicz is the other famous Polish novelist from the 19th Century) for us this collection was the most important one when we have this project but to have points for the publication and for the authors to have points for the involvement we needed to make a classic book (it is not classic because it is only in PDF, in digital form but it needed to be registered by the Ministry). We are planning on working on advocacy on both those fields to make digital monographs also available for evaluation and also digital edition to be evaluated but it’s… I’m afraid that there is a long way to go to make it happen.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, when I go to ‘nplp.pl’ and I see all the editions, these are all the scholarly editions that you created?</p></sp><sp who="#BS"><speaker>BS</speaker><p>	These are the digital collections.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Okay, these are the collections...</p></sp><sp who="#BS"><speaker>BS</speaker><p>	Not all of them are in English but three of them are and these are kind of monographs this is Postmoderrn Sienkiewicz I told you about - it is probably most rich collection, they are probably more for publication but there is the other side...</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Oh yes, I see…</p></sp><sp who="#BS"><speaker>BS</speaker><p>	I put it in the chat the second one, the TEI.NPLP.PL this is the platform for digital editions for now it’s only in Polish.</p><p>	Some of them we have just started but they are the different corpora of the text. We started working on this matter of digital scholarly editions in TEI in 2015. We have editions of letters from Polish writers from the second half of the 20th Century. With letters the process is simpler because usually you have one version of a text of course there are some interesting exceptions, but they are exceptions. There was a Polish writer who used to rewrite letters and change them for the audience but generally there is one version of the letter, so you don’t need to have a tool for comparing versions. Then we got funding for the project of editing modern Polish drama and then we had to create this tool for comparing versions and currently we are working also on corpa of Polish novels from the 19th Century. We got also other infrastructural funding and we are working on two very difficult texts one is a Polish drama from the first half of the 19th Century - it is handwritten on the separate pages which are not numbered and also has writing all over this site, so it is complicated, and author also made a lot of changes and so it’s extremely difficult, but such cases are the best for upgrading tools. Because if you can do something very complicated usually you can also do those less complicated things, so we are working on the big upgrade for this. The second corpora are texts from the 16th Century, so this case is also quite complicated because they are in the different version of Polish language, they are handwritten, they have a lot of stuff going on there. We are upgrading our tools almost all of the time and I think what is important is that we are very strongly in literary from We are aware that generally there might be a need, I don’t mean just in Poland but I think generally in Europe for those to make editions for other disciplines like history, philosophy. We worked on the Horizon Project for Digital Editing. Unfortunately, it didn’t get funding - two days ago we received the reduction, anyway the process of working on this proposal showed us that we have quite similar problems or ideas as colleagues from Italy France or UK.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	How does this model work? Who funds it, how do you decide who gets to create a collection, how do you decide who uses your TEI platform?</p></sp><sp who="#BS"><speaker>BS</speaker><p>	Ok so the main thing is as I said we started working on our digital projects in 2014 and that was the moment when not only New Panorama for Polish Literature was created but our Digital Humanities Centre was being organized by Maciej Maryl. So many things happened quite spontaneously because there was an option of funding so we went in such a direction. Most of our collections and editions are funded by ministerial grants. Our model looks like this: someone, usually in our institute but we are open to work with other institutions,  has an idea that he wants to do, I don’t know, an edition of letters - he has a couple of letters, he wants to do it and he also wants to do a digital edition because it is quite important now to also have this digital component of the project. So he contacts us and we talk with them and we evaluate what is to be done, how much it will cost to do this way, if we need to upgrade our tool for that. Then we make this part of the proposal and if the project gets funding our digital part is being done of course in cooperation with the leading scholar of this project. With the Sienkiewicz Postmodern collection I was the leading scholar - it was quite interesting for me because I had everything under control. But usually, we have a partner who is creating content making it the best it can be. We are thinking about creating something like business model that could involve also us making some things for anyone who can come to us and wants to make a digital collection, we can do this collection if he has money or we can just price it and describe it the same as collection but again I think it needs time. We would very much like to work with publishing houses because it would solve the other problem I was talking about -evaluation. The publishing houses would register those editions or those collections as their kind of digital book. As for now our work is financed in 99% from grants from ministerial projects, it isn’t very fortunate for stabilisation of a team Even if project least for example for five years, it’s long but it’s not the same as you have like a job so it’s a bit of struggle to get all of the things going -I think all of us in Europehave come across some of these problems. For example now we have six big projects and frankly speaking it is enough for us, right now the next projects are not needed to get funded but we don’t know what will happen in two years so we need to get the next proposals to have a future. So basically, we are writing proposals all the time, different proposals and for now we have quite good funding and as I told you  at our digital humanities centre we have big project which has the advantage that it’s institutions that get this funding need to sign regular job contracts with people in  so this is the first moment where all of the people in my team have at least a part of you know regular job payment but To be honest I think it is easier to get funding on digital projects or projects that are partly digital than for those that are not.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned the publishing houses, do you think there’s a disconnect between digital editing and publishing?</p></sp><sp who="#BS"><speaker>BS</speaker><p>	We are strongly involved in the operation on the side of open science, and we believe that when something was publicly funded, it should be publicly accessible. But the perspective of publishing houses is a bit different because they usually want to make money on the books they edit so they can’t make it open I believe that, to be honest, when we make a digital edition it isn’t a problem for the sale of books with the edition in paper because I think different people are using different ways of publishing but anyway quite often publishing houses do not allow to publish the text from the book in the digital environment and there is some strange situation when you have the site of the project and there is almost nothing there because all of the content created during the project was in the book and the publishing house says it can’t be published in any form on this side. Of course, we tried to do it differently, we also have quite a specific situation in the Institute of Literary Research of the Polish Academy of Sciences because we have a publishing house inside our institute so we have our own publishing house and it makes many agreements much simpler but I think generally it is quite important to make people realise that most of publicly funded knowledge should be accessible publicly.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I was looking at the site and you said that the key concept underlying this transformation is the so-called museum metaphor, I wonder if you could explain what is meant by that, this idea of the museum metaphor? I mean, I obviously know what a museum is, but have you intentionally structured the project as a museum? What does that mean in digital terms?</p></sp><sp who="#BS"><speaker>BS</speaker><p>	There are several interesting issues for this… when we created this collection Postmodern Sienkiewicz, we knew that we wanted to propose a new form of telling, we use this term - we try to tell scholarly stories in the digital environment. So, the collection has its own narrative you might say and of course it is… it involves many aspects, its quite a new field of scholarly knowledge and it evolves all the time. In our case what is interesting many people from my team are also gamers so we’re into such digital stories also and of course we have Postmodern Sienkiewicz which is… what you can see in this collection and organisers of this system Museum of Sienkiewicz is this Palace he was given by the nation at the beginning of the 20th Century and that you might say very eclectic also you might say that it is really ugly, it is also very interesting because he was given it from the nation, nobody asks if he wants it and nobody asks how it should look, they just created it and fortunate if you like it and he didn’t. The building is interesting and it shows the reception of Sienkiewicz, he was mostly known for his novels from the Polish 17th Century and it is a bit like the distillation of the 17th Century there is a knight over the door and inside of this palace is the Museum of Sienkiewicz and it is interesting because he actually used to live there and many artifacts that were brought to this place by this author so for example when there is in the dining room there is a set of graphics from the One Thousand and One Nights, some of them are, I’d say, very strange, they connect erotica and violence and so it tells something about Sienkiewicz’s taste and what he liked and it also it is connect with a theme of one of the texts that is in this collection, it is about connecting violence and erotica in the novels of Sienkiewicz which is… Sienkiewicz wrote Quo Vadis novel, maybe you know it or heard of it, it is a great example because there are scenes from the Roman arena when the Christians are being killed but there is also an aspect of nudity, beautiful girls that are killed there so this is in many of his novels. I am telling this to show that it is a space of the museum but it is changed by us, created in the digital environment by us to tell the story we wanted to tell, this is quite interesting because lately this museum made this virtual walk so you can compare how it looks there in real life and how our narrative looks. For example, first of all we could move stuff to look better so that modern stuff like chairs we could get rid of them, we got rid of any modern stuff like radiators or such things so this space in real life doesn’t look like that in the museum  For example when we wanted a specific painting to be in a specific place we digitally moved it in this museum from this perspective you can’t see this paining but we switched places to make this digital story better and this… what is interesting also is we made all of stuff that are artifacts very… they are all visible very well, this is not the case with virtual walk where there is light on those graphics some of those things you can’t see at all but we work on that with our photographer and our graphic designer and so this space is based… the story is based on this three rooms in this museum but actually we recreated the space to fit into our narrative. There is some stuff that was not at all in there like the newspaper that is on the table and it’s through this newspaper we go into the article on Sienkiewicz writing for the newspapers so, it is the newspaper that quite probably would have been on this table and probably Sienkiewicz would have read this paper and actually this number of this newspaper because it’s the edition after the death of Boleslaw Prus. So it’s quite interesting, so he probably had this newspaper on this table but it is not there now so we recreated this space to tell this story so it’s I think it is quite interesting because at first they recreated the space for the purpose of the museum and then we recreated this digitally for our narrative. Actually so this… we have this way of telling stories but we try different ways we also quite often use digital maps for example we have one… there are sum maps in those three collections that are in English but we have two collections that are I think interesting from the point of view of cartography or telling those scholarly things differently. The first one is the Atlas of Polish Romantic Period Literature and the basic interface is a map and all the articles/texts are about places and the idea is quite obvious but it is done this way because usually when some scholarly narratives are created about Polish Romantic Literature they are based on people so in this way the map is the space is something that makes the structure you can also think differently about the subject that you’re working with and I think that’s one of the most important collections now we have, it’s only in Polish now but there is high possibility we will get funding on the upgrading this and translating. It is Atlas Lieratury Zaglady which means Atlas of the Holocaust Literature because we also have some very strong holocaust studies team in our institute. It is digitally born project, it is impossible to do in traditional way in paper because the basic idea is connecting places, people and events so the most important are places, we’ve had fifteen memoirs/testimonies/texts created by people in the Warsaw Ghetto and our research team note every part of those memoires with some places mentioned so we made an article about each place for example one street, one specific address and we have some addresses which were mentioned only by one person but there were some addresses that were mentioned by many of them so all of such an article consists of all of the mentions of the parts where this address was mentioned but it’s also linked to every part is also linked to the person and you can see all the things that this person wrote about these places and the period of time. All of those three categories are interconnected so it is a complicated structure which you can not do in the paper book. It’s also quite interesting because it changes the perspective of thinking about this and also it is, I’d say as objective as possible when you work on a project of Holocaust.  We plan to, when we get funding, to make it much bigger so I think we have fifty five more of those memoires to analyse and we’ll also involve Lodz Ghetto which is also a big one. Topography of the Holocaust is quite important and the topography of experience - these are very, very interesting things. Of course when you are talking about Holocaust it is also not very easy mentally to research this but I think this will be, if we get this funding and if we will also be able to make it in English, I think it will be a collection that could be widely used all over the world. When we are on the subject of cartography and topography what’s interesting I think is we in our digital editions in TEI we mark different kinds of entities it’s quite often that we mark people but we also mark places and it’s quite unusual for the Polish editions to take out of places but when we mark them quite naturally we would also like to write something about them and there is much more and quite often this topography of edition or text seems to be very interesting and probably, generally in traditional editions a little tend to explain who are people involved in these letters or… but they not very often explain places that are mentioned, so we are very much into topographical stuff and some of our members of our team and our graphic designer have interest in topography in general. I think this is maybe one of the things I can mention, it’s not connected to editing directly but it is very important for what we do and how we do it actually because from the beginning one of our assumptions was that a professional graphic designer is a member of our team and everything what is done on our platforms but also when we do a poster or a presentation everything is professionally designed by a graphic designer. It is quite unusual for digital humanities for this approach but it helped us to be quite fast with recognisable because people just liked our posters or design we had such moments when people were making photos with our posters not being totally interested in what is on the poster because it is so nice and we had some talks with Michael Pidd about that and he said that usually when they have a project, they don’t have a graphic designer at all because there is someone to make this tool, the programmer, and he is taking care of how it looks but for us it is quite important to actually, if we want to make this audio-visual narrative clear, we need to take care of this visual side and this is very, very important for us.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You seem very conscious of that engagement with the public.</p></sp><sp who="#BS"><speaker>BS</speaker><p>	Right now there is a lot of talk about user experience in digital humanities but even when we started, we were not aware of the term user experience actually, but it was very important for us. If you want to tell a digital story it needs to be told properly because otherwise it doesn’t make any sense - of course there are some users that are going on our site only for specific article about Prus or ‘The Doll’ but I think some of them are going through the collection and into this narrative. We have quite good numbers for users I think there is over ten thousand unique users monthly on our platform. You know - it’s nothing compared to the popular YouTubers but on the other hand it’s I think much more than any scholarly publications in paper. One of our problems is that we have so many projects that there are some things that could be done, even should be done but there is no time or resources to do it. One of the aspects is probably creating some scenarios of lessons that could be done with our collections to make using this platform by teachers easier but it’s not so easy, all of my people are involved in so many projects that we can’t prioritise that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That leads nicely into my final question: if you had unlimited resources, a magic wand situation, say, what would you add to this project that you don’t already have, or even generally, what should digital editions do that they don’t do right now?</p></sp><sp who="#BS"><speaker>BS</speaker><p>	There is a very big need for automatization ,different kinds of automatization. We do all of the stuff manually and our corporas aren’t so big that we could not handle it but when we talk about this European project for digital editions infrastructure the first thing most of people involved wanted was to make some kind of automatized markup. There is I think quite big need for good scanning and OCR. I think there is one important thing about digital editions is that we learn from experience of others. Of course you can have very sophisticated tools, I can think of two great ideas, Becketts edition, - (a case of Beckett is interesting because often French and English versions are parallel) they have a great tool for showing manuscripts and connecting to parts of the manuscripts with the transcription and it’s done very well. This Beckett edition it is behind a paywall, to make it work It’s very difficult to make it to work fast enough when it is open access When we finish this funding, I told you about we’ll probably have lots of tools and I think we’ll have all the tools we need for such editions. I think you know, I can’t think of something that I dream of, you know functionality For me the most important thing in my work and for quality of this work is knowing that all of my team have good funding and stabilised situation because it’s much easier to plan things when you don’t jump from project to project, I think we have quite good tools to do our stuff.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>