<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Luigina Ciolfi</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  Michael Kurzmeier	 on Date: March 15th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_MK_LC.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>LUIGIANA CIOLFI is Professor of Human Computer Interaction in the School of Applied Psychology at University College Cork, Ireland. She researches human experiences and practices around digital technologies, with culture and heritage being one of her domains of expertise. She has worked on several national and international projects exploring the design of interactive technologies for heritage interpretation.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	As an opening question, how do you think the digital has transformed the way in which we engage with culture and cultural materials?</p></sp><sp who="#LC"><speaker>LC</speaker><p>	That’s a huge question, where do I start? Yeah well, I mean I don’t know where to start. I’ve been looking at the digital in relation to culture and cultural experiences for twenty-three, twenty-four years so the digital is not something that just happened last week or last year. It’s been around a while. And I guess there’s no such thing as the digital either in the sense that there is a general trend to introduce more and more digitised elements to various aspects of culture and heritage but of course through the years what we imagine when we say ‘the digital’ has changed significantly. My interest is in the human experience of digital technologies particularly in the context of museums and exhibitions and more recently in relation to heritage more in general also looking at the level of community, grassroots, heritage movements and so on. The digital has changed a lot since I started, so what was imagined to be a suitable digital platform for the museum experience twenty years ago is very, very different now. It has also been affected by some of the fashions in the world of digital innovation, from the mobile to now … We’re talking about AI and virtual reality and all of that, and so our whole vision of what it could be has changed a lot. I think when it comes to engaging with culture and heritage, some things have changed but some things haven’t changed at all. So the things that have changed, I think: we have become more used to thinking of heritage not just as something that lives inside an archive or inside a museum glass box. We’re much more open minded when it comes to thinking about what heritage is, the idea that it can be something that is purely digital, or born digital even, and that engaging with digitised instances of heritage holdings is a valid experience. I think in that sense there has been a lot of growth even in public opinion of what counts as a heritage experience or a cultural experience. Look at the pandemic and the idea that you can attend a concert remotely, does that mean you haven’t been there? I think people might have given you a different answer depending on whether you asked that question five years ago or last week. At the same time, from my point of view, which is very much from the perspective of the public so visitors, people who engage with culture and heritage rather than scholars who maybe work on it. I think the fundamental mode of engagement between people and digital collections/digital resources hasn’t changed very much because it’s still very much ‘this is the information and I give it to you’ in interesting ways, in maybe more entertaining, more complex ways but it’s still very much you are the audience, here’s the experience. So I think there’s been attempts to change that model but it hasn’t quite got there yet and I think in a way the persistence of some models of interaction that were devised at the time when technology and the digital could only do very few things is surprising because technology can do many more things now. So, that’s some general opinions I have on this but I don’t want to talk too much as I said it’s a big question and it could be taken on for days on end.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you so much. Maybe to talk about your work a little bit more because I find that very interesting, so much of your work obviously is focused on human computer interaction in the context of museums and cultural heritage sites and I’d like to know your thoughts on what you feel digital cultural heritage does well and especially what you think is missing from the field or if there is anything missing from the field?</p></sp><sp who="#LC"><speaker>LC</speaker><p>	Human computer interaction is a field in between, so there is a lot of us that specialise in certain domains of application of technology, and culture and heritage is one that I’m looking at but at the same time you can’t ignore other fields that are kind of neighbours to it: from digital humanities to museum studies and exhibition design and heritage studies that shape this course. I’m very much situated in HCI because as I said my focus is very much on the “user” in inverted commas, so very much looking at the perspective of what happens when digital cultural heritage is used as part of some kind of interactive experience that involves the public or is made available in some way to a community that is outside of an institution, outside of heritage professionals let’s say. What I’ve been working on really is thinking of … maybe at the core is this idea of questioning a little bit the model of engagement with heritage from the more didactic one of informal learning  - I tell you about what you should know and you go home and you know a little bit more - to maybe looking at how digital cultural heritage is more flexible, being part of experiences that might question that or make it a little bit open ended. What I find, so there are a few things that I’m missing, although there has been attempts for quite a while. There’s been a huge push to digitising assets. For decades it was about digitising, scanning objects, digitising companion materials from manuscripts, books, resources, all of that to digitising even visitor data that gets captured in various ways. There’s been a few attempts to ‘ok now we digitised all these things; how do we use them?’ ‘What do we do with them?’ I think that is still not quite as developed as I would like. So, there’s a tonne of material that is digitised, that is there but very little that gets done with it besides telling people ‘oh look there’s a digitised version of X and now you can look at it from your computer at home or from, you know, school, if you can’t go to an archive or a museum’. And I think we can be more creative about that, there has been as I said some attempts but not near enough in my view. Making these things that are digitised more alive in a way; and the other thing is … I think it connects to what I was saying earlier in answering your previous question … is that I think maybe there is still a very limited view of how we present heritage and digital heritage to the public that I think we could be more creative, and maybe more subversive about that too. So, I think digital heritage in a way is coded in a way that preserves those structures of interpretation, but maybe could be coded and stored and shared and archived in ways that suggest a little bit more of an openness in terms of what do we use this to get people to think about and respond to. So these are some of the things that I’ve been working on in my own research. Obviously, in the world of HCI we don’t have like the big debates on what is heritage, what should it do? Should it be for people to topple from pedestals like statues of, you know, slave traders in the UK, or should it be something that people identify with because it represents them. Those debates are found in other disciplines, and I find that sometimes in HCI we’re a little bit blind to them so that’s why I also try and follow that because I think it’s core to what interactivity can do. The two things are not separate. So maybe the other thing that’s missing from digital heritage is, in the same way I think HCI is missing some of these other disciplinary debates, maybe digital heritage could do with looking a little bit outside to get maybe some ideas on how to be a bit more innovative or different from what has been done so far. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. When you, because you’re talking about digital cultural heritage, is there specific tools or platforms that you find interesting in that area?</p></sp><sp who="#LC"><speaker>LC</speaker><p>	Not per se. I’ve worked on various projects and looking at different types of heritage, different types of heritage institution, different types of heritage professionals, because they are different to publics and communities that they relate to. There isn’t one that I would kind of go to necessarily. A lot depends on what is the problem to be solved or what is problem to be addressed if not solved. So I’ve kind of looked at a variety of them and helped build some others. I guess, some of the more recent projects I’ve worked on, everything that is in Europeana and its various sub sections has been very, very useful as a model to look at how heritage is digitised, how it’s made available, how to interface with other repositories or any other form of digital heritage knowledge structure that can be designed, and it’s almost become a standard in terms of European heritage to relate to. The digitising, for example, of recent intangible heritage from archiving, you know, the Repeal the 8th Campaign as a kind of a digital heritage holding in the Digital Repository of Ireland, I think that’s a fascinating project in terms of living heritage. So I think it really shows that heritage again is not something that lives in archives from centuries ago and that if it’s digital heritage it’s the past and you have to kind of engage with it, but that it can be very recent past, it can be - you know - the present, it can be anything that people feel it’s of value to them, to society, to their community. So I really like following that work and what’s happening in Ireland with that.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. You have also done work on participatory methodologies an in studying the process of how technology is collaboratively designed. And I wonder if you might share some of the major insights you’ve had over the years working in participatory design and digital cultural heritage.</p></sp><sp who="#LC"><speaker>LC</speaker><p>	Yeah, I’ve done quite a lot of participatory projects and co-design projects, and with different stakeholders too. So sometimes the participatory design is done with the heritage professionals that work in heritage institutions and cultural bodies, sometimes it’s done with visitors or communities that are invested in that heritage. It’s something that I really enjoy because I think it really brings to the fore a lot of, again, some of the things that are a little bit hidden about digital heritage: how people feel about it, why they think it's important besides why the institution thinks it’s important. So, I think it can be a very powerful way to work in terms of re-imagining what cultural heritage can do for our life and for our society in all kinds of terms, from what we remember, but also in terms of how we feel as part of a cohesive community. So some of these meanings come out when you’re trying to create something new and you give people equal voice together with the people who are specialised in technology. It’s something that requires time because, as I said, I think there are some very strong structures in thinking of what heritage looks like and what does it do, and it can be quite difficult to encourage people to think outside of these, and sometimes it doesn’t work so that model, it doesn’t get, how can I say, it doesn’t get questioned as much as maybe it could be useful to do, if not to change things completely but to reflect on them: why are things the way they are? I was working in the UK for several years and there was a whole debate in terms of what’s in museums that have a colonial legacy, for example, and obviously in Ireland it would be similar when you’re looking at Ireland being a former colony and how is it that those structures of thinking about things that are preserved can be questioned, or how different voices can be brought together. And with participatory approaches, again, you in a way set the scene for shared decision making that might question those things. But it’s very, very difficult to actually have people do that, so it may be something that takes time. I find, you know, doing participatory work would benefit from longer term support to projects compared to what we usually have to do. The other thing that I found is that in a way technology is more widespread today, so people are much more used to using technology in their life besides, you know, work but these, you know, leisure activities, they’re a kind of social world, people are very comfortable with variety of tools and platforms. What I find fascinating is that when I started some early projects that were looking at more participatory approaches around twenty years ago, there was much less of that. And in a way, people were more creative when you say okay, let’s imagine an alternative way of, you know, finding this exhibition in your life, visiting this exhibition, interacting with objects. But now it’s very difficult to get people out of thinking ‘oh we should build an app that does this and so that you know to interact with the object’ or ‘we should bring augmented reality glasses to view things’. I think, in a way, we have more really effective examples of interaction in our lives, and it makes it very difficult to think outside of those…almost standards of interaction. So even in participatory projects sometimes the common decision is maybe not as innovative or ground-breaking as it could be, and not because, you know, being ground-breaking is what you want to achieve, not necessarily, what you want to achieve is something that makes sense, that has value for the stakeholders that take part in those projects. So it doesn’t have to be the next revolution in heritage interpretation but part of the participatory process is throwing out ideas and together then filtering them through, and thinking about what could benefit everybody who is involved in the process. And I think that open phase of the process really needs much more sustaining from the point of view of the facilitator than it did before. Because I think a lot of the… you know what people have in mind in terms of modes of digital interaction with things are very much shaped by what an app can do, what social media does. That again makes it easier to explain ‘what if you could do this’ because people know it or can imagine it, but at the same time find it very difficult to think of alternative ways. So, I think those are some kind of long-term insights on how participatory methods can pan out. I still think it’s a very worthy thing to do, to work in a participatory way around heritage, because as I said I think it brings out some of the kind of values and discourses that people feel in relation to heritage and culture that sometimes are hidden or don’t really come to the surface, but it definitely needs strong support and facilitation and also in terms of, you know, telling people or encouraging people to think about what the digital could do, rather than just accept that there will be some and it will look like X.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Do you think there’s particular methodologies for doing just that, for maybe breaking out of these standardised views about what the output might look like?</p></sp><sp who="#LC"><speaker>LC</speaker><p>	I don’t think there’s one methodology in particular. A lot depends on who you’re working with, which groups, what are the circumstances of the participatory process. For example, it changes significantly if you’re working with people who are co-located and can have in person interactions, or people who have to maintain that participation remotely or in a hybrid way. So, I don’t think there is one methodology. You have to kind of think in terms of who are they? What are they comfortable engaging with? What I find, though, is that sometimes a methodology stands for the whole participatory process…So you see ‘oh we did a workshop, so we are participatory’, which is not the case. So having done a workshop doesn’t necessarily make the whole process a participatory process. And I think participatory as a word is very attractive and it signals commitment to listen, to open up discourse and decision making, but it has to be maintained through a long-term commitment to truly understand what might be the barriers to participation. So I think sometimes the danger is being too like thinking ‘oh I’ve done a workshop so I’m a participatory researcher’ so, to me, you can facilitate a participatory process through many different methods and techniques but what counts is the general position you put yourself in. In a recent project, Culture Labs, we were looking at the relevance of participatory engagement with culture and heritage for communities such as migrants and refugees who have just arrived into a new country and we gathered data from the migrant communities, the institutional stakeholders and the public sector that facilitates them, and we got them to talk about what do you think participation in cultural heritage could be, what it could do for you, and it was really interesting to see what kind of different understandings were between these three core stakeholder groups that would do these activities. So I think there’s also a lot to unpack in terms of what a participatory processes in relation to digital heritage, digital culture can be. I think maybe we have taken again some models that have been around for a very long time in certain settings and kept them going for very long and maybe we need to rethink that too. But I don’t know how. It’s just that it’s very fresh in my mind because of recent work.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you very much. And then moving on, I was wondering if you could speak to the relationship between the physical and the digital when it comes to heritage?</p></sp><sp who="#LC"><speaker>LC</speaker><p>	Yep. Something that I’m really interested in is the idea of kind of hybrid interaction. So, the kind of digital element, the interactive element, but in relation to the materiality and felt experience of heritage, whether it’s an object but not necessarily an object; it can be kind of felt immersion in, for example, intangible heritage such as music, crafts and so on. So how do we maintain some concern for the material and also how do we maintain some aspects of that embodied and tangible experience in the interactive experience and the digital experience? So in some work that I have done we have looked at blending the two and for example, designing installations that try and… how can I say… blending the physical and the digital, whether through this idea of kind of assemblies for interaction, which is a kind of interaction frame that was developed several years ago in HCI, where we look at the experience of the visit through the kind of assembly of various components, that includes tangible ones and not just digital ones and how to bridge the two. So, for example, how could the manipulation of a physical object link to digital interaction or digital experiences. But more recently in a project called meSch that I was part of we also created a toolkit for heritage professionals to create tangible installations in museums, which was an attempt to bring the idea of tangible interaction outside of the research lab and into the practice of cultural professionals. And that was a really fascinating project because again when you think about digital heritage and digital cultural heritage lots of people think of things that are online on the web but how do they travel from the web back into rooms and objects is anybody’s guess; so in a way it’s almost like once it’s digitised it’s gone in this kind of cloud and you can only ever access it through a computer and the computer looks like a laptop or like a smartphone where you have an app to see it, so the idea we had in the project is that you can embed digital behaviours and digital content into physical and tangible interaction with objects and exhibits. We built a number of exhibitions that worked in that way, using anything from replica objects of our actual museum artefacts that could be manipulated and connected to digital content, to portable devices for interaction that were not phones or laptops and that had some kind of physical shape that connected to the theme or content at the exhibition, to the idea of personalised souvenirs that basically took digital information and behaviour that was monitored and made them into an object that people could take home at the end of their visit and represented again some of the physical qualities of that experience. When it comes to turning that into something that exhibition designers think about in their work, that’s the real difficult part again because it is a model of interaction with the digital and the physical that is less widespread, more difficult to realise, but I still believe that it’s got a lot of potential in terms of thinking of alternative ways to encounter heritage. So, what if instead of, you know, so you have a physical replica of an object, what if you could destroy it because that object brings to you something that you disagree with, or that is difficult, that is traumatic. Again, what I was saying earlier about some of the legacy of collections, especially in some countries, that’s to do with racism, colonialism and so on and so forth. It could be applied to, maybe, again subvert that model of encountering heritage a little bit more, and it’s something I’d definitely like to do more of, although of course after Covid touching things is very much frowned upon so I’m not sure when that will happen.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	We already talked a little bit about the C21 Project and part of that project is interested in how textual materials are shared in the digital age and what I would like to ask you is do you feel that matters of design in interaction are given enough consideration by existing resources in this domain for similar projects? What would you like to see in those projects? Digital scholarly editions in terms of maybe what would you like to do with the texts in them? </p></sp><sp who="#LC"><speaker>LC</speaker><p>	I guess it would be good if textual editions would offer clearly those opportunities for someone like me who is interested in what happens when people encounter them, what they could do. Maybe give more direct hints to possibilities to translate into interactive experiences. I think that would be really interesting because I’m not an expert in textual materials, so if I’m looking at co-designing an exhibition that might feature some of these resources, I need help to understand what are, for example, elements of it that could connect to an interactive experience, whether it’s giving people suggestions for, you know, their own reflection or their own imagination or around what’s in the text. So, I think maybe a sense that it’s not about just reading them and encountering them now, but also, how they could it become part of something else and how they can be connected with other digital resources for example visual material. It’s almost like some kind of a higher-level links to other corpuses and maybe try and see how text and other media could connect. It’s really interesting, I have seen some interesting uses of textual materials in exhibitions for example, looking at words that were used in historical texts and how people don’t use them today and almost encouraged them to use them in another context, like creating their own, for example, poetry or word art with it. So there could be a lot of potential for that. But a lot will depend on, of course, the context, so if it’s an exhibition about whoever wrote the text or if it’s on something else. So a lot depends on what it goes into the world to do. I was thinking of, oh yes, something else I know that there is a lot of work on is looking at metadata and archival practices that very often replicate existing power structures, and also some legacy structures that might be problematic. So definitely when it comes to looking at digital editions, I think there should be a similar effort to try not to replicate them, or rather being a bit more conscious about how the metadata, anything that goes into a textual edition does not replicate problematic issues. This might not apply to some of the content, again it’s such a broad field…but might apply to others. So I think in the same way as archives of objects are questioned and then re-thought maybe textual editions should also be concerned with that.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you and then just lastly, another open-ended question, what does the ideal future of digital cultural heritage look like to you?</p></sp><sp who="#LC"><speaker>LC</speaker><p>	Hmmm I don’t know. I think something that is, again…Something that doesn’t just live on websites, that becomes more lively into people’s lives so maybe a closer connection between digital cultural heritage assets and the life of communities. I think in general there’s much more to be done in terms of connecting communities to heritage and therefore to digital cultural heritage too. In a way the digital is an attempt to make things more accessible because you don’t have to go physically somewhere to enjoy something or explore it, but at the same time it can exclude other people who might not be comfortable with technology or might not have the means to access it. So, I think my general aspiration would be what it’s always been, which is again trying to bring people to think about what heritage is and what is culture and make it mean something to them or make what it already means to them visible and expressed. So, I think I will continue to do that because we haven’t fixed that problem yet, it hasn’t gone away and we need to keep working on it.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>