<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Alex Gil</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on January 20th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_AG.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>ALEX GIL Alex is Senior Lecturer II and Associate Research Faculty of Digital Humanities in the Department of Spanish and Portuguese at Yale University, where he teaches introductory and advanced courses in digital humanities, and runs project-based learning and collective research initiatives. Before joining Yale, Alex served for ten years as Digital Scholarship Librarian at Columbia University, where he co-created and nurtured the Butler Studio and the Group for Experimental Methods in Humanistic Research. His research interests include Caribbean culture and history, digital humanities and technology design for different infrastructural and socio-economic environments, and the ownership and material extent of the cultural and scholarly record. He is currently senior editor of archipelagos journal, editor of internationalization of Digital Humanities Quarterly, co-organizer of The Caribbean Digital annual conference, and co-principal investigator of the Caribbean Digital Scholarship Collective, funded by the Andrew W. Mellon foundation.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	The idea of scholarly editing, specifically digital scholarly editing, what does that mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	To me it’s the important work that scholars do to make sure that our documentary past survives—and I’m just going to focus on text, although obviously the things that we talk about can apply in some ways to video and audio, film, architecture, buildings, statues, whatever, but I’m just going to be focusing on text if you don’t mind. I’m guessing that most of your interviewees are doing the same. So for me, I find it fundamental that we pay close attention, at least to a selection of the materials we inherit, of the artifacts that we inherit from the past, right? And I say careful because, of course, the activity of editing by itself can be distinguished from scholarly editing because we see editions ranging from Project Gutenberg’s kind of slap-and-dash, just put up any transcription of the text there, to the super careful editions of teams working for years on a set of texts. One of the most beautiful recent examples of the latter is the Samuel Beckett digital edition. I know you’re talking to me from Ireland. I was the head of the committee of the MLA when we gave the prize to that edition. It’s not just looking at the published versions of the texts, but also looking at the manuscripts, at the napkins, you know, anything that Sam Beckett did around his textual production, and that kind of work has its place. I think it should have its place in scholarship because it’s the base for the sort of critical, theoretical or historical analysis that we may do based on these documents, right? And very often, more than people who don’t do this work would assume, it can clarify a lot of misconceptions, and you know, set the record straight on historical claims that are made that have no foundation in the texts. That kind of engagement, that kind of processing, of engaging with the production of text certainly helps to refine our analysis of the past. So, I hope it’s here to stay even though we’ve seen an erosion of supported positions, of paid positions to do this kind of work.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think we’ve seen an erosion of this kind of work?</p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	In departments, yes, it’s one of the interesting phenomena that I see, that I think is true. I haven’t done any serious study of the situation, and I hope that your study might shed some light on this phenomenon: that there is an outsourcing of a lot of the traditional activities that were embodied in the scholar, to the libraries. And because of the outsourcing to libraries, which for the most part are under different labour conditions, different labour arrangements, and because of the place they find themselves in the 21st Century, that also means that a lot of these functions are outsourced to vendors. So one of the things that we see vendors doing, for example, is careful editions of this or that. They don’t call them editions necessarily but value-added to digital archives, where they would then get back to the scholars for annotations, but they would take care of the production. If it’s digital, which is what we’re here to talk about, they would take care of the production of the digital platform, of the interface that will make the edition tangible to the reading public and to other scholars. When I say functions, the word function is key here, because what I see driving this is a rearrangement of the division of labour of what it takes to produce these things. Now there was always a division of labour, it’s always been around, it’s not like we’re in this century inventing the division of scholarly labour. It’s that textual scholarship is being broken down into component tasks that are being done by different people than were being done before. To give you an example, to clarify, and not to take it too much to the abstract level: Because of the digital, you need people to do the conversion from Microsoft word documents to either TEI XML or to HTML depending on the type of editions that we’re doing, and then you also need people to actually produce the front end, that might involve some JavaScript and other things. But also think of the work of other compilation of documentary evidence. So that was the work that only the super elite scholars that had the funding were doing. Say this is fifty years ago or sixty years ago. They were doing those super legendary editions that give us a lot of the theory that you and I inherit, the compilation of the papers of Rosetti or of Whitman or whoever, right? These kinds of things, these kinds of compilations used to be done by the scholars who got the funding to travel to all these archives to convince them to allow them to put together an edition, this kind of thing. Now, for example, you have companies stepping in and doing the compilation or a large team of scholars. So it’s just that the component parts, the way that we go about building these things is changing and the stakeholders, the landscape has different players, and they’re playing different roles now that may or may not be good for textual scholarship in the future. And I do worry about the increasing role that vendors are playing in this, in that even librarians are playing in this, because the way that librarians approach some of these things may not be the best in all scenarios, because of the bureaucracy that libraries bring into this. If you’re in a library, you’re just “staff,” and the relationship to the documentary path of staff is going to be different than a scholar’s, right? Anyways, these are some things that I see in the landscape right now, this kind of rearrangement of the chairs or the functions, of the different tasks that you need in order to do scholarly editions. I think it’s too early to tell what’s going to happen, but there’s room for concern, and we should definitely learn more, study the situation more. I hope this study helps to do that. I don’t know if that was one of the things you set out to do, was it?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s what this exercise is, it’s an opportunity for us to see what people think we should be looking at. </p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	Okay, so before we get to the technological side, is it ok if we talk about what new forms or the actual approaches to the past that inform… at least this will make a lot more sense later when we do get to the technology of why minimal computing, and why not those other platforms you asked me about earlier [before the interview started]. Something else that I see today, and it’s very exciting, is that at least on this side of the Atlantic—definitely we’re more focused on this than in Europe for many reasons—but right now, for example, we are focusing a lot on what we call the work of recovery. We can trace different genealogies to this. Definitely, during the birth of the internet, that word ‘recovery’ meant publishing of minor authors and voices that had been silenced, that never found a publisher. Including indigenous black women, for example. There was a rush to self-publish, and to do scholarship using the Web 1.0, right? So a bunch of people are building HTML sites in the 90’s. This is when Project Gutenberg comes in, and theirs is not necessarily recovery work. It’s more like they’re trying to be exhaustive and canonical, but a bunch of people also begin doing these sites where it’s like “women writers of the 19th Century”, etc. It's like you could tell, and they would tell you explicitly, the reason they’re doing it by themselves online is because they couldn’t find publishers to do this kind of projects. And a lot of digital scholarly editions that are like the grandfathers of a bunch of stuff we see today are born under this rubric of recovery. Recovery is transforming as a concept at least in the digital realm. If you think about for example… I don’t know if you’ve read Kim Gallon’s essay on Black Digital Humanities, I think it was DHQ, I’m not positive, where she says that at the core of Black DH is recovery. Recovery here is slightly different because it transforms a little bit, because it’s like: we know the Europeans came with print culture to the Americas, and of course clashed with the oral traditions and in some cases pictographic traditions, right? Because you do have pictographic languages. And also they bring all these enslaved Africans during the process of colonisation, as the prelude to capitalism being born in the Atlantic world, and those are also oral cultures that are coming in. I say clashing because it’s impossible to say that they remain oral. You know the clash with print happens in the contact, right? In that history we see the formation of, in this side of the Atlantic and in Europe, we see the formations of what we call modern libraries and modern archives today. And it’s hard to extricate them from this process. The sort of bulk of the documentary past that we inherit from this at least five hundred years… (and, I’m not going to go into the classics and medieval European stuff, although all of that stuff becomes part of that process in the past five hundred years, and it doesn’t skip to the present, right?) That bulk, which leads to the bulk of what is actually digitised and being digitised, does not represent the sort of artistic culture, historical perspective of the enslaved populations, of the indigenous populations. In fact, there is evidence of active destruction of cultural production, of trying to… this has always been a tactic of the conqueror, right?... for the most part to try to erase the culture of the conquered, not all conquerors, surely—the Roman Empire was particularly generous when it came to this, I hear. But that means that today when we try to say this, we’re like, fine, but how do we do then the history, how do we do Black history, how do we do indigenous history? Do we just settle on the idea that we have to simply filter it though the voice of the ethnographer, through the cleric, through the voices that ended up being part of the print record, is that the only way we can do this? There are many strategies and many theoretical gambits, including a sort of… we see a new rebirth of sculatio, right? Of the rebirth of, what is now called in one of its most elegant theoretical manifestations, “critical fabulation”; where we try to read between the lines, read against the grain of that print record in order to try to recover that perspective, try to recover that cultural production. And so recovery then becomes a sort of like, not the recovery of documents as such in their integrity, but it’s a kind of mission of extraction, right? A good example of this work is the early digital archive of the Caribbean, which is done in TEI. And I use this example because I know your readers are going to be hearing a lot about TEI, so this is one way to explain what this kind of recovery looks like on the ground in professional practice—but not necessarily the only way, right? So there are testimonies in a lot of the records they’re working with in early modern Caribbean texts and you hear quotations and you have quotations of a slave speaking, and then other voices around this time, not necessarily enslaved, from these kinds of populations that speak there and then. What you do is you tag them, and then once you tag all of these voices, then, as you know, you can extract them, and start trying to take them out of their context, in a sense creating a new document. So this work of search and extraction is I think one of the most exciting things that is happening right now. We’re trying to go into this print record that we inherit, and as scholars we are trying to recover, not centering the document form, but centering specific things that we’re looking at, something that of course TEI is amenable to, that kind of isolation of things within documents. So it’s the documents within the documents that defines a lot of the things that at least I’m interested in looking at these days. Having said that, let’s talk about technology, that’s fine. I just wanted to point out that this is a particularly exciting turn of affairs for me personally, because it allows us, it give us an approach to the past that will allow us to construct a future in which we can get along better, and without letting go of the honesty of scholarship that looks at documentary evident. We don’t invent it. We don’t flat out make up stuff. You know we have to have this honest relationship with the record, right? So ok, so having said that, let me answer your question.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	With the disciplinary culture of digital scholarly editing and critical edition making being so textual, and with many of the cultures that have been lost being non-textual, do you feel that considering the emphasis that scholarly editing places on text, that the practice can ever really be an act of recovery?</p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	I think there’s room to do it from within the textual cultures that we inhabit. I personally think that there is work to be done on trying to recover from those things that do survive in oral form, because even though these traditions work according to their own logic, it’s not like print never evolves too. No, print is full of revisions, reeditions and stuff like that. We know that we lose the originals at some point. Originality is lost during the process of print too, so originality is not necessarily what drives our studies in print either—although some people… sure—but what we’re talking about applies to the sort of work that is being done in this kind of oral traditions you see today, the contemporary ethnography, which is not necessarily the same as the one around in the colonisation period, that is, during the colonial period leading all the way up to the 20th Century, even in Ireland. The idea is that this new work on oral traditions is fine, and can be informed by what we do, but I’m concentrating on the work that can be done within the print cultures themselves: to recover the representations of those cultures in print. I mean that’s what interests me as a scholar, without discarding that fantastic work of trying to also look at archaeological evidence, architectural evidence, even the sort of transmission, non-textual transmission of societal formations that history deals with; the persistence of cultural forms, in the way that people go about, that we go about being a species in packs. </p><p>	All of that is fantastic, but as a textual scholar I’m interested in the ways that we can approach the material record with an eye to recovery that does not centre the document. I don’t care that much about titles, you can keep on calling it documentary evidence if you want, but what I’m saying is what we consider to be the object, like what is the object, is it a book?… this tends to reify sometimes too hard. And part of this recovery process involves a kind of unbinding of textuality that creates new documents that were not in the same binding that they were before… and I think that’s the key for me, that is, the key turn, the de-fetishization of the editing of the document. So we go back and say, well there’s this document, a whole document, and we’re just editing that document. And what I’m seeing now is people saying, not necessarily the whole document. Let’s not edit necessarily the whole document. Let’s edit for something else. Let’s apply our know-how to extracting things. I think that’s going to lead to a lot of debates around here, definitely within the Black community, the indigenous community, people doing ethnic type of scholarship. (We use ethnic here to mean “not the majorities culture.” Everybody’s ethnic, we all have an ethnicity). Well, I think that’s going to drive most of our debates. I actually don’t know the state of those kinds of debates is in Europe right now. You probably have a better sense than I do.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, the technical side of it then, the tools and the platforms, what are the affordances and limitations of these?</p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	So TEI is still the rooster of the coop. There has been movement on making it easier to publish editions in a positive way with CETEIcean and a couple of other solutions, Recogito too. This is a great move forward, and I know of course people had been trying to do this, creating some kind of general solutions. Never universal, because no TEI is. I think most people understand now that there will never be a universal TEI solution. But at least general enough that one can cover a lot of territory with a… because also, and I may be wrong about this and others might disagree and take offence, but I think the emphasis for the first twenty years in TEI was on the ontologies of the texts themselves. I think they overvalued the semantic work of tagging, and the actual publication took a back seat, I think there were structural reasons for that. I think one of them is, of course, that the finances have to be bigger for publication because you needed a team of engineers. The people who were doing the tagging were not necessarily the people who were creating the interface, and they didn’t have the technical skills to do it, and most of the successful editors were senior scholars who commanded the resources to have graduate students tag, and themselves tag, etc. This is of course when we first see the early, the big editions like the Rosetti or the Whitman editions operating on this model. You have these super famous faculty members like Jerry McGann, and then you have a team of graduate students, and then you have engineers right, the technologists that would come in and do the tagging and would create the editions, and of course that wasn’t going to work out as the general model for everybody because we cannot command those resources. People were always stuck, like a lot of people are being told, you learn TEI, this is how you’re going to become a digital humanist, and then they end up with super thick marked text and nowhere to go because who’s going to publish that? And now I want to share with the world, and the only thing you can share is the TEI files. So I think we had a breakthrough, I think now everybody understands that the most important part is the publication and not the super fancy ontology of the text with your heavy annotations that you can’t do anything with. So now even with the tagging practices today, you only tag the things you think your interface is going to have. You never tag for anything outside of what your interface is going to have, and this is fantastic. I’m sure some people in TEI have a different perspective of the past. That’s how I see it from what I’ve seen, and that’s great. So, in the TEI world we’re seeing that. That doesn’t mean that the TEI world is the only place where editions are being done. Obviously some people still mess around with Wordpress. We also see for example another type of edition, and I hinted at those earlier which are, for example, you know, these kinds of digital archives that are not content anymore with just providing you images and metadata of things, so now they start adding also diplomatic transcription of text. They don’t even know what to call diplomatic editions but they start doing these types of transcriptions of these things; so you have the images of the things, the metadata and then they start asking scholars to do footnotes, etc. You see this at the sort of aggregate level because they never sell you an edition on one thing it’s always this body of two hundred or three hundred artifacts that then have these kinds of editions with footnotes and stuff like that. I would call them scholarly editions as the people doing the footnotes are scholars, and not necessarily because the text was established by scholars. It may have been established by other people, but that does not make it for me a non-scholarly edition. I don’t think it’s a requirement for something to be called scholarly that the text must be established by the scholar, I think something counts as scholarly if a scholar also just does the work of annotation. We can debate that but as long as the scholars are involved at some level that produces new knowledge, I think we should call that a scholarly edition, in any case. So those types of things use bespoke platforms that the company or the library uses, whatever it is, and that could be a range of things, including industrial-strength solutions doing that type of thing. These are definitely not the Wordpress type of flavour, although you also see some of those things be Omeka sites; and you see also some people trying to build subscription tools and edition tools into things like Omeka; and it’s for precisely these type of collections; so they add transcription tools; for example, one is called Scripto that works with Omeka. It’s been around for ten years. Laura Mandell is working with that project. So we see those types of technology. Enter minimal computing. In this landscape, this is when I propose Ed as an intervention about five or six years ago, as a prototype for the general conversation that we’re having about minimal computing, which is not limited to scholarly editions. Minimal computing is very broad in the range of what it addresses within the world of the humanities, where the conversations centre both hardware and software around the observation that we produce all these different kinds of genres in the humanities right, in the Digital humanities, ranging from digital archives, to maps, to digitalisations, to online syllabi, to all these things that we produce, even what we call databases for lack of a better word as a genre. That producing all of these things, we would be mindful of, first, the environment, the carbon footprint of our heavy-duty computer use and how that actually grows the more work we do on the cloud, because of those server farms, and all this kind of stuff. So conscious that we shouldn’t sacrifice the planet to the drive to remember the past, the drive to curate the past. We wanted to start to think about how we would redo things, how we would redo these genres. Second, besides the environment, we can go down a list of things that are concerns, second one is for example what we can call the digital divide: it’s not a black and white thing. It’s not like a heads or tails, it’s not like this, people who have computers and people who do not. We can understand the digital divide as sort of different ecosystems that apply everywhere around the world: technological ecosystems. In Cuba, for example, people use sneakernets or for your audience: using USBs to pass files. Because the internet, at least for a really long time, they had only 3% penetration to the internet or something like that and 10% penetration to a national intranet. So the ecosystem there… they have a national intranet, so they curated their own version of Wikipedia called Ecured which is right out of a Borges novel because they created this alternative universe outside of what the rest of the world was doing which is like Wikipedia, but not the same. So they were like… and that universe has… 50% of the content doesn’t exist in Wikipedia because its Cuban related content, things that they care about, while the other 50% is like a reinventing the wheel of things that were on Wikipedia! So it’s like an alternative encyclopaedia, and they’re building this in an intranet. We have access to it on the internet but these are things that people have access to inside the intranet that they don’t necessarily have access to on the internet, and this is what I mean when I say the digital divide: that there are these simply different technological ecosystems. At the hardware level it means things like no or low access to the internet, only electricity in the afternoon, or you have to pay for data in a different way. We have unlimited data here in the United States across the board, but in so many parts of the world you have to pay for this many megabytes per month or buying cards and this kind of stuff. There could be censorship for example, so the government might be cracking down on you. In any case, in all these different ecosystems we were building our world of digital humanities where we weren’t conscious, we weren’t really thinking about how are my projects, how am I participating in African, South American or Asian ecologies? Or even those parts of the global south that co-exist here? Like Rikers Island, for example, the youth jail that we have a few blocks away from my home in New York, where the young inmates don’t have access to the internet. It’s like this different ecologies also apply even within our urban centres. Are you in Dublin right now?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Cork.</p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	You’re in Cork, it’s big enough, so even within Cork you know what you have is not the same technological situation everywhere, right? So, we wanted to be conscious about that and we did things, and then more things, thinking about more problems: control, gender, you go down the list. There’s all kinds of things to worry about. Labour conditions, labour is huge, so this idea of who’s building these things. Scholarship has never been done by just one person working alone, it’s always been different divisions of labour, how are genres contributing to maybe what could be inequities in labour conditions for people in the academy. So anyways, all these concerns, they are very well documented. You can share with your readers. And we are about to publish a special issue of DHQ on minimal computing that’s going to gather many voices from around the world addressing these issues. But in short, though, Ed is born out of those concerns, those conversations. Ed was a solution for digital editions, Ed is like so how do we do digital editions if we care about all these things that I just mentioned, and it's a prototype because when I set out to do it I don’t know where I’m going to end up, I just know that I’m going to be thinking about these things during the design process. I’m going to be thinking about these things constantly, and every little detail, I have to pause. And while I was making it, I was like pausing at every little detail and thinking, how does this affect this? and how does this affect that? So what I ended up coming up with was using a static side generator, Jekyll in this particular case. I skipped TEI, not necessarily… you could do similar things with TEI it was… (in fact I and others have created editions of TEI marked up text with Ed) but Ed is definitely focusing on the front end, or it’s focusing on the final product. It definitely centres the edition itself as an object that the public will consume and the public is mostly other scholars. These scholarly audiences will consume, and in that sense for me what was most important was the HTML, not the TEI. For those not familiar with this technology, the HTML is that markup language that we use that browsers can read, and browsers interpret HTML in order to figure out what are the parts of the given document, of the given web page. So for me that was the most important thing. There are a couple of things that I centred that I landed on, I had to ask myself the question, what is the most fundamental things about scholarly editions? And I had to answer that. Of course that was a question that drove a lot of the minimal computing work, which I sorted of posed people in an article that has made the rounds: to always ask themselves What do we need? Because we might give up some luxuries, but we might still get what we need. We might not get what we want, but we might still get what we need. The answer for scholarly editions for me was that you need a text that can be read. Something that I haven’t mentioned, but something else that I noticed was like—aw man—we created so much crap interfaces that you can’t even read them, this goes for vendors too. They don’t create pleasant things. Like you can’t read this shit, it’s like, wow ugly, not ugly but clunky too, and like no, it doesn’t work on your iPad and it’s just like why? Then people run to the bookstore to buy the book version because the book edition was produced thirty years ago and no one can recommend to their students to read this crap. I wanted to make something where the text itself was readable was pretty was a pleasure to read on an iPad, an iPhone or a computer so that was it, my choices on font, colour, layout were driven by this idea that I wanted to make something that people didn’t run away from. So the second thing that I said that scholarly edition needs is the ability to do footnotes and markdown allowed me to do that so I was like you know this Jekyll might be good solution because scholars can add footnotes and the way that Jekyll is built out of the box the footnotes, it’s endnotes not footnotes, the endnotes go at the bottom of the page of the edition. I didn’t do any pop ups or anything like that, I got rid of all that stuff because at the end of the day it’s still the same, it’s just an anchor that points to another place in the text whether the surface is right on top of the thing or not to me it’s relevant because in a microsecond it’s going to be in front of the eyes of whoever’s reading this and of course I find the pop-up solution also contributing to this kind of unreadable interfaces that nobody wants to mess with. So, readability, the ability to do footnotes, enough general layout solutions for poetry that would make it viable for most poetry, not the best solution probably for people like the New York poets who are just doing magnetic poetry on paper like I do on my fridge but enough that you can still do you know Wyatt or Milton, you can do Yeats for sure if anybody wants to take that one up. </p><p>	So, labour wise the solution actually moved us away from the need to have, in my view, the need to have super hard separation between the scholars doing the tagging and the engineers that are going to build the site. That was a very big attraction to me, and the engineers that are going to build the thing, the learning curve for it is somewhere in between what it takes to be an engineer to build a fancy interface on TEI and what it takes to learn markup, so it’s a little, but more than just learning markup, but it’s enough that it might allow a lot more people than just the people, the professors with a lot of resources to do their own editions; and my gambit bore out because I’ve seen a lot of people that don’t reach the level of building an interface for a fancy TEI edition that have been able to produce a super decent edition with Ed, I’ve seen it everywhere, including students, because I’ve taught it in the class. And also, it eliminates the need for those systems that use a database, that use dynamic generation of content; it reduced the cost of maintenance because you don’t have to do patches or anything like this, once you produce a static site you just, you can park your files on the simplest form of servers and even on a USB—remember that I mentioned that in Cuba they pass around things on USB—so now we have the possibility to have this Digital Humanities project on hard media without the need for a server. So, it’s addressing that concern that I have about people without internet, and all of these things, and there’s a lot more and I documented this in an article that I wrote for a Julia Flanders that I can pass to you where I detail how these design decisions all address these issues but that was the general gist of creating Ed. Since creating Ed, others have done other solutions and even CETEICean is informed in one way, I don’t want to be arrogant and say influenced, but that team was paying attention to what I was doing when they were developing CETEICean so, I’ve talked enough, that’s basically the story.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	The article that you were referring to, this is the one The User, the Learner and the…</p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	Machines We Make… that’s the one where I ask what do we need. The one that I talk about the design decisions for Ed in a very detailed way is called… Julia Flanders did a series on Diversity and Digital Humanities in Northeastern University where she is... I’m sending you the link now, my piece is called Design for Diversity: The Case of Ed. It was an initiative, she had a grant to gather a bunch of pieces of people thinking about design process in digital humanities and she was interested to see how do we design when we are trying to accommodate all these different types of student communities and scholarly communities with different ethnicities, sexualities, etc right so this is how the word diversity in the United States is kind of a word that tries to encompass, it’s sort of a replacement for multicultural which we used to use. But anyway, these pieces address all of these design decisions for… they could have been a product of an interview so you could throw it in a text analysis because even I hear a lot of the same things I just told you you’re going to hear.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I think you’ve already been very generous with your time so we might start to finish up. I really like the emphasis on recovery here, which hasn’t been foregrounded in other conversations I’ve had.</p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	I’m surprised because it’s the difference in scholarly… because I work with a scholarly community that cares deeply about these… we have a record that we consider to be broken, right, the way that we approach the record that is the thing we inherit in libraries and archives, we consider that to be a very broken artifact as a whole… because it represents a history of founder years but it doesn’t have, it’s not exhaustive in the way that it went about you know making sure that we captured the history of all of us what’s happening, the people’s history, as opposed to the history of only the elite or the winners, right. So in that scholarly community, I’m talking Caribbean Studies which is my field, this is something most of us are aware of this and of course that is why recovery is so important because it’s trying to come up with strategies for how do we deal with this, our object of study is fundamentally broken you know it leaves you with that sense that… it’s like this relationship where you’re like… of incompleteness that is unavoidable. Anyways maybe it all depends on the types of areas and subject matter in the human past that people are addressing too. I think it would have a lot to do with that, that’s why I always kept saying to me it’s exciting. In society in general I think we’re going to see like a post-colonial society like Ireland, even Yates was doing this kind of work right, so it goes older so the scholars at the turn of the 21st Century in Ireland were all about this shit and they were trying to revive that language even. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Oh yes, the Irish Literary Revival was very much driven by an intentional programme of de-anglicisation in Irish culture, really privileging Irish language, English language Irish stories, games were a big one… cultural nationalism, essentially. And cultural nationalism still persists a great deal in Ireland; there are certain things that hold particular privilege in the public imagination, like our national sport, hurling.</p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	Is it fun?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It is. It was described in some film as a cross between hockey and murder.</p></sp><sp who="#AG"><speaker>AG</speaker><p>	Hockey is already a murderous sport, that does sound fun.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>