<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>C21 Editions: Claire Connolly and James Smith</title>
                <title type="sub">Interview conducted by Michael Kurzmeier on March 8th,
                    2022</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Unpublished working draft</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels. (2023).
                        <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions [Data
                        files].</title> Available from <ref
                        target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions"
                        >https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_MK_CC_JS.xml
                    downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>$today</date>Header added</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div>
                <head>Interviewee bio</head>
                <p><list>
                        <item>CLAIRE CONNOLLY is Professor of Modern English at University College
                            Cork.</item>
                        <item>JAMES SMITH is a Postdoctoral Research fellow on the Ports, Past and
                            Present project at UCC.</item>
                    </list></p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> To start, I have an open-ended question here. So, what do the terms scholarly
                    edition and scholarly editing mean to you? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> I understand a scholarly edition to be one where the kind of highest standards
                    of bibliographical processes and textual editing have been followed. I have done
                    scholarly editing and would, on my CV, I would make a distinction between
                    scholarly textual editions and popular editions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> I agree with that but I would just add that I would expect an apparatus with a
                    scholarly edition and in scholarly editing, I would expect quite a lot of
                    footnotes to be like the sort of metatext of the scholarly edition as well as it
                    being that very high definitive standard. But other than that, I agree with what
                    Claire said. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you. And do you see anything that digital scholarly editions do
                    differently than print scholarly editions?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> I suppose access is one thing, and maybe a certain depth of intertextual
                    stability in terms of references, where one could open up the text in richer
                    ways through links and so on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> I guess as well as that a digital scholarly edition can be interoperable and can
                    be sort of be context neutral so it can be marked up in an interoperable format
                    like an XML or TEI, or whatever it may be and linked open data and it can be
                    reused to different purposes and presented the front-end can be many different
                    things, but the core data might be archived and reusable in a lot of different
                    contexts but it would still have those same burdens of quality and a certain
                    amount of interpretation and apparatus but expressed in different ways,
                    flexibly, creatively perhaps.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Next I would like to talk a little bit about the Ports Past and Present project,
                    would you like to tell me something about it, just as an introduction?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> Do you want to take that, James?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> Do you maybe want to start in general and then I can go into the specifics of
                    it. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> It’s an applied cultural heritage Project funded by the European Development
                    Fund via the Ireland Wales programme and the idea is to see what sort of social
                    and economic benefits can be drawn from deeper engagement with natural and
                    cultural heritage, particularly in relation to tourism. It looks at the five
                    ports in the Irish Sea Basin and connections back and forth. At the moment, the
                    project lives as a series of kind of short cultural heritage stories that James
                    has curated on an Omeka site, along with an app and some other forms of
                    associated digital output.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> And I guess in addition to that, I mean out of our six work packages, some are
                    administrative in nature or dissemination or engagement in nature but there’s
                    three, like there’s one that’s creative connections which is 12 creatives,
                    writers, artists, etcetera producing work that’s on the ports and then there’s a
                    third work package that’s films that was based on quite a lot of research and
                    interviews etcetera and then there’s our work package which is the work package
                    four based in UCC which is called ‘Bringing the Past to Life’ and that’s where
                    the stories come from. But what’s starting to happen now is especially as we
                    archive, we work towards the end of the project, they’re starting to mix
                    together and we’re starting to, I guess going back to the previous point about
                    interoperability, we’re starting to kind of mingle the material together, to
                    archive it long-term but also to exhibit and to disseminate at the end. So, they
                    started off as very separate strings but they are kind of all coming together
                    now. So, I guess that’s partially that we’re going to need a lot of different
                    ways of different apparatuses to display and to use that material as well, as
                    well as trying to capture it in interoperable formats in this case on the
                    Digital Repository of Ireland, of which UCC is a member.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you James. I was just wondering could you maybe say a little bit more
                    about the challenges of archiving a project of that size or maybe making it
                    available in a sustainable way?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> Yeah, I guess there’s a kind of tension between the project, I mean it comes to
                    the interface thing like I mean if you look at it on an Omeka collection and
                    also if you look at ours which uses a public history themed front-end theme
                    called Curatescape, it has a very specific way of showing you the material but
                    then of course like there’s Dublin Core Metadata behind it where we are working
                    up and shaping up into ingest spreadsheets to put in, you know, like so we’re
                    basically having to abstract the information and figure out what form to keep it
                    in that’s a bit separate from the way it’s been displayed, you know, the
                    front-end, the CSS, the styling and the maps and all the stuff the way that we
                    presented it and that’s the same for the Arts, I mean, it’s presented some of
                    its literally stuck to walls, some of it is sculptures, how can we bring that
                    all together and archive it in a particular way and how can we talk about it and
                    write about it for example later on. So I guess that’s the thing is getting it
                    all in, finding format for it that can be reusable and sustainable in the
                    future, but we’re also working, for example, to archive like to create a
                    snapshot a web archive of the website as it appears so that people can get that
                    user experience and see what it looked like when it was in that format, even if
                    we’re thinking like 10-15 years, whatever in the future when the website in its
                    current form might not be there anymore. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Claire, could you maybe say a few things about the project that you’ve worked on
                    before the Deep Maps Cork Project?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> You mean in terms of archiving and so on? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Yeah, maybe in terms of its approach and its design. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> Sure, so that was an interdisciplinary project and, I suppose, a bit of an
                    experiment in interdisciplinarity. It was funded through a scheme where an Arts
                    and Humanities PI had to collaborate with a stem co-PI. I worked with Professor
                    Rob McAllen from the School of Biological Earth and Environmental Sciences. He
                    is a Marine Biologist and we decided to try and develop — at a relatively small
                    scale across a relatively defined historical period — a model for thinking about
                    the coast and coastal heritage, coastal cultures, with the idea that perhaps
                    earlier cultural representations might precociously bearing witness to
                    environmental issues in our own time, or the information about the environment
                    might be gleaned from earlier cultural representations t. It remained pretty
                    much kind of an experiment. The Ports project is more fully formed, it is funded
                    for a longer period, has a larger research staff and it’s hosted on a WordPress
                    site on the UCC website. UCC was not a member of the Digital Repository of
                    Ireland at the time which was a problem for us. The site is still live and it's
                    informally looked after by Orla-Peach Power who works in MaREI, UCC’s Marine
                    Research Centre along with another researcher who worked on it, Dr Rachel
                    Murphy, now in the University of Limerick. But I wouldn’t describe it as a
                    successful story in terms of legacy. In fact, it’s on my conscience to think
                    about it and try to figure out what to do with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Great. Thank you. Maybe to tie all this up, do you consider these projects to be
                    critical editions or do you see any similarities between how these projects
                    engaged with the underlying data in the way that a critical edition would do?
                </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> Maybe more so for Ports, for Deep Maps I don’t because I think it was, you know,
                    an avowed experiment in a form of interdisciplinary thinking so the forms of
                    inquiry that were pursued were the output, if you like. It was funded over quite
                    a short scale with a relatively limited budget so I think its legacy is more
                    methodological and belongs to kind of modes of inquiry that continue if you
                    like. I don’t in anyway think of it meaningfully as an edition. Ports, I suppose
                    is more like that, isn’t it? Although truthfully, that’s a bit of a stretch for
                    me actually to think of it as a scholarly edition. You know you can see some of
                    these books here behind me, those blue volumes just over my shoulder is the
                    selected writings of Maria Edgeworth, I edited two volumes of that collected
                    edition. It was my big post PhD project: I spent a number of years working under
                    a general editor, agreeing on certain standards, pursuing them, debating them,
                    and so on. That work was done before there were digital possibilities, but I
                    could easily imagine that continuing into a digital edition and I find we’re
                    stretching the term a little bit to go into the Ports project in terms of
                    scholarly editing as I understand it. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> I think to add to that I might add the one thing that Deep Maps and Ports, Past
                    and Present have in common at least is that the way we’ve curated a lot of stuff
                    is through using Deep Maps and the methodology of Deep Maps and kind of giving
                    different types of knowledge equal audition and I think that might include
                    podcasting audio, creative works, the films, material that arose from the
                    project, people’s personal stories, we’re kind of doing that re-collage Deep
                    Mapping thing there and I think something that all Deep Maps have in common is
                    that they’re almost antithetical to the idea of being finished so a critical
                    edition has to even if it’s not finished it has to pretend to be finished or be
                    a snapshot in time of something even if it evolves or grows as it moves along
                    it’s trying to present sort of a moment even if the moment is changing whereas I
                    think a Deep Map is never really a moment because every single person that looks
                    at it deliberately gets something different out of it because you can never have
                    a uniform interaction with a Deep Map because you’re always going to look at a
                    different set of material when you go through it, at least in its kind of
                    original, imagined form. But it can, I think be extracted into things that you
                    could consider to be an edition like glossed and put into formats but I think
                    there’s a distinction between the Deep Map as a kind of wellspring of different
                    types of material all bumping up against each other and the sort of outputs of
                    the Deep Map which I think in certain situations could conceivably be a critical
                    edition or be considered to be critical in some way, or an edition in some way.
                </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> And I would just add to that in so far as Ports has a commitment to the kind of
                    co-production of knowledge with our community stakeholders from whom we often
                    receive heritage stories. Those go through a certain process: James holds the
                    writers to certain editorial standards and we’re comfortable that they’re
                    factually correct, grammatically correct and so on. But I think that pulls
                    against the kind of notions of authority inherent in a scholarly edition, the
                    sharing of the authority about the knowledge about the ports with the community,
                    that to me would feel quite different from what you do where you take an agreed
                    set of scholarly conventions and apply them to new materials. So I think for
                    example, the last edition that I looked at with any kind of critical eye was the
                    new or the ongoing edition of the letters of Thomas Carlyle Lwhich are coming
                    out in a hard copy and online kind of more or less simultaneously. You get some
                    interoperability with the digital edition but otherwise it’s more or less the
                    same thing: you can hold a big volume in your hand or you can avail of increased
                    search capacities, online. So for me that’s too much of a stretch from there to
                    what we’re doing with Ports. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Oh, absolutely. And we don’t need to, we don’t need to force that comparison.
                    But what I’d like to know is with either project are there things that you would
                    have liked to have done that weren’t possible because of resource or technical
                    constraints? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> So much. James will know this already and you and James will be encountering
                    this as you move through 21st century editions, but our research infrastructure
                    in UCC is just simply not fit for purpose in terms of realising the ambitions of
                    a large-scale digital project. It’s felt like battling all the way. I feel we’re
                    insufficiently funded. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> I guess that add to that of course Covid just made everything completely
                    different to what we would have imagined we’re doing stuff like literally now
                    that really I would have preferred to be in doing in the middle of 2020. So, in
                    some ways I feel like in the way we’d imagined it, we could have done all the
                    things we potentially wanted to do. I mean, there’s always something, I mean
                    that that’s an imaginary count of actual life I find had to grasp, to be honest,
                    but we could have done a lot more of certain types of things, but we’ve also
                    done, you know, we’ve had to pivot and everyone has had to pivot and we found
                    other things entirely that we wouldn’t have otherwise done and I think it’s
                    given me more time to focus on thinking about legacy and digital sustainability,
                    data management and I think we’re a heck of a lot better prepared that then we
                    would have otherwise been.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> That’s interesting. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> But I guess it means we’re now on this… we’ve got a new colleague, Dr Claire
                    Nolan, who’s really game to gather material and has got a sort of enthusiasm for
                    like interviewing people so I think we’re going to catch up a lot of things I
                    would have liked to have been doing last year and in 2020. But I think in other
                    ways we’ve kind of especially the Project Manager Aoife Dowling and myself and
                    others, we really had a chance to think through some things we had to think
                    through because they were kind of proving to be our main legacy. So of course,
                    when the project is living online a lot more than we thought it would have
                    otherwise done then the digital legacy of the project suddenly becomes massively
                    more important in making sure that it survives. So, I think it’s hard to
                    untangle how things would have turned out without Covid but I think we’ve gone
                    off in a slightly different direction in some things and I think that might
                    prove to be… we might get a bit of both in the end, like when all is said and
                    done. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> Yeah, it’s an obvious thing to say but I would have liked more primary research,
                    more time in the archive with time to develop new accounts of and the past.
                    We’ve done a bit of that but it hasn’t been possible to do it all as much as
                    we’d hoped.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> And everyone needs somebody like James on your project because there’s never a
                    problem, there are only solutions. So that has been very much our mode and it’s
                    been great.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> That’s a great attitude.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> We’re definitely trying to sort of Carpe Diem now that we can actually go places
                    but it would have been so much better if we could have spread this stuff out
                    over three years.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> But it would be true to say that we now conceive of ourselves as a digital
                    project in a way we never did before Covid. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> No, sure. I see there’s an app for Port Places and I was wondering, could you
                    maybe tell me a little bit about the app and what it does? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> It’s probably a useful, interesting DH story, because basically the app is … I
                    suppose you’d call it like a reskin with some customizations of an app and an
                    authoring tool that goes with it called Safarnama which in Sanskrit I think
                    means the story of the journey and it’s from Lancaster University, from their DH
                    people, from Deborah Sutton who is a Professor in Modern South Asian History and
                    she created or worked to create with a sort of seed funding grant from the AHRC
                    in the UK this app for telling stories in places like Mumbai and in Karachi,
                    it’s complicated sort of multifaceted urban history is essentially where there
                    is these blurred lines and basically everyday experience and interaction with
                    lived history and the legacies of the place you find yourself now. And it’s got
                    some useful features that we like which is that, firstly, it’s not like a web
                    app so it’s not dependent on the Internet so you can pre download like a whole
                    experience which is what sort of collection locations are called and just use
                    your location services to navigate it so long as you’ve got the sort of map
                    tiles loaded in and you’ve got the, you’ve got the thing downloaded all the
                    images and all the media it works fine and that’s important for us because you
                    really can’t guarantee a good Internet connection in a lot of our regions and on
                    the ferry for that matter. </p>
                <p>So it couldn’t be a web app and I know that’s a popular trend in app development
                    is using web apps and if you’re in a city, if you like doing a doctor’s
                    appointment or whatever, that’s all well and good but for this kind of thing,
                    that wasn’t really suitable. It also is quite simple, it’s just blocks, blocks
                    of text, images and then audio or video, very simple components that you can
                    shuffle them around and make whatever you want from them. And it’s also very
                    simple in the sense that anyone with a Google account can log into the authoring
                    tool and make things. And lastly it kind of, it has QR codes so you can download
                    them, but essentially, it also had this sense of being kind of, it has these
                    trigger zones, like all around the locations that’s a bit like a Geo fence, but
                    it doesn’t work when you crossover the circle, it tells you on your
                    notifications if you’re close to somewhere, or you can just look at it yourself,
                    you know wherever you are and those are all things that we attracted us to it. </p>
                <p>So essentially Port Places is… we didn’t pay for a service from an existing
                    provider, what we did essentially was invest in Safarnama because it needed a
                    new version, it needed to be updated and it only had an android app didn’t have
                    an iOS app and we basically invested essentially and we are continuing to invest
                    in its long-term future by putting money into growing it and that’s allowed it
                    then in turn to grow and do new things. There are new projects that’s come out
                    of that that Deb Sutton is doing that’s about silk makers in India. And there’s
                    other options for people to make apps from it in future, we archived all the
                    codes on Zenodo, it’s open source, it was all hooked in from GitHub when the
                    developer finished it. So basically, we tried to make it open data, but it’s
                    also kind of it was simple in the ways that we wanted it to be and complicated
                    in the ways we wanted it to be and we chose to invest in the development of the
                    discipline and of the technology rather than paying for services and that saved
                    us money, but it also, we have labour, but not as much money as some projects
                    have for that kind of thing, so it was a good trade off really. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Was the app a consideration from the start? Did you go into the project knowing
                    you wanted to add an app to it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> Yeah, it’s a deliverable so we have to, yeah. It was always a thing we had to do
                    and it’s good in a way because it lets us, we have all these stories that we’ve
                    done, but we have basically they form a big scrap book of material that we can
                    cut little bits out of and arrange but we’ve also been able to offer some of our
                    stakeholders a way to have an app that they wouldn’t otherwise have any access
                    to. We’re refreshing a 15-year-old town trail that doesn’t function anymore as a
                    book, but now it’s going to be app, you know. So basically, it’s giving us the
                    chance to provide things that wouldn’t otherwise exist, but also to re
                    articulate our material in a new format. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> There is another open-ended question here. What does a future digital edition
                    look like to you? What would be the ideal scenario to have a digital edition
                    in?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> Well, in the period of literature that I work on, particularly in the 19th
                    century particularly in relation to Irish writing in English of that period we
                    are gravely lacking proper editions of a number of collections and
                    correspondence, so I see like a huge need for more. James will know that we’ve
                    done some work with Máirín MacCarron as well and my colleague Cliona ÓGallchoir
                    in relation to the Maria Edgeworth correspondence which is largely held in
                    Oxford and in Dublin. So for me, a digital edition will have to answer the
                    challenge of manuscript material that is largely locked up libraries with very
                    limited forms of access. For proper scholarly access we just need an explanatory
                    context and a framework. So I look at something like the Unlocking the Mary
                    Hamilton Papers project in Manchester for instance, where they’ve used AI for
                    handwriting recognition. I would hope that we’ll be able to find ways to start
                    to make accessible in authoritative ways some of this material. JS: I think in
                    addition to that what I would say is trying to firstly make it so that the task
                    of getting as many editions into a machine-readable format as possible is
                    separated from the scholarly work of interpreting them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> It’s so important, I agree.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> You’ve got your interoperable text that’s being properly marked up using all
                    these tools we have now like great best practise stuff or TEI or whatever you
                    choose to do or you’ve got all your named, you know your Geoparsing or your
                    named objects or whatever, you’ve prepared it and that’s a whole field of
                    scholarship, but then the freedom to create new interfaces and new ways of
                    interrogating and navigating that text and those two things going on
                    simultaneously, but be able to move back and forth. And I think there’s like,
                    one thing I saw that excited me recently, I mean, we talked about machine
                    learning and transcription but there’s tools now based on Transkribus that can
                    transcribe or search within a digitised but untranscribed corpus. I saw one, a
                    big corpus of mediaeval texts called HIMANIS, French manuscripts that have never
                    been looked at by human eyes, they’ve been scanned and uploaded and really
                    there’s been no interpretation of them. But being able to search through them
                    and find words using Transkribus essentially without anyone having ever…
                    basically, I think that automation of the transcription is, you know, there's
                    always that thing about where they say, ‘oh, we can never do this without
                    humans’ and I think it’s that thing about in DH of let machines do what machines
                    can do well and let humans do what humans do and creative work, creating a
                    textual environment where the automatic transcription can then be corrected and
                    improved but then simultaneously that leaves the scholar to focus on the task of
                    devising more interesting and intensive and hybridised and creative ways of
                    interpreting the text. So, I think that's a thing, there’s like two parallel
                    tracks of innovation, and I can really see that being something exciting. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> And the other thing for me is that I want to see is a fuller reckoning with the
                    spatial dimension of literary texts in the 21st digital edition, whatever that’s
                    going to be. James and I have done some work using Recogito for some travels and
                    tours to try and see what we can map in space as well in as well as in time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> And then I guess Recogito would be a perfect example of a real quantum leap in
                    just enabling anyone to do texture lamentation and to simultaneously spatially
                    annotate and do different types of markup on a text. But then once you’ve got
                    that ready, you then don’t have to keep reinventing the wheel, which I think is
                    a fairly common feature of early DH is that every problem required a bespoke
                    solution, but we’re really in an age now of burgeoning interoperability and I
                    think that’s one of the fruits of it and that’s where I can see like a lot of
                    the most exciting stuff happening. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you both and speaking of interoperability and research infrastructures,
                    are there developments in those areas, especially in research infrastructure
                    that you would like to see? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> You know, I’d like to see a team of research technologists appointed to the
                    College of Arts. Celtic Studies and Social Scienes at UCC and a significant
                    scaling up of our ability to support projects, both in terms of people but also
                    server space and proper support. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> That’s fair.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> If I were to imagine a kind of like utopian scenario for digital scholarly
                    editions and I think it’s not utopian, a better scenario, it would be one where
                    anyone who has sourced the text can easily transcribe or OCR it without needing
                    a huge amount of playback can easily get it into a machine readable format
                    without with the aid of things like say, you know, like the innovations and ease
                    of scanning and digitization, they can easily get hold of it, they can easily
                    get it into machine readable text. But then they can use something like Recogito
                    to interpret it and pars it and do whatever they need to but then they also have
                    access to a range of of-the-shelf ways of displaying that text, you know, like
                    beyond just sort of boiler plate TEI but they don’t then have to do an entire DH
                    project to have a good way of displaying their texts so they’re not on their own
                    any of those steps, there are existing tools that mainstreams the ability to do
                    a critical edition and if you bring down the overheads that means more people
                    could do it. </p>
                <p>Like in Medieval studies there’s this joke that the only people who do critical
                    editions anymore are retired people and monks because they don’t have to be paid
                    for it and I’m not even joking if you look at the number of Medieval Latin
                    translations it’s all monastics. Because part of their devotional activity and
                    they’re all like very accomplished Latinists who, it’s not just that that
                    they’re the equivalent, it’s part of their job, their lectio divina, is to
                    actually engage with Scripture and commentaries on Scripture, so a lot of it is
                    that but also retired scholars often go and say, well, there’s that’s edition
                    that I’ve been meaning to do my whole career and now I’m just going to do it.
                    But we shouldn’t be dependent on unpaid labour to do these things, I mean sure
                    I’d welcome that but anyone who wants to make one and can benefit from the full
                    sort of span of their experience because if you’re talking about footnotes and
                    annotations, I mean, what better time to do an authoritative critical edition
                    than right at the end of your career I mean but at the same time…</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> I don’t know James, that’s when your eyesight is terrible … (laughs)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> I mean, I guess like that it’s a thing that I think I can understand why it’s an
                    activity that is particularly appealing at that stage but at the same time it
                    shouldn’t be such a, I mean, we live in in a world of scarce academic resources
                    and the more that technology can bring the barriers down, the more that people
                    who want to do a critical edition can do one that that’s what I would wish for.
                </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> It’s so difficult: to undertake any kind of scholarly editing at scale requires
                    enormous resources and it does not happen outside of additional funding in the
                    contemporary university. I go to the example of nineteenth-century Irish authors
                    are not getting the same scholarly, critical, editorial, textual attention as
                    say the Scottish writers who are their contemporaries because Scottish
                    literature benefits from the AHRC research framework which acknowledges the
                    value of large-scale editorial projects that can be funded simply on their own
                    terms. We just don’t have funding schemes that recognise that kind of work at
                    the moment. And once we add in questions of infrastructure and sustainability
                    and longevity it adds to our challenges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> And just allowing it to be more quick and agile, I was reading a book review the
                    other day that kind of made me sad and obviously made the reviewer sad because
                    there’s this well-established series of like critical editions of Medieval
                    manuscripts in microfilm and microfiche format that is never going to be
                    finished. They were like ‘this is the last edition of that’, they didn’t get to
                    the end because it’s obsolete. And it’s like if those had been able to be done
                    more quickly … I mean, they said actually talking about apparatus actually the
                    quality of these editions is not in talking about microfiche it’s talking about
                    the sheer like the quality of the annotations basically so they’re saying we
                    should take all the annotations out of this series and add them to another text
                    like a digital text and that would be amazing. But if it had been able to be
                    done in another time, now or in future more quickly before microfiche became
                    quasi obsolete, then that could have been done on the fly a lot more and so
                    those amazing annotations and footnotes would still have survived but you know
                    that…</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> You remind me that when I began my own little bit of scholarly editing which I
                    did in the ‘90’s. So I was doing an edition of a novel and the novel went
                    through different changes and the author made different changes and the printer
                    made a few changes and so on and there were maybe three or four different
                    editions I had to go through and it was simply a matter of reading line by line,
                    you know, but one of my older colleagues then who is a bibliographer of some
                    renown showed me a sort of a tool he had which was like a kind of a slide rule
                    where you could, I forget what it was called, but you could put it down on the
                    page and you know you could use it to scan across and you know I was younger, I
                    had good eyesight I just used a ruler and I was perfectly fine without this but
                    there was a sense of kind of, you know, that’s not, it’s not the same kind of
                    technology, a ruler is not the same kind of technology as microfiche, but there
                    isn’t, you know scholarly editing was never innocent of technology or never
                    proceeding without an intimate relationship to the technology of its time kind
                    of, so yeah. It just seems to be an interesting cultural story there as well.
                </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> There’s just another interesting example of like trying to rapidly survey
                    something but then essentially like there’s the index of Middle English verse
                    and it’s like entries, XML form entries about different manuscripts with
                    Medieval verses and then it says like where it appears in the book and that’s
                    all that’s in each entry but basically, you could imagine if that’s being done
                    in different time, it could have the actual text as well and then interoperable
                    text could allow you to, if that’s all you wanted to show like where does it
                    appear and what’s the manuscript, you could have added that on top, but now you
                    can’t go back because that was all that was collected, you know. You’re painted
                    into a corner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Now that we’ve been talking about the ideal futures and outlook and great
                    wishes; Claire, you’re obviously a member of the Royal Irish Academy and do you
                    feel that a body such as the Royal Irish Academy what role do they play in
                    trying to bring this future about, of advancing the cause of editing and
                    publishing in Ireland?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> I’m not sure I can have enough of a bird’s eye view of the Academy to say
                    exactly, but there are obviously major projects for which it has responsibility
                    including the Clare Island Survey or the Dictionary of Irish Biography. It
                    sponsors particular knowledge exercises but sit also keeps an eye on scholarly
                    and critical developments including questions of Open Science and Open Access.
                </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> I guess one thing indirectly from that is that the Academy, as you said Claire
                    it shelters, projects of the Academy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CS">
                <speaker>CS</speaker>
                <p> Including DRI of course.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> That they are not themselves the Academy but benefit from it. And then I guess
                    that’s one thing the Academy has always been is a safe harbour for long-term
                    projects that wouldn’t survive in like the Historic Towns Atlas or like the
                    Biographies but they need someone who’s gonna say yeah, we’re going to back this
                    project forever because it’s of national importance but then you end up with
                    things like the Atlas still uses CD-ROM stuck in the back of it because that’s
                    part of the cost of rigour and long-term consistency is that sometimes you can’t
                    move as quickly, but at the same time the DRI host is hosted by the Academy
                    despite being its own organisation. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> I suppose if the question is anyone at a higher-level taking care of the fate of
                    the scholarly edition right now, I think nobody is. I don’t think the British
                    Academy is. Perhaps it will advance as part of Open Science.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> Yeah. And then, of course, the stake of losing digital material is massive, like
                    there’s many CD-ROM based critical editions of Medieval manuscripts done in the
                    ‘90’s that are no longer readable by modern computers. The format is completely
                    obsolete. They were made with like Macromedia Director or something like that
                    twenty years ago and they’re just completely unreadable. So, you actually then
                    have to start doing digital archaeology to extract the data and hope it’s not
                    partially corrupt, and add an entire level on top of that, assuming you even
                    have the original, you know. So, I guess there’s also been like, like you were
                    saying, Claire, I mean, the government just given that massive tranche of
                    funding to North like the Irish Open research framework and that’s going to make
                    a huge difference and really put Ireland up ahead, but that’s all about like
                    infrastructure and collaboration and high-level solutions that doesn’t mean that
                    anyone is taking any care of the edition specifically.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> And it just goes back to resources again. With all the OA debates, we’re not
                    talking about free publishing, we’re talking about publishing for where the
                    payment model is changing. You can’t really advance a discussion about editions
                    without tackling the question of how they’re going to be funded and I don’t
                    think there’s a great appetite for that at the moment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> But I guess then that makes it all the more important to create ways of bringing
                    down those costs of creating this stuff so that it can be more democratised, so
                    that editions can not only be created more easily but also then when they’re
                    created in an easier open format, they can become open data that’s archived so
                    by bringing down the levels that you need to actually make them in the first
                    place, that could have a fairly profound affect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> We’re coming to the end, is there anything else that you feel needs to be said
                    that we’ve missed out on our discussions so far?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#CC">
                <speaker>CC</speaker>
                <p> You’re making me think I’d like to get back to doing scholarly editing
                    Michael.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#JS">
                <speaker>JS</speaker>
                <p> I have one thing to say which I think is that there needs to be room for things
                    that are just pure blue sky thinking, like with Deep Map editions that are just
                    purely experimental and are frankly just kind of bizarre. Like it doesn’t matter
                    if they’re bizarre and like unusual because they’re an experiment in a form and
                    then they can be like, I guess the original of Deep Maps were like that, I mean
                    it’s ok for something to be gonzo and a bit bizarre and eccentric if it achieves
                    an artistic vision or a creative vision because then it can be used for other
                    purposes. So I think my thing is that I wouldn’t want critical editions to
                    become kind of utilitarian to workman, like not have that kind of spark, that
                    ability for them to be just like, I mean you can take existing open data and do
                    something strange with it but I think that you can’t cut out experimentation at
                    different levels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you both.</p>
            </sp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
