<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Dirk Van Hulle</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  Michael Kurzmeier		 on March 7th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_MK_DV.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>DIRK VAN HULLE is Professor of Bibliography and Modern Book History at the University of Oxford, director of the Oxford Centre for Textual Editing and Theory (OCTET) and of the Centre for Manuscript Genetics at the University of Antwerp. With Mark Nixon, he is director of the Beckett Digital Manuscript Project (www.beckettarchive.org), series editor of the Cambridge UP series ‘Elements in Beckett Studies’ and editor of the Journal of Beckett Studies. His publications include Textual Awareness (2004), Modern Manuscripts (2014), Samuel Beckett’s Library (2013, with Mark Nixon), The New Cambridge Companion to Samuel Beckett (2015), James Joyce’s Work in Progress (2016), the Beckett Digital Library, several genetic editions in the Beckett Digital Manuscript Project, and Genetic Criticism (OUP, 2022).</p></div></front><body><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Just to start out very broadly, could you maybe say a few words about what the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	That’s an easy one to start with – I’m being ironic here. I think, for me the main aim of scholarly editing is to make available in my case modern manuscripts that are hard to find or hard to get access to a broad audience in a way that allows them to check what the editor did with the material, if there are transcriptions involved, and that’s why I also think that the digital medium is such a great medium to do this with.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	What do you think digital editions do well and what might be done better? What do you see as the difference between the digital and let’s say print scholarly editions?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	I think the print scholarly editions are of course a wonderful tool and we should continue making them. For me personally, the advantage of digital is that it is easier to make connections between the different versions because the print paradigm, if you can call it that, has to some extent and understandably conditioned us to some degree into thinking that we need to make single reading texts and then provide all the information about the various versions and textual variants at the back of the book, whereas I think in Germany they call it a Variantenfriedhof, a cemetery of variants. So, we sort of unwittingly buried the variance at the back of the book, whereas I think one of the aims of scholarly editing should be that we bring the variants to life, that we show people that there are differences between versions and that this is not a problem, but that that is what makes it interesting. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Absolutely agree there and then much of your work is on genetic criticism, I wonder if you might explain what that is very briefly.</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	Genetic criticism does not necessarily try to make one reading text. Its main aim is the study of the writing process, so it is important for genetic criticism, if you want to share what you find in the in the archive, to present all the variants that you found, and all the versions, all the versions of all the texts that you’re studying. So, I think there’s a difference between genetic criticism and genetic editing and many genetic critics don’t even try to be editors, and that’s absolutely fine, they’re just interested in studying the dynamics of the writing process. But I do think that they are very related to each other because of course if you’re studying the writing process of an author that not many people know and whose manuscripts are hard to find, then if you want to make a point about something, I think it’s important to be able to share what you found. If nobody knows about this, then you’re rather alone and isolated. That’s why I think genetic editing has a very good function. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. And to what extent do you think that digital tools and platforms have changed the way in which this genetic criticism was specifically or specifically text criticism is done? Do you think it has become easier to perform this kind of analysis with digital tools?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	Well, I’d like to believe that that’s the case. In Beckett studies, for instance, I do think it has changed it little bit. I have the impression that people increasingly take manuscript material into account in various kinds of criticism, not only genetic criticism. This has become more self-evident in the sense that it’s just part of what you have available as tools. In the past, when you went to an archive and you said something about a manuscript, you were almost automatically placed in the kind of category of bibliographers or book historians, whereas now, you can actually just go to the Samuel Beckett: Digital Manuscript Project, have a look, and if it’s interesting to you, you just integrate it in your scholarship. I hope that that is a trend that will continue and that it will become more just part of the tools that we have to do criticism in general, literary criticism I mean. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Great. Thank you, and yes, the Beckett Project is of course something else that we want to talk about so you are obviously one of the Directors on the Samuel Beckett: Digital Manuscript Project, could you tell us a little bit more about that project and its general scope? </p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	Yeah, so in Beckett Studies there are more than a dozen holding libraries that hold manuscripts by Beckett and many of these holding libraries hold material by Beckett that Beckett donated to them, which sort of indicates that he certainly did not have a problem with people doing this kind of genetic study on his work, but you could even say that in some cases he seemed to have encouraged us to do that. But of course, it’s spread over more than 12 holding libraries in the world so if you are interested in, say, Krapp’s Last Tape, you have to travel at least to three or four holding libraries on either side of the Atlantic and that was our initial impulse or motivation to make the Samuel Beckett Digital Management Project. It was really a project to bring together all that material digitally. And from the very start, we’ve been sort of in doubt whether we were an archive or an edition, you know, a digital archive or digital edition. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Can you elaborate on that distinction between archive and edition?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	We are working on it and it’s an ongoing process of course. But I think we are moving more and more towards a digital edition and of course that means that I have to sort of define the difference for myself. I would say the difference between a digital archive and a digital edition is that the digital edition makes connections. You already have an archive if you put all the images online; you present it to the Beckett Community, and that in itself would already be very, very valuable. That’s what we did in the beginning. But then we added transcriptions, and then we added the personal library by Beckett; we saw that there were connections between what he was reading and what he was writing. So, you make those connections, and I think the connections turn it into an edition.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. I was wondering, when you think back to the origins, so maybe the design phase of that digital manuscript project, what were the key design decisions that come to mind? Were there any crucial decisions that were made early on in this project about how the edition should be? </p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	Yes, actually it is that old, you could say, that in the beginning we didn’t even think it would be possible to include digital facsimiles. The project started off by me going to Reading to the archive and making transcriptions in situ so on the spot in TEI XML. We thought in the beginning that that was what it was going to be, a website with the transcriptions of all the manuscripts that we could find, and in that sense it’s perhaps a little bit comparable, perhaps with the James Joyce Digital Archive because that also doesn’t have any facsimiles. But very early on, we also started talking to one of the other holding libraries, the Harry Ransom Centre, and they were happy to provide scans for us to make the transcriptions, and then we thought, well, this is our moment, we need to ask the Beckett Estate whether that would be a good idea and then actually we had a very good conversation with the Beckett Estate and they supported us in what we did, even though it is copyright material and it’s all very delicate, of course, but they did support us. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Great. Can I maybe ask a follow up question here? When you said you weren’t sure if you could include facsimile, was that a technical limitation or was it just maybe more a question of availability?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	I think, it’s hard to say but I think in the beginning we just didn’t think of it. It’s very hard for me to remember. It’s a long time ago.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	You said you transcribed them in situ so that sounds to me that obviously there was no one source for scans. Was something to start out with that just availability was a problem then? </p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	I mean you have to remember that when I went to Reading for the first time, they did not have the special collections as they have now. They were located in the basement of the library and when you went there as a scholar, they would first give you a black and white photocopy to work with, as most of the material was not scanned or digitised. I think that was part of it. And when we went to the Harry Ransom Centre, they had more money and they were in the process of digitising everything and I think it was Tom Staley, at that moment, who said that their motto was ‘visibility’. So, instead of seeing the archive as something that keeps the manuscript, it was seen as something that shows the manuscript. So, we were there at an interesting moment, in the development of thinking about archives because we were doing what they wanted to do with their manuscripts, namely, reach out. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	I have one more technical question and that is; was XML a decision that you made from the start? Did you give that much thought? How come you decided to use XML transcriptions? </p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	That was my decision. I wanted to work with TEI because, I think it was in ’97, I attended one of the, possibly even the, first TEI Summer School Workshop at Oxford, with Lou Burnard. I was working on Finnegans Wake at that moment, but then I discovered Beckett and I thought: perhaps I can apply this to Beckett, and that’s what I did, I went to the basement in the library of the University of Reading and then I just tried to apply what I had learnt with the TEI. So, the TEI was first, even before the images. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Just one more general question about this, if you want to start this again, what would you do differently about this project? </p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	I think I would not necessarily have started with the compartmentalisation into different works. So now you can go to the website and if you are interested in Endgame, you can see all the manuscripts of Endgame. I think that’s still a good way to proceed, but I do think that it is also informed or conditioned by the print medium because in the print medium, you also think in terms of let’s say ten volumes for the complete Works editions and volume six is Endgame and you get all the materials that relate to Endgame over there. But working more and more on the Beckett project I see how he is really an oeuvre writer in the sense that it’s a long process. He saw his work as one long process, and therefore it’s important to indicate or to give the tools to readers to see how certain projects coincided or were written in tandem, that there is interaction between those works. And so that you don’t necessarily have to present everything in terms of neat compartments so to speak. There are also many works that didn’t lead anywhere, that are still unfinished. In the manuscript he worked on them for four versions or so, and they were never published. So in a way, I would like to try and find a way – and that’s what we’re doing at this moment – to find a less teleological way of presenting it, if I can put it like that. The teleological way would be to start with every word that made it into a publication, that’s the starting point. And next to that you would have a non-teleological presentation that says okay, we’re going to just look at what we have, the material, just give me all the notebooks, even if they never led to anything. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Could we speak about some of the key points in your Practical Guide to Digital Genetic Editing. As we talked about digital genetic criticism earlier, and I just wondered if you could say few words about this one, this practical guide?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	I was writing a book on genetic criticism, which consists of two parts: ‘genetic’ and ‘criticism’. The genetic part is more technical than the second part. It became gradually more and more specific and I thought, okay, if you are a student and you want to make a digital genetic edition, it may be helpful to know how you could go about doing it: this is one way you could do it, this is the way we have done it. I thought of it as just a practical guide because this is our experience that we share. It’s certainly not the way to do it or anything, it’s just the way we have done it and if you think it’s useful, go ahead and apply it if you want. So that was my main rationale behind it, nothing special. But then of course, it became so specific and so, a little bit too technical, I think, that I decided to just take it out of the book and develop it a little bit with Wout Dillen and Vincent Neyt who were working in Antwerp and just put it on the website. That’s the history behind it. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Great. Thank you and maybe building on from that, how did you find teaching digital scholarly editing or even teaching genetic criticism?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	I think there’s a difference between two types of students here. My students in Oxford here don’t have a digital humanities background and I do think that it is important for them to be aware of the existence of digital scholarly editions, so I make it part of my course on material texts in which I present them with many different disciplines, bibliography, book history, textual criticism, genetic criticism but also digital scholarly editing. It is not very easy to convince them that they can actually do this and can make their own edition because of course I don’t have enough time to explain everything. But I do spend at least three hours or four hours with them on making a small-scale collation or something, or a transcription that they can visualise. They do appreciate it, but of course they are trained to be critics, so when it comes to writing an essay, they will choose something that is closer to what they have learned before, closer to a literary criticism type of essay. But I also teach digital scholarly editing in a Summer School in Antwerp and this year the summer school in Oxford, the Digital Humanities Summer School in Oxford asked me to present the Samuel Beckett: Digital Management Project in their TEI section and I’m sure that there the audience is quite different. After a week they want to be able to do it themselves, so that’s a different audience.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	And building onto that, what lessons have you learnt about how we may better approach this pedagogical aspect of digital editing, you already mentioned different types of students, would you like to see a deeper integration into a course?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	I think what would help is a kind of environment, a virtual research environment VRE, something like that, that would help students visualise what they do behind the scenes in TEI. That is something they all want. They’re learning something, they’re learning a new language, a markup language, and it goes very fast and that’s all fine. They get the principle, but then they want to see what they’ve done. You could apply perhaps TEI publisher, but that did not work very well for me because I’m dealing with genetic material and you need to make many connections. So a virtual research environment that would make it easy for non-specialists to make the connections between the documents that they found, that would be cool. That would really help pedagogically. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Have you attempted something like this? </p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	Not personally, but a PhD student of mine, Joshua Schäuble did.  He wrote his PhD on manuscript web, a kind of virtual research environment that we had in mind and he developed it to a large degree, but it’s not finished. In the future, it may turn out to take the shape of a more modular ‘toolkit’ for genetic editions. We continue working on it and see where we land. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	And then just to zoom out a little bit more, so reflecting on the wider fields of digital scholarly editing and publishing what are we missing or rather what do you think the field needs? </p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	More work on sustainability. That’s the most important thing at this moment, I think, and the library is where my hope lies. I can’t see any other type of institution that could take better care of this task. I mean, the publishers won’t do it. We’re talking about institutions that will be there for many years, many centuries hopefully. So I hope that we can work together with libraries to achieve this. Personally, I’m not technically skilled enough to come up with great ideas here, but I think together we will probably be able to find a way to preserve those links that I was talking about, the connections. What is easy at this moment is to reduce everything that you created back to an archive, just the images and the transcriptions perhaps. But that is such a loss. It is the whole edition that you have created, all the connections that you have made; it’s those connections that need to be preserved and that is something we really need to work on. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Could you maybe say a bit more about what you mean by sustainability? You mentioned some technical aspects and you mentioned some preservation aspects. I was wondering what exactly do you mean by sustainability?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	Mainly preservation actually, so that what you create – and we put a lot of money and effort in it – will be available to future scholars. When, for instance, Mark Nixon and I are not around anymore, the Samuel Beckett: Digital Management Project might still be useful. If I don’t find a host for this project, a long-term host, we might not be able to host it, let alone update it and maintain it. Because of course all the software that is being used needs to be updated constantly. That’s all I meant by sustainability. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you very much. And then just finally as a very open question so what would ideally, what would a future digital edition look like to you?</p></sp><sp who="#DV"><speaker>DV</speaker><p>	On the one hand, digital scholarly editions have been around for quite a while but at the same time everyone knows that we’re just at the very beginning of a totally new medium, so I think we should give ourselves some time to find our bearings here in this new medium. I’m sure there will be many, many forms that people will come up with and what we have done so far is probably still conditioned to some degree by the print paradigm. We’re gradually growing away from it and finding new stuff and that’s good. I think we’ll need so many different kinds of editions. I’m making genetic editions, but that’s just one type of a hundred types that you could come up with as potential editions. Editions of Twitter accounts or editions of emails or so. I’m involved in the James Joyce Correspondence project, so a letters edition dealing with old material on paper, but we also need to think about how to make editions of recent, born-digital correspondence. They will be completely different. I can’t start enumerating all the various forms that will emerge, but that’s very good and I hope your project will contribute to that. </p></sp></body></text></TEI>