<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>C21 Editions: Roberto Rosselli</title>
                <title type="sub">Interview conducted by Michael Kurzmeier on March 21th,
                    2022</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Unpublished working draft</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels. (2023).
                        <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions [Data
                        files].</title> Available from <ref
                        target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions"
                        >https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_MK_RR.xml
                    downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>$today</date>Header added</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div>
                <head>Interviewee bio</head>
                <p>ROBERTO ROSSELLI is Associate Professor in the Department of Humanities, School
                    of Humanities, University of Turin, Italy.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Just to get started with the conversation, could you maybe say a few words about
                    what the terms digital scholarly editing and digital publishing mean to you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> They mean a lot to me, in fact I started being interested in digital scholarly
                    editing when I first saw the Electronic Beowulf edition by Kevin Kiernan which
                    was published in 1999. Because of that, I got interested in digital scholarly
                    editing and started investigating about creating a similar digital edition of a
                    very important manuscript, which is known as the Vercelli Book. So, it was a
                    long journey learning about semantic annotation and, after making good progress
                    with the TEI encoding of the files to be used in my digital edition, I
                    discovered that the tools available at the time, I’m talking about 2007 or so,
                    were not so suitable to achieve the goals I had stated. Therefore, I also had to
                    include digital publishing among the new methods to learn and I created my own
                    tool to display digital editions, EVT.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> And you have also written extensively about digital editions and there is an
                    essay from 2016, The Battle We Forgot to Fight: Should We Make a Case for
                    Digital Editions? And in that essay, you write; We are at a crucial moment in
                    the evolution of digital scholarly editing: if we wanted to succeed, to be
                    accepted by our own colleagues, we should continue to discuss and improve its
                    fundamental methodologies, not only amongst us ‘pioneers’, but also with the
                    numerous scholars who may be interested in adopting such methods, and I have
                    thus far refrained from doing so because of the many hurdles they assume they
                    have to overcome. I wonder if you might reflect on this matter a little bit and
                    especially how you feel things have changed since that crucial moment in 2016 as
                    you described?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> I think that things have changed a lot, but I’m not entirely happy with the
                    current scenario. Let me explain myself better: I think that now we have many
                    more tools, we have a standard methodology to create digital editions and there
                    are many, many digital editions being published every year. But I don’t think
                    everything is all well and good because I think that there are still many
                    problems unsolved. My point of view, as I tried to make before in my very short
                    introduction, is that of the lone scholar, because when I started working on the
                    Digital Vercelli Book I had no substantial financial means to take it to an end,
                    and the situation has remained the same for most early career researchers today.
                    I always try, even if now I have more research money, to think as a PhD student,
                    for instance, or as a person who’s right now starting to delve into digital
                    matters. And I can see that there has been very interesting progress on the
                    technological front. There are several new research methods, such as linked open
                    data, ontologies, processing of the edition data, which will enable new insights
                    about the texts being edited. But things have become also more complicated for
                    the lone scholar, because it is really difficult to master all these
                    technologies. I can see that there are a good number of colleagues of mine who
                    might be interested in joining the ‘digital revolution’, but they really are
                    afraid of doing so because they always ask me, ‘how long is it going to take to
                    learn doing this or that?’ And of course, if about 15 years ago learning
                    semantic annotation was almost all you had to do, now things are much more
                    complicated, and it really depends on what you want to do with your edition. In
                    a way, you have much more power now to decide how to shape your DSE, you can
                    pursue many new research directions, but it also is very much complicated for
                    someone who is starting right now. Also, I don’t know if you have heard about
                    the Digital Scholarly Editions Manifesto which has been launched recently at the
                    German DH conference: I think that, while being a very worthwhile initiative, it
                    also is sort of a symptom that the battle still has to be fought, because one of
                    its goals is to reaffirm that digital editions are important. And they are
                    important as a means to know more about the texts you’re publishing, because
                    they are better as a research tool than a printed the traditional edition, etc.,
                    basic facts that we know well. But if you have to repeat that, it also means
                    that not everybody accepts it as a fact. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> I was wondering, do you think because there are so many tools available, would
                    that lead to a situation where projects are more and more alike because people
                    get to pick and choose tools more so than they have to develop them
                    themselves?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> Yeah, that’s a good question. In theory, yes, but I also regard as valid the
                    distinction made by Elena Pierazzo between the prêt-à-porter edition and the
                    haute-couture one, where the haute-couture is a software tool or a sophisticated
                    web site which has been specifically created and/or customized for a digital
                    edition project. At the present moment I see that there may be people resorting
                    to standard tools, but also there are many projects which are going to go the
                    other way because they feel that only by means of a customized design or use of
                    specific research tools the goals of that edition project can be eventually
                    achieved. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you. You have already mentioned the Digital Vercelli Book and could you
                    say a little bit about that project? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> Yes, well, that was my first digital project, and it isn’t finished yet, alas. I
                    think that also may tell something about the liquid state of many digital
                    editions, if you want. It isn’t finished because while I worked on the project,
                    I started another project about the software tool I mentioned to be used with
                    the Digital Vercelli Book, and then this led to many collaborations with
                    different projects which wanted to customise this tool for their own purposes.
                    So, it has been a bit distracting, the project is in good shape, I mean that I
                    have all the text files ready and the images, everything, I’m just waiting for
                    the final version of the EVT to publish the project. This is an important
                    manuscript because there are only four manuscripts which hold about 90% of all
                    the Old English period poetry and this is the only one which is preserved
                    outside pre-printing. So, it is a particularly interesting case in itself. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you and maybe going from there to the other editions that you have worked
                    on, I would like to know was there any key decisions relating to the data format
                    analysis, modelling or publishing that were taken during those projects? What
                    were the key decisions on those fields? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> Almost all the key decisions were TEI related, as you can imagine, and TEI is a
                    great tool and it is a really rich data format for text encoding, although it
                    has its limits. One of the projects we collaborated with is the Codice
                    Pelavicino Digitale (http://pelavicino.labcd.unipi.it/) where they used the TEI
                    markup in a different way. Even if it was a diplomatic transcription of a
                    medieval manuscript, they did things completely different compared to the
                    Digital Vercelli Book, which meant that we had to adapt the software to display
                    the text sometimes in a completely different way. For instance, you can have a
                    &lt;front&gt; element in the TEI data structure which is usually used to host an
                    introduction to the edited text. When working with historical documents, on the
                    other hand, that element contains a regesto, i.e. a summary of the document
                    content, and since it is really formalised, we had to analyse a completely
                    different structure to be able to parse the XML content and to produce a
                    corresponding output that is readable and understandable for the historians. I
                    could not say this is really unusual, in fact when you work with TEI you might
                    produce different markup for many different purposes, which is the case with
                    Codice Pelavicino Digitale. Another interesting case is that of a project named
                    VaSto (https://dharc-org.github.io/progetto-vasto/), this is an edition where
                    people customized EVT by expanding the CSS rules in the style sheets so that
                    they might add marginalia and other features to their edition of the manuscript
                    text. I think that there is a great potential in encoded texts, and that the
                    tools have to be adapted to be more receptive to this richness. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you and then building on tools, could you tell me something about the EVT,
                    the Edition Visualisation Technology, that was developed as part of the Vercelli
                    project and especially why did you feel the need to develop such a tool? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> As I hinted before, it was because I did a survey of the available tools about
                    2007-08, about that time some of these tools were difficult to use and/or
                    proprietary software, in fact I have been offered a software which had been used
                    for another edition and it was an interesting software, but I wasn’t allowed to
                    modify and redistribute it, for instance, which is why I turned it down. I also
                    tested the TEI style sheets which were very simple to use but quite limited,
                    f.i. you could not have text and image alignment which is essential for a
                    digital facsimile with an accompanying transcription. And I also tried eXist-db,
                    at the time there was no ready to use graphical front end. To make a long story
                    short, it was really a problem to find a tool which could offer what I needed in
                    a relatively simple way. Again, at the time I was the lone scholar, with limited
                    resources, besides it was also important to have an open-source tool so that I
                    could modify it and possibly share my changes with other people. So, when I
                    decided to try and start such a project, the tool was designed to be flexible,
                    free and open source right from the start. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you and then staying with the topic of tools for a moment, you also
                    published a paper on using 3D content in digital editions and I would really
                    like to hear your thoughts on this if you could speak a bit more about this
                    work. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> Okay that’s interesting because I was looking at that just a couple of days ago.
                    It’s been an exciting experiment, and I want to have this sort of functionality
                    in EVT, but it is not as simple as for other normal edition components. Let me
                    explain, we are considering, for instance, to implement the concept of the
                    distributed edition, meaning that part of the content, be it text or images or
                    other material, could be served somewhere on the internet, and we only had to
                    retrieve it so that it can be ‘injected’ into the viewer and displayed. We are
                    considering using for instance Zenodo for some of that work, also because Zenodo
                    offers permanent IDs, which is quite an important feature, and we are also
                    considering how to improve support for the IIIF functionality in EVT. We
                    experimented with 3D because we added a 3DHOP view to EVT. 3DHOP is an excellent
                    3D model viewer, the problem there is that you cannot rely on distributed
                    models, for instance you cannot serve a 3D model from Zenodo because it would be
                    really slow, it wouldn’t be suitable. This means that you have to keep
                    everything 3D on the server, but also this means that you have to carefully
                    decide the level of compromise between level of detail and downloading time,
                    because a 3D model is really heavy in terms of space and also of time to
                    download. So even if 3DHOP is such a great tool and even if this first
                    experiment was mainly successful, we are waiting for some breakthrough either in
                    Zenodo or in other technologies to share 3D models and load them into EVT. But
                    it works, I can assure you, and we are looking forward to implementing it in EVT
                    3. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Great. Thank you. And do you think that the present digital editions are
                    sufficiently multimodal then or do you think that all editions could benefit
                    from something like a 3D content?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> No, not every edition of course. Two things, one is that the 3D model would be
                    needed in the Digital Vercelli Book in connection to a specific poem, The Dream
                    of the Rood, which is also preserved on a monumental stone Cross. The goal is to
                    compare the original documents, be they something as traditional as a manuscript
                    and something that you need 3D viewer to browse. Also, The Dream of the Rood
                    version on the Ruthwell Cross is preserved in runic characters, so that also
                    calls for special attention. But this is a really special case, you might be
                    more interested in considering a manuscript parchment as a 3D object that is a
                    completely different research, it also is a very interesting one, but it is not
                    something I’m looking into right now. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> I also wanted to talk about a tutorial that you wrote on designing a graphic
                    user interface for digital editions and I would like to hear what you feel the
                    key points are that one must consider when designing a user interface for
                    digital edition. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> Well, first of all you have to consider that what you are going to publish will
                    also be the point to first impact for any kind of audience. So, what we always
                    tried to do is to keep EVT as simple as possible, which doesn’t mean that it
                    can’t be powerful, it means that you have to design the user interface in such a
                    way that it is easy to access the more powerful functionality. At the same time,
                    you don’t want it to be intimidating, you're not going to see lots of buttons,
                    f.i. with single characters on them to recall specific functionalities, because
                    that is also something that requires you to learn a lot while browsing the
                    edition; this is not the best way to design a user interface. And during the
                    years we have now three versions of the EVT software, we are working on the
                    third one. We always kept the usual display layout, dividing the space on a
                    computer screen in two parts, one part for the main object and a second part for
                    accompanying material, such as the apparatus frame or the transcription text, if
                    you’re looking at digital facsimile, and so on. Really simple and we have been
                    adding a stuff but without overloading the interface… or so I hope. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you. And then building on that, I’d like to see, do you feel there is a
                    tension between digital scholarly editing and the print model, especially when
                    it comes to the format and the presentation. Do you think digital scholarly
                    editions are maybe too closely oriented on the print model or has that changed?
                </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> Well, they’re trying to get free. And I would go back to what I was saying that
                    they are trying to spread their roots on the internet, for instance adopting the
                    distributed edition model, so that the digital print paradigm doesn’t apply
                    anymore. The problem is that even if we have infinite space in storing an
                    edition data, we have exactly the same kind of surface that you use in the
                    printed edition, which means we have a 2D environment where space really is
                    precious, so you have to think carefully about how to use it. And this also
                    means that it is inevitable that in some way there will always be something of a
                    printed edition in a digital one. I don’t think this is an easily solved
                    problem, even if you would think of 3D interfaces which have been attempted in
                    the past but have been discontinued because they were more hassle than useful, I
                    think. Also, another concept that I think it would be interesting to have is
                    digital editions and printed editions coexisting peacefully, because I don’t
                    think that DSEs are going to get better than printed editions in a very
                    important aspect which is that of portability, unless you consider perhaps
                    mobile devices. But even there, the fact that I can pick up a book and take it
                    with me everywhere and even if there is no charge or no electricity or no
                    internet, that is really unbeatable. And the fact that I wouldn’t advise anyone
                    about reading texts on a computer screen for a long time because just it is not
                    healthy. I think that a digital edition is first of all a research tool and
                    under that aspect it is a better tool than a printed edition. But printed
                    editions have their advantages as well, so I don’t think that that is going to
                    change. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> And to stay with that point, are there particular design methodologies that you
                    feel are particularly suited to digital editions? You mentioned a few in terms
                    of portability and maybe accessibility for the print editions. Is there
                    something that you see that a digital edition does particularly well too? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> Well, the thing that a digital edition does really better than a printed edition
                    is data processing, because with the printed edition you (the reader) do all the
                    processing, but with a digital edition you can have the viewing tool doing also
                    stuff for you. For instance, producing concordances or doing analysis or
                    producing lists of named entities, or sophisticated data queries, we are looking
                    into that for the next EVT version, and I think that’s a promising research area
                    because there is so much that you can do with TEI files. When I started encoding
                    the Vercelli Book text, I used the TEI method based on elements from the gaiji
                    module to encode special characters: at the time I wasn’t sure if it was going
                    to be needed for the project, but I knew that it might be useful for people
                    doing palaeography research. Now we are developing a library which is going to
                    make calculations and build statistics to see how special characters are used in
                    different quires of the manuscript, to see if something is a specific scribal
                    habit or maybe it is due to the copy which is being transcribed by the scribe,
                    so that you can do palaeography research even under that aspect. This is just an
                    example of what you can do with TEI markup. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you. And then looking at the wider field of digital publishing, is there
                    something that you feel the field is missing? Is there a development that you
                    think you would like to see in the field of digital publishing and editions?
                </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> Well, I’m not really in the position to discuss about digital publishing at
                    large. What I miss would be for a way for digital editions to talk to each
                    other. I know there are some specific protocols, such as Canonical Text Services
                    and others, but in the end, one particular aspect of printed editions which is
                    still valid for their digital counterparts, which I don’t like very much, is the
                    fact that even the best digital editions are often islands in the great Internet
                    sea. So, it would be useful to have a sort of middle layer, something like Mesa,
                    which it is a framework accepting digital resources and then allowing for a
                    distributed search within those resources. That is something that I would like
                    to have. And also, at the present moment we have two competing standards, CTS
                    and DTS, I would like to have just one good standard that I could use to make
                    the textual data of my edition easily available. That is another aspect which
                    is, I think, a really a nice development, the fact that you can share
                    immediately all the work you’ve done and it would be nice to transform all the
                    edition components in linked open data so that other people can access and use
                    them freely. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#MK">
                <speaker>MK</speaker>
                <p> Thank you very much. And then lastly, is there something that you feel we have
                    not mentioned that needs to be mentioned in the context of this interview? So,
                    anything else that you’d like to add before we stop the recording? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp who="#RR">
                <speaker>RR</speaker>
                <p> Well, something that I would like to mention is the problem of text
                    representation: as I said the TEI is a great tool, but it relies, as we know, on
                    XML and so you have the technical baggage of XML, meaning that you cannot have
                    overlapping hierarchies without resorting to some ‘workarounds’, for instance,
                    which is perhaps the main problem of TEI. It is not an unsurmountable problem, I
                    think, because I’m doing that, but it will be interesting to have in the future
                    at some point a text representation tool, which is designed by and for
                    Humanists, and not as an abstract text containing structure, which is really
                    easily processable by software. At the present moment, however, I cannot but
                    conclude that TEI is the base and sort of a de facto standard for the job. While
                    that is my conclusion, I would love to see something better emerge. </p>
            </sp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
