<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  James Cummings</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on September 28th, 2021</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_JC.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>JAMES CUMMINGS is the Senior Lecturer in Late Medieval Literature and Digital Humanities in the School of English Literature, Language, and Linguistics at Newcastle University. He specialises in late-medieval drama and the use of the Guidelines of the Text Encoding Initiative for the encoding and publication of digital scholarly editions.  </p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Well, I mean obviously there’s been a lot of ink spilled on that and ah, I could come up with something but I’ll try and be careful with my words, let’s see…so a scholarly edition is a representation or re-presentation of a historical text that follows some sort of a consistent and explicit principles in how it goes about making that text accessible to its readers. Does that sound good?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It certainly does…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	You know, I mean, it’s always re-presenting text its always historical texts, I mean what text isn’t historical one could argue, the sort of decision making about consistent and explicit principles, I think, is the key editorial aspect. I guess there are some cases where you might have a more authoritative scholarly edition where it’'s like everyone agrees it’s an acceptable surrogate for some set of original documents, you know, and it’s like a community of readers all say ‘ok this is stable and reliable, we accept that’, I guess that’s another level of edition or level of scholarly edition because you can have a scholarly edition that’s scholarly done that just nobody uses.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That idea of authority is interesting… In an age where people are increasingly doing things around curation and editing, because it’s so easy to do now and there are so many tools and platforms that make edition-making is much more accessible, what are the repercussions for this idea of authority in an editorial sense?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	I think there’s a… it all sort of comes down to responsibility, like, there’s a responsibility of the editor to be intellectually honest in their representation or re-presentation of that text, they have to, as I said, do so in a way that’s consistent and applies certain principles that they’re doing so in a transparent way. I chafe entirely against, I don’t know, a way in which people marking an edition and saying ‘Yes! This edition is a good edition’ even though I’m tangentially involved in a project that the MLA did that do. You know, it’s certification of editions is something that I think is… it’s not the right way to go about it, I mean, I guess we had that sort of sense of authority with print editions with publishers choosing to publish it or not but, you know, even centuries ago there was still vanity publishing, so, you know, maybe not. I think what it comes down to is those readers, it’s those people as a community of readers deciding that ‘this is something that we trust’ and that’s really where the authority comes from it comes from its grass roots rather than imposed from above. I mean obviously something print or digital published by well-known institutions or recognised by well-known scholarly societies and bodies is going to get that acceptance more easily.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s interesting that, in all of the interviews we’ve done, I believe you’re the first person to really mention authority…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	I guess we may have things where you have editions that somehow, I don’t know, somehow intentionally misrepresent texts or history. I think that’s relatively rare. I’m not sure why someone would put in the effort I mean, I guess, yeah, ok to try and prove some other point, but… Richard III was a nice guy, he didn’t kill the Princes in the Tower. I’m trying to think of like, you know… Like I mean fakes and forgeries I get but we don’t normally tend to think about those when we’re talking about scholarly editions, you know. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Representation versus misrepresentation… how do you as an expert this think about it? At what point does editorial expertise become misrepresentation? You know, when you think of Gabler’s Joyce, and say, the naming of episodes… </p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Yeah, which then become, by unwitting readers, become the name of the episodes. The kind of, I don’t know, the synchronic edition by Gabler is interesting, not being a Joyce expert and talking to somebody in Ireland, I’m not going to comment on Joyce, you know! I’m a Medievalist, I should say that, so my viewpoint of type of edition is often really very philological and textual (graphemic) so the idea of, for example, naming a section of it or providing a section title, subtitle, chapter titles, things like that, that aren’t in the original without there being some transparent indication to the reader that this is editorially supplied material is anathema to me I can’t picture… like except in very particular types of, I don’t know, texts like an acting edition of a play or something like that, where at that stage you don’t care whether it was provided by an editor or not but in the scholarly edition to have things where it’s been normalised by the editor or provided by the editor without there being some indication of that. So, that can be where I’ve normalised the spelling of these kinds of words throughout the entire edition and that’s just a note at the beginning of an editorial principles section, fine fair enough, but, you know, I would put things in italics or square brackets depending on style guides to say ‘look I’ve stuck this in here’.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is originality, however contested or outmoded that concept may be, important in editing? </p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	That is a loaded question isn’t it. I… because one is doing an edition of a text, I think you have a responsibility to clarify and make accessible your best understanding of that text. I mean editing, like markup, is always about interpretation so it’s always about my reading of those characters on the manuscript, you know, ‘I think it says this’. Now, if I’m being honest and transparent then I should include a note that says well I think it says this but James O’Sullivan says it’s this and I think he’s wrong because when he said that he was drunk and I’ve seen the original and he’s only seen it through a microfilm. I can justify my reasoning but I should… skimming over things and just presenting my point of view I think is unscholarly.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Thank you…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	I’m not sure that really answered the question…</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	No no, it does, and I like that idea of transparency. When you think of the edition, the field of editing, what is done well and what might be done better?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Well I guess… ok so, if a scholarly edition is doing that stuff, undertaking those tasks to produce an edition the thing that’s key I think is the considered decision making about how to present or understand you know individual bits of text, words, phrases, lines, chapters, whatever, so I guess when people think of editions they think of multi-witness critical editions I mean I, like a lot of people in the pre-modern age, like, I tend to deal with texts that only have one extent copy so you’re not rationalising a textual apparatus across many different witnesses. You might be looking at many previous editions of a work but it’s that decision making, so if I OCR a printed text or probably more crucially for our discourse for the next decade if you’re talking about the future of editions if I HTR, Handwritten Text Recognition of some handwritten manuscript then I say that’s not an edition but a form of transcription because like Google Books or HTR or whatever they’ve not undertaken the consideration of those individual bits of text, they’ve not said well what might be necessary to make this bit of text truly accessible to my readers. So that’s sort of what I think about when I think about what editors are doing and what an edition is. I guess, you asked what they do well, right?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yes, what’s done well and what could be better?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	In print editions especially, they collect together those textual variations, provide a stable text that people can refer to, express the interpretations and understanding of the editor, hopefully provide some kind of background information… yeah, I guess they’re good at bringing all of that together and I guess print editions especially force a decision of a sort of primary reading, that sort of choice of best text if that’s what you’re doing and that’s sort of enforced by the nature of the medium. So even if you get print text where you’re printing things in multiple versions in parallel columns it’s still affected by the very fixed affordances in the nature of print. So, print editions then are very good at forcing the condensing of the information into a limited space which I think has benefits. Obviously, you know, I’m going to argue that that has drawbacks as well and that digital does that thing better. Things they could do better…um…tracking varying opinion, as I said, where people have disagreements about how something should be interpreted, the degree of certainty of the editors of any particular decision. I mean and even in a textual apparatus with levels of notes and things like that and glosses and editorial notes, you know, everything is basically just a note in that kind of system. </p><p>And I know that students have a problem where like I’ve assigned something like The Riverside Chaucer or something like that… where there’s a line number or they are reading a middle English text and they come across a complicated word and they then have to jump down to the bottom of the page to see if there is a gloss for that line, then figure out what they’re line they’re on because they’re only numbered every five lines and believe it or not people don’t count in groups of five very easily to figure out if they’re in between it, then they have to decipher that set of glosses for that line to see if one of them applies to the word that they’re having trouble understanding in that line, you know, that kind of having to jump back and forth and stuff and not knowing which bit of information applies to the thing that you’re looking at, that’s something that editions could do better and I think digital editions have affordances that allow them to do that. It’s the same way we think about text critical apparatus, you know, if we have a whole set of witnesses for a multi-witness text then we’ve come up with this critical edition special formula for displaying all the variations between the witnesses in essentially what is a short text note but that in itself is this lossy kind of representation of us holding in our head competing variations of a particular line, let’s say, or a particular phrase of words at the same time, we’re holding that in our head and then we represent that very poorly on the page and I think if we do represent that in a digital form it should be as close to that conceptual object that we are holding in our head at the same time. Does that make any sense?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Oh yes, completely…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	I mean in some ways yeah; the problem then is what is the edition? Is it the conglomeration of the set of conceptual objects, probably not, is it the representation of those, let’s say, in TEI encoding and things like that or is it the view on it, the re-presentation that we give to other people? I mean, I think we have lots of opportunities to do things better in digital editions but we’ve got sort of stuck in both mimicking things we could do in print or reacting to ‘well we couldn’t do this in print so we’re definitely going to do it in digital’ and also technologies have come along that have allowed us to do certain things that we’ve then sort of latched on to and it’s not necessarily, like we’re not making, sort of, free choices. It’s like when you have a group think, everyone says ‘oh we’re going to do blue-sky thinking about this’ and then somebody mentions one idea and then a lot of the ideas that follow are either variations on that idea or reactions against that idea, they’re not truly blue-skying outside the sort of remit. But that’s just something I notice in meetings. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And so…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	People say ‘let’s brainstorm something that’s new and original’ and then they do something that’s not new and original. Sorry, that’s a tangent.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, considering the centrality of print, both to culture in general but also the practices and professions that dominate this space, do you think that we will ever be able to come unstuck from print, to do something with the digital that isn’t print-on-a-screen?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Ooh good question. I think our main way of looking at editions online and text online is still a form of print. Like, we’re just printing it on the screen, if you want to think about it that way, we’re still, you know, I’m not quite sure what it means to become unstuck from print or dislodge ourselves from print except in the affordances of a paper print based medium versus a digital one. I think we’re still limited, we’re still, you know, we’ve got extra affordances, extra abilities to do things but I think it’s inconceivable that will move to a post-print world but that some of that print affordances might be in digital form. Does that make any sense?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yes…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Like I’m distinguishing between print as a form of medium and our representation of text in printed form. You know, I mean, we could have some very dated but whizz bang 3-D kind of interface, you know, I’m thinking William Gibson, Neuromancer, I jack into the net and I experience things in other ways, you know. I mean, you could say that yeah 3-D virtual worlds or even other things like, let’s say, YouTube or something like that, the preponderance of digital video is a different way to communicate that’s not print. Are we having editions that you would call a scholarly edition in video? I don’t… I was going to say I don’t think so but except whereas those themselves are sometimes editions of things like computer games or something like that. I’m open minded enough to say that yeah, a computer game is a text and we can have scholarly editions of them and one way to represent that scholarly edition would be in a video and so you have a non-print based… yeah… haven’t thought about that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	When you do think of digital editions as they typically tend to exist at present, what kind of tools and platforms come to mind and what are some of the affordance and limitations of these platforms?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Obviously I’m going to start with the TEI aren’t I, you know, a lot of my life has been spent doing things with the TEI, Text Encoding Initiative (as I know you do know) and there are tools that come with that, the TEI produces style sheets and things like that. There’re newer things like TEI Publisher, CETEIcean as a HTML 5 Custom Elements way of displaying editions, those are sort of good on the, you know, a little bit of the creation or the dissemination version. There are always these, sort of, lightweight, roll your own style sheets. I’m part of a Mellon project led by Diane Jakacki and Susan Brown that’s updating the software behind CWRC the Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory (I think, I always get that wrong) and that’s sort of updating the software behind that for creation the publication of editions with embedded linked data as the LEAF-VRE. But really things like the Endings Project and the Endings Project Principles For Digital Longevity have been high in my mind recently in terms of a set of recommendations for how we should be creating digital editions even though we don’t necessarily always want to follow them.</p><p>Let’s see, you said that what can they do and what limits them. In terms of what digital editions can do, I mean, one could say that they can do everything that a printed book can do except perhaps longevity. I mean that’s the major challenge in many ways. Digital versions can have user interaction (you know all this), different views on the text. I tend to like user-centered editions where after an editorial recommendation users can interact with the base text they want or interact with the form of editing that has taken place. Digital editions can aggregate surrogate images from vastly different physical locations we can’t really do that in print. As I sort of said before with people having to look up notes and figure out what line they’re on and things like that, a digital edition can obviously present those glosses/notes in a way that are more immediately available whether that’s in a margin subtext or sur-text or on hover-text, though I guess that has problems. I guess with print editions you found it hard to have, let’s say, facing page facsimile text but that’s now standard in digital editions, so much so that we don’t really think about why we’re doing it when we choose to do it, that kind of thing. I guess I’d say the promises of things like linked data are finally starting to emerge in digital editions especially with named entities and standard URIs to refer to them and thus sort of backwardly aggregate other editions that are mentioning and talking about that named entity of person, place, work, event, object I guess, things like that and that’s the sort of stuff that works well with the TEI the kind of developments we’ve seen in the TEI recently.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, tell me about the TEI. What is the place of the TEI in digital editing? Do you feel that TEI has made a significant impact in the way cultural material is…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Oh definitely, I mean, while it’s not well known enough outside digital humanities and digital libraries and things like that I mean, you know, it is in many ways the de facto standard for text encoding of historical documents for scholarly research purposes, you know. I don’t think anyone would seriously disagree with that even if they want to challenge that place. I mean the central thing about the TEI framework that some basic users sort of ignore is its customisability. The ability and indeed the TEI guidelines recommend that you constrain it to your particular project and use that same machine-readable format to extend it to areas that TEI just doesn’t cover yet. I mean TEI ODD is the one major thing that I think sets the TEI apart from any other form of standard that you’re able to use something in the standard to constrain or extend it past where it originally went. So I guess if the TEI used to be a ragtag group of rebels over the last, sort of, thirty years or so, well more, even now, it’s become the establishment and that means that there are the young Turks, not always so young, who would sort of throw away the establishment the TEI has become and replace it with their choice of shiny new technology. RDF and JSON are often being suggested here and while they’re great especially as generated outputs from the TEI, I would hate to hand encode a text in either of those and I guess whenever some new shiny approach comes along that claims to be lighter and more agile and say we should be looking at what’s lost from the older thing, you know, mass community adoption, rigorous customisation and validation and things like that. And so yeah, I find when we do have that kind of conflict of people saying ‘no let’s do this other thing that’s not the TEI’, or whatever it’s often people who have a very limited sense of what the TEI is, not recognising that its customisable or that they think the TEI is the view of the TEI that they have and there’s other people using the TEI that are doing things that are completely different contexts like let’s say digital libraries and say with very different needs. And that’s why the TEI does these big generalised kind of things and if people go about trying to separate the creation of information from the underlying format so for example editors that hide the tags that you’re using to mark things up which is fine then the format could be anything underneath. So whenever somebody proposes that alongside saying ‘oh we should get rid of the TEI, my question is ‘but if the format could be anything underneath because you’ve created this shiny interface for editing on top of it, why not use the TEI or at least export to it?’ But yeah, the TEI has definitely had a significant impact even just openly released on GitHub there are literally millions of documents in TEI as a format and I think the TEI has always had a sort of strong kind of open access spirit to it like everything the TEI consortium does is open access and openly licenced and so a lot of the things created by the community are licensed the same. If you create a digital edition in the TEI and you look at something like the RIDE guidelines for a checklist of things for reviewing a digital edition, you know, one of the things would be ‘well is the underlying data openly accessible?’ But I think lots of people use it even in context where you wouldn’t necessarily think, like even people who don’t view themselves as digital humanists use the TEI. So manuscript cataloguers for example, you know, if you’re a manuscript cataloguer you don’t view yourself necessarily as a digital humanities person, you’re just happening to use the TEI as your format for manuscript descriptions in the British Library, Bodleian, Cambridge Library, the Vatican, all sorts of places. What else did you ask?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Just to step back a moment, if you were to explain to a complete novice who was just dipping their toes in DH for the first time, what would you say the TEI is and why do they need it? Why use it?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Ooh that’s an interesting question. It depends on how much time I have to explain it to them, I guess. Is this just an elevator pitch?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Say it’s an elevator in a tall building…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Then, I mean, I would be saying TEI is a framework by which people can record, through markup, their understandings and interpretations of one or more texts and make those accessible to users (readers) and that that comes with the ability to provide additional information for example linking names to the information about people or something. But also clarifying and being transparent about your approach as an editor and that this whole framework is customisable and extendable to suit their needs and by customising and extending it through using the same format, the TEI ODD customisation format, that this means projects in the future can look back at their data and understand exactly what version of the TEI they were using, what differences in their particular projects that were from that version of TEI.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And why is that standardisation important? </p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	I mean it’s that hope for the reuse of materials which obviously doesn’t necessarily happen as much as we would like it but also the potential reuse and migration of those materials in the future. That at some point fifty years from now people are going to look back at this wild west of a sort of digital incunabula kind of period and go ‘well all those interfaces used different JavaScript libraries and different things, there was no standardisation’. The one thing that was standardised was their use of the TEI and ‘ok some of them marked thing up like this and some of them marked things up like that’ but (for the good editions at least) they documented that through their customisation and we have their data and we have their customisation so we could compare like to like across all of these editions or we could migrate them across to new formats or whatever we’re going to be using in fifty years. Well, I’m probably not going to be doing anything in fifty years, you know, and you will hopefully be retired.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Hopefully…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	You’re younger than me, I mean,… I will be dead.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think the TEI engages enough with the materiality of texts?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Ooh good question. The guidelines in terms of let’s say editing and transcription of physical primary sources, you know, in the updates that were made to them some years ago made concentrating on the physical, on the material, that much more easy. We’ve now followed that up with a descriptive element so whereas we’ve always had manuscript description, not always but for quite a long time we’ve had manuscript description as a thing that’s just a specific case of a more general class of wanting to describe objects and I happen to be the person who spearheaded the creation of the object element to help provide a structured way to describe objects. So in terms of that sense of materiality, yes, I think it’s gotten quite good. One can do all sorts of things in the TEI that people don’t do. You can be doing millimetre precise locations of segments of text on the page and its only… it tends to be people dealing with modern manuscripts, you know, you get that draft of Joyce or whatever where he’s scratched out this and circled that and you can trace the exact line of the circle or the line from one word to another and there’s always a sort of cost-benefit analysis that one has to do. Is that really worth it? Is it important to say that ‘well there was this written word and they circled it and they drew a line and an arrow up to this phrase up here’ and what we might mean by that, like, move this up here or something and is that enough? Or does it really matter that this line was a little wider or used red ink rather than blue ink and there’s some people and some use cases where that’s really important and then for most of the things that I’m interested in that’s not important at all. Like the intellectual content of this bit of text should be moved up there is important but other than that the fact that it was in red ink or blue ink, I don’t care.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	The specifics of the material elements of a text… is metadata the answer to that? Can metadata be the thing that allows us to embed that in editions?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Yeah, one can say ‘ok this edition is of this manuscript that has these physical attributes’, this particular bit of us let’s say where you have a flap of paper that’s been stapled onto another bit of paper, you know, we can describe the physicality of that, the size of that, you could even describe the type of staple used if one wants and yeah all of that is descriptive metadata. I don’t know, call me a cynic, I tend to think that except in a few instances that’s probably less necessary in terms of the basic editorial tasks of making the text accessible to your readers. Like, does it matter if it’s a steel staple or a copper staple to the person reading the text? It may, it may not, I sort of fall on the slightly sceptical end like where I would draw the border line is before that in terms of what I would describe, personally, as an editor. Do I think people should be able to do that? Yes of course. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think there are limitations to TEI encoding? I know we’ve possibly touched on a few but can…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Maybe, I mean, if we don’t say TEI in general but just sort of digital editions then the limitations are mostly those either inherent to the medium. So, they’re like inherent to the fact that we look at this stuff on screens though of course we have multiple types of screens that we’re looking at these on. One could do this fabulous 3-D edition with all sorts of fancy bells and whistles and that kind of stuff but if the site goes down sort of three to five years after the project, you’ve got to ask yourself what was the point of doing it? Like, you know, there’s got to be some sustainability I think in our commitment to produce editions that don’t have the benefit of benign neglect that a printed edition does. If a librarian or an archivist takes a book and sets it on a shelf or in one of those nice archive boxes then leaves it there for ten years, the truth is it’s probably going to be fine because it’s in a climate controlled kind of area and that kind of stuff, you know, but if you do that with a digital edition it’s probably not going to be fine, you know, something will have gone wrong or something that had one of those fancy bells and whistles means that now it doesn’t work because there’s been some security flaw with that. Yeah, I’ve definitely had editions where the passage of time has then created a problem. So, I mean, if you do make one of these editions with all these fancy bells and whistles there are limitations of accessibility as well. Like those who provide information solely available by things like colour, you know, that’s obviously bad for screen readers or bad for colourblind people or those where, I was talking about glosses earlier and stuff, but if you provide something by a pop up tool tip whereby you hover to get more information, that’s really tempting because that’s the kind of affordance that’s really easy in a digital edition and you can understand why you would want to do that but it’s wrong and it’s wrong because it limits the medium through which it’s accessed. It’s not good for, you know, (if I hold up my mobile phone again) it’s not good for me hovering on my mobile phone. Yes, ok, some interfaces on mobile phones can sense that your finger is near the screen rather than touching the screen and hover in that way but making it so dependent on the physicality of the medium I think is problematic. So there are things like that so that’s why, I think I mentioned before I’ve been sort of thinking about things like the Ending Project Principals for Digital Longevity, you know, and I think it’s hard to convince project partners that ‘no, we shouldn’t have the flashier website’ because they of course view the website as ‘the edition’ we should instead have something slightly less flashy that’s able either to be exported to or in itself is archivable as a sort of flatter version where we can take this and stick it in an archive, you know, in a zip file and bring it out fifty years later and it will just work. Yeah. Is that enough on limitations?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Certainly, very useful…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	I could’ve done more…</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Anything else you’d like to add? Either on limitations or in general?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	I guess, I’m still thinking of limitations, sorry… I don’t want to bore you. I guess the thing I’d add is that, which I guess I was talking about digital editions generally and I didn’t really talk about TEI in terms of limitations and there’s some things when developing them that TEI goes ‘oh look, there’s this mass adopted, popular, international standard that’s out there we’re not going to thread on its toes’ so it’ll do stuff that will sort of slot in with it or it will do the basic case. What’s a good example of this? Things like SVGs, Scalable Vector Graphics, ok, a different XML standard, people use it all the time for all sorts of things, people don’t know its XML that they’re using when they do it but… you know. The TEI gives ways, in thinking back to physicality materiality, ways to describe sort of like polygons like, for example, this section of text might be it’s written in a spiral like this or something but the TEI provides a very basic version of that because it recognises SVG exists and you can embed your SVG inside TEI if you want, yay, the benefit of multi-namespaced documents, everyone hates namespaces but that’s why it’s a good idea. There are other cases where something else exist as an open international standard but the TEI has such a need for it itself that it does duplicate what’s happening out there in its own language but it tries to do so in a way that’s compatible with that standard so you could export to that really easily or something like that. The stand-off element in TEI inherently compatible with other standards like the W3Cs Web Annotation Data Model so that’s an example of doing that where they’ve constrained or limited the way in which it’s expressed in the TEI so that if people use it they’re usually inherently compatible with something out there. I mean I guess that’s sort of ways in which the TEI chooses to limit itself. I’m not sure if that’s helpful or not.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s very helpful!</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	I mean, once you understand that the TEI is extendable, then to say ‘aw it doesn’t have an element for this’ is nonsensical because you can create an element for that, you know, just for your project if you want and if your project likes it then you can propose that to the TEI and then the TEI will go ‘wow that’s great, except that’s a very specific use case, how about we make a more general use case of it’. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is that community element one of the advantages of the TEI?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Definitely yeah, I mean avoiding sort of fragmentation, where everybody is doing something different in a wild west kind of scenario, but also then coming together for support, calming theoretic basis, teaching, training materials things like that. I’ve taught the TEI lots and lots over my life, well, let’s say over the last twenty years and the number of times I’ve either accidently found or heard from somebody who is teaching TEI in some other context like ‘oh I’m teaching the TEI in Mexico’ or ‘I’m teaching the TEI in Japan and I’ve used your slides’ like ‘I’ve taken your slides and I’ve plagiarised them but I’ve written it in Japanese’. Indeed, I remember once I was teaching a TEI workshop in Japan and the great thing about the TEI in terms of multilingualism is that it has its glosses and descriptions for elements available in certain other languages where volunteers from that community have chosen to donate the time to translate them. And so I took the TEI slides that I already had and I ran them through a script I wrote that for every time I mentioned an element went and looked up how that was described in Japanese and replaced the text immediately after the element with the description that was in Japanese. So where it says ‘forename; a proper noun or noun phrase’ or something like that, it then went and looked that up automatically in Japanese and then replaced it in my slides, I regenerated pdfs from it and they absolutely loved it! It looked like I’d put in lots and lots of work to go and copy and paste for every slide the description. Of course, the problem with teaching that is that when you’re teaching it, you’re saying ‘ah this slide is obviously about forename, now what was I going to say about it, I don’t know, it’s in Japanese now (laughs) so that was fun.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And why XML?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Ooh that’s an interesting question. If you ask me, I have an article where I address this, if you ask me ‘is the TEI XML?’ I would say ‘no’ the TEI used to be SGML or expressed its encoding recommendations if you should use SGML and now it currently does so as XML. One can replace that with other things potentially in the future as long as they meet sort of certain thresholds of mass adoption, ease of use, you know, human readability, things like that, I don’t find RDF very human readable. I would hate to encode a medieval manuscript in RDF or JSON or something like that, directly at least and as I said before, once you’re not doing it directly then it doesn’t matter what’s underneath it as long as it’s adhering to some abstract model. And so, the TEI is sometimes an abstract model that can be provided to any markup system. So yeah, I would say the TEI isn’t XML is just happens to currently be expressed in XML. TEI will be around thirty years from now and it might not be expressed in XML.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What is the article where you discuss this?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	That’s my one in Digital Scholarship in the Humanities, Myths and Misconceptions about the TEI or something like that. (It’s not the best written article but you know…)</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s not bad if it’s in the DSH…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p> 	But, yes, I answer a whole bunch of things that people have basically said to me about the TEI over many years, you know, ‘the TEI has no way to do stand-off’, ‘yes it does’, things like that. I can send you a link to it.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yes, I have it here… You have the list of misconceptions, that’s really useful, it’s structured very nicely.</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	There is another article, in the International Journal of Digital Humanities, ‘Opening the Book: data models and distractions in digital scholarly editing’ and that’s one where I argue that there’s certain type of editors who shouldn’t have to learn things like TEI. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Can you explain?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	That they shouldn’t be distracted by coming up with proper data models and understanding all of that. Yes, there are editors that are in between that. Yeah…</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So you’re suggesting that there’s some kind of front facing interface that they use…</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	If there is I think that’s fine, like that can be the future of digital editing if we all sort of get on the same page. Like the things that we want are easy ways to edit single or multiple witness texts, to have annotations on those in one form or another and provide more information about particular types of object in that text whether that be named entities or linguistic objects, conceptual objects, or whatever, I’m trying to be very vague and generalistic here.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	If they don’t learn TEI, how do they create editions?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	So, if you look at the latest release of TEI Publisher, at some point, they’ve now got something where ‘oh, I can highlight this bit of text’ and ‘I am creating an annotation that says this is a person’s name’ and ‘oh here is more information about that person’ or link it to one that’s already existing, that’s one example of enriching a text. One can also do this with LEAF-Writer (from our LEAF-VRE project). Do I think a… here’s the interesting question about what is or isn’t an edition, where I’ve mentioned handwritten text recognition before, if you, and I think Transkribus in READ Co-op are doing this through some of their editions where you run a text through HTR, you get this transcription back, ok, so you have a transcript of the text and you go though, and let’s say you go through and add more information about the people and places in it? Is that an edition? And I… I sound like an old fuddy duddy or something but I think that it goes back to that idea of ‘has due consideration been applied to every phrase of text that’s there?’, you know, and unless in addition to adding those people and places and that kind of enhanced metadata they’ve also gone and corrected where it’s wrong and that kind of thing, then I don’t think it’s an edition. There has to be that editorial human input.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And do you think that feature where you can highlight it, do you think TEI needs that? Do you not think TEI is relatively easy to learn?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	That’s one of those things where for somebody like me, yeah, it’s fairly easy to learn. I think for… my example is usually Jennifer Richards here, I don’t know if you know her, she does lots of stuff on Renaissance text and voice and things like that, rhetorical stuff, is the PI for what they call the Thomas Nashe project, a Renaissance playwright and satirical writer…satirist (I guess is the word I was looking for). But anyways, she has the vision to understand that doing things digitally is important and good. She has sat in on my TEI teaching. She will probably never sit down and use TEI to initially edit her editions, you know. Like, she is too busy, she is the director of our digital humanities institute and things like that, you know, she’s too far progressed in her career, though age isn’t really an excuse, you know, like there’s almost nothing I can say that would convince her to do that, even though she recognises it as good and important. And so there are people in that kind of slice of life but if an early career Researcher came to me and said ‘should I be learning TEI to do this’ then I would be saying ‘yeah’ not only because yes you learn TEI but by learning TEI you also learn all sorts of other things, you learn about hierarchical text, you learn certain theories of text, certain approaches to the interpretation of text, you get to look at other editions and see what they’ve done or look even just at the whole list of elements in the TEI and go ‘oh I never thought about encoding that’. So, that goes back to that sort of community thing again of seeing other people’s work or other people’s concerns. It’s one thing the TEI… it’s not very good at actually is its own history. It has this history that’s affected things so like one of the earlier editors of the TEI Michael Sperberg-McQueen who’s a great text theorist; I don’t know if you’ve read anything by Michael. But yeah Michael Sperberg-McQueen, excellent, you know, he was one of the first editors of the TEI he went on to become one of the co-editors of the XML standard so there were things in XML thus in every word document you use now and things like that because DOCX is XML, you know, that are there because of his experience in editing the TEI guidelines. I think things like Xpointer that TEI had an element called XPTR which then it got rid of to adopt the W3CX pointer which Michael had a hand in creating based on his experience in the TEI you know so there are these sorts of circular things, you know. But yeah, no we’re not good at explaining our own history, I guess. I forget what you asked now that made me go off on that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	If TEI is easy to use, basically, why do people need a front end for it?</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	It maximises the potential use of it, yes, I think it’s better to encode things with tags and see that you’re doing. But it’s exactly like people typing in a word document, you know, you type in a word document, you make something bold, you make something italic and as a student today you don’t think about it, you think that text is bold, that text is italic and you don’t think that there’s something underneath that creating the representation of bold and the representation of italic. I mean the thing I do for students in class is to take a word document that we’ve jointly written some stuff in, save it as a .ZIP file and unzip it with all the contents in the word file and it blows their mind also because students aren’t thinking about files anymore like files, folders, directories is almost a foreign concept to them because they’ve lived in a cloud based, app based world.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Great point...</p></sp><sp who="#JC"><speaker>JC</speaker><p>	Yeah I think that’s increasingly going to be a problem… the watershed moment for students is going to be realising the thing they’ve created in the program, whatever the program is, like Word or oxygen or whatever is a separate thing from the program like they go into Office 365 and open up their file they don’t view the file as something different it’s just an option in the programme and like obviously there are computer geeky people who will never have that problem, you know, but I’m talking about your average undergraduate and I think that’s probably becoming more of a problem… (he said, caging his words with lots of uncertain language). I definitely think it’s becoming more of a problem. I don’t know how much it will become a problem, like in ten years are we going to be going ‘oh my God these students don’t understand anything because they’ve only ever used a tablet and a mobile phone’, that’s their version of computing. And if that’s the case, what will scholarly editions look like to them (ha ha, he said, bringing it round).</p></sp></body></text></TEI>