<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Mary Chapman &amp; Joey Takeda</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  Michael Kurzmeier	 on Date: March 7th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_MK_MC_JT.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bios</head><p><list><item>MARY CHAPMAN is Professor of English at the University of British Columbia and Director of The Winnifred Eaton Archive. She is also author of Making Noise, Making News: Suffrage Print Culture and US Modernism (2014); editor of Becoming Sui Sin Far: The Uncollected Fiction, Journalism and Travel Writing of Edith Eaton (2016); and co-editor (with Angela Mills) of Treacherous Texts: US Suffrage Literature 1846-1946 (2011).</item><item>JOEY TAKEDA is a Developer in the Digital Humanities Innovation Lab at Simon Fraser University and is the Technical Director of the Winnifred Eaton Archive. </item></list></p></div></front><body><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	What do the terms “scholarly edition” and “scholarly editing” mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	I have a background in scholarly editing but I’m newer to DH so, for me, “scholarly editing” is an activity that requires a degree of precision about source texts and publication history and things like that. Being very deliberate about those decisions can make explicit to students and future scholars what kind of cultural work a particular edition has done. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	I think to me, at least, “scholarly editing” is really about making visible explicit decisions. My understanding of scholarly editing comes out of working in TEI so my understanding goes beyond just printed text or really standard textual material. I think of scholarly editing and a scholarly edition as working with a broad variety of cultural artifacts and making explicit editorial decisions to enable transparent interactions with a text, however broadly defined.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. To follow up on this, is there something that you think digital editions do especially well in that context?</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	Digital editions liberate you from so many constraints: They liberate you from time and space and some financial constraints, although they create others. But the fact that one can update them and relaunch and add to them as one’s project evolves…That’s very exciting. The fact that it can be a little bit more collaborative in the process, getting people to react to your first effort and complement what you’ve done with things they can add… I also find that really exciting. Spatially and visually, there are so many rabbit holes that a digital edition can take you down in terms of the illustrations and the printers, that is, the many hands that have had roles in the work, how you can provide information about those and, depending on the tools you’re using, create interesting comparisons… I just think the possibilities are endless. That’s what I love about preparing a digital edition, even if it means our work is never done. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	What I find so incredible about digital editions is that they defamiliarize the text in a very interesting way—you have to stop and think about what this thing is… of course, it’s difficult because a digital edition can mean so many different things; at what point is the edition not digital if every print edition these days begins its life as a word doc? But what I find so compelling about encoding a digital edition—say in TEI or using other formal structures—is that it requires really engaging with the text. This is a really, really close engagement that gives multiple occasions to pause and think: “What is this? Is it a quotation or is it something more? What could we call this little block of text?” So I think doing a digital edition offers many powerful moments of really engaging and thinking about either the author’s intentions or the printer’s intentions or your own editorial intentions, the interventions that you would like to make in the text as well.</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	May I add something? Joey made me think of a few more things. We’ve discovered multiple versions of several of the texts that we’ve edited for the Winnifred Eaton Archive, and doing a digital edition has given us the freedom to work with all of them. We’re starting to do more of that, right now, because we are working on some of Eaton’s later texts, for which we also have manuscripts, but a digital edition offers an opportunity that a bound volume would only gesture to in a clunky way in terms of variants. But also, Eaton often remediates some of her works; she may write a short story based on journalism and then transform that into an outline for a screenplay and then write a script that might result in a film. So a digital edition allows us to provide links to as many of the multimedia forms as we’re able to acquire or digitise and that multi-mediation expands the audience for the actual work that we’re doing because the multiple texts could appeal to film scholars in addition to the literary scholars we presume are our primary audience.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	You’re obviously both involved in the Winnifred Eaton Archive and I was wondering if you could tell me more about the project.</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	Winnifred Eaton Babcock Reeve (1875-1954) was the first Asian North American novelist. In her lifetime–childhood in Montreal, a short journalistic stint in Jamaica, over two decades spent in New York, Chicago, Cincinnati, and Hollywood, and then almost 4 decades in Alberta–she published 16 novels, hundreds of short stories, articles, poems, and interviews, and wrote or contributed to scores of screenplays. She is an important author in multiple genres, who worked in both Canada and the US, but because of her ~15-year masquerade as “Onoto Watanna”, Japanese noblewoman, she has fallen out of critical favour so many people are unfamiliar with her monumental contributions to various forms of popular culture. In 2003, Loyola University Maryland professor Jean Lee Cole built the Winnifred Eaton Digital Archive, an edition of two serialized novels and a few dozen periodical publications by Winnifred Eaton. The Digital Archive was housed at the UVA eText Center. But in 2010, UVA stopped supporting the digital edition so, while individual texts are still available on the UVA Library website, the edition has been dismantled and the apparatus that Jean created has been lost. So it was always in the back of Jean’s mind to relaunch that edition. Its dismantling was discussed by Amy E. Earhart in Traces of Old, Uses of the New: The Emergence of Digital Literary Studies and by other DH scholars who are worried about the sustainability of digital literary recovery projects. I was working on Winnifred Eaton’s sister Edith Eaton, otherwise known as Sui Sin Far, and was stumbling upon unknown texts by Winnifred and I thought: Wouldn’t it be great to bring all these Winnifred materials together? Winnifred is known as the “bad Eaton sister” because, for some unknown reason, she masqueraded as Japanese even though she was born in Montreal to a British father and a Chinese mother. So I was convinced that providing a fuller representation of her oeuvre beyond her Japanese phase—her work as a screenwriter in Hollywood, her work as a journalist and author in New York, her work in Alberta as a kind of Canadian literary nationalist and rancher-–would be very interesting to scholars who were only familiar with her Japanese phase. So, I reached out to Jean and she was keen to repurpose her XML files, although they were in an older TEI version. So we started working together and Joey was instrumental in determining the shape of the larger project.</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	I had worked for a number of digital humanities projects before, when I did my undergrad at the University of Victoria so I had experience in digital editions and training in TEI from Martin Holmes at UVic’s HCMC. In 2019, I had moved to Vancouver and was working on my MA in English at the University of British Columbia and I saw that Mary had posted an ad for a research assistant for her project and I thought: This looks like something I’d be really interested in since my other research interest, in addition to the digital humanities, was Asian Canadian literature and I’d never heard of Winnifred Eaton and her strange career. When I met up with Mary, she told me she was thinking about making this an Omeka archive. I was still working with the Endings Project at UVic at the time, so I pushed back quite adamantly, insisting that the kinds of questions we wanted to ask about these texts and the kinds of relationships that needed to be shown across these texts would really be better represented through a more robust TEI archive, especially because there were, I think, maybe forty texts…I can’t remember exactly the number…already.</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	Jean’s archive started with about thirty and we knew there would be over two hundred texts in the end.</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	So we already had all of these P4 TEI files and Mary had already worked on a number of transcriptions on Google Docs, Word Docs etc, so all that sort of stuff already existed. My feeling was that it was going to be challenging to represent these texts as an Omeka archive at that point, especially given hosting requirements. So we decided to go full steam ahead with TEI, which is always a fun thing to do, especially with someone like Mary, who is so invested in textual editing questions already and has taken to it pretty quickly. It’s been very fun.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. Just to drill down on that a little bit: When you think back to the origins of this project, are there any key design decisions that come to mind? You already mentioned TEI but I’ve also seen there’s a big emphasis on open access on the project so was that a consideration from the start?</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	Open access was always going to be key; there was no debate about that. I think when I look back as a manager of a team that was doing something that I didn’t immediately understand fully, I realize how invaluable it has been to have someone who can take the lead on the technical direction and has both the software tool skills and a sense of the traditions and conventions within digital humanity scholarship. Joey was key in that regard. The Winnifred Eaton Archive recently went through a peer review process with the Recovery Hub for American Women Writers, a project led by Jessica Despain, and the key decisions that reviewers praised were all Joey’s decisions about how to ensure open access, crediting of collaborators, sustainability, etc.. Having Joey on the team early on was key.</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	And I would say that many of the infrastructural decisions as well as the technical ones were born out of my own desire to do this freely....not on a shoestring, necessarily, but I’m not a server administrator and there wasn’t any formal infrastructural or technical support available at UBC. It had to be open access because we were using open access tools, and everything that I wanted to do, I needed to be able to do freely and just experiment. While I think we always had wanted the archive to be open access and available in public, that sort of sealed the deal. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you both. Just to round this up, is there anything you would do differently if you were to start this project again?</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	I think because we were learning as we went, we definitely had some workflow issues.  We started by storing texts on Google Drive, then we moved to GitHub, and we initially used a Google Docs spreadsheet to task-manage but our project manager Sydney Lines pushed for different kinds of project management tools that we could use to make the collaboration more efficient. Definitely using a proprietary project management software and GitHub has been great. Those two shifts I think enabled better team work, better workflow. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	I really want to highlight how instrumental Sydney Lines has been to the project management side of things. She’s an excellent project manager and a really, really organised and smart member of the team. She’s been able to smooth out workflow complications and translate between the kinds of things that the project was thinking about and the kinds of technical rabbit holes one can go down when working with exciting manuscripts. She is able to rein it in and make really good calls for what the right approach is for going forward.</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	Yes. What it underlines for me, Joey, is in many ways just how random it all is, how by chance you and Sydney happened to be in the English graduate programme at the same time with these complementary skills and you had both come from, in Sydney’s case a master programme, in your case an undergrad programme, at places that had fostered some DH projects already. So both of you came to the University of British Columbia with skills that other students in my department didn’t necessarily have. I had hired some students ahead of Joey and Sydney and they’d helped with transcriptions and things like that and they were also very helpful for the team, but they couldn’t provide the complementary leadership skills and knowledge that Joey and Sydney brought to push the project forward.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	What is your experience communicating the value of a project such as the Winnifred Eaton Archive? How do you go about it and what experience have you had?</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	We have had so many opportunities. Because the Winnifred Eaton Archive is a static site, we have made occasional announcements on social media each time we have launched a new version. We had our first online launch, featuring a number of contributors and team members, in September 2020. Sydney and I made a short video about the project for the 2020 C19 conference, presented at a Digital Humanities Innovation Lab Pecha Kucha event, and shared some stuff at MLA. Many people have asked us for online interviews or university media interviews, many of the contributors have shared their own teamwork at conferences, Jean and I did an online presentation to the Association for Asian American Studies DH Group. Right now, the team is planning a July 2023 conference in Calgary, Alberta, on the centenary of the publication of Winnifred’s novel Cattle, which is set in Alberta, and the centenary of the passage of Canada’s Immigration Act, which excluded Chinese from immigrating to Canada. The conference will bring together the team as well as many of the people who have volunteered and contributed transcriptions and headnotes and done scholarship on the Eatons. I should add that the organisers of Historic Calgary Week and the Calgary Chinese Culture Centre are cosponsoring our conference, which means it’s also open to the public, so we’re hoping to raise Eaton’s profile in Calgary where she lived for almost 40 years.   </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	In terms of communicating the project at a scholarly level, we also presented virtually at the TEI Conference in 2019. Winnifred is so multifaceted and her work speaks to multiple audiences, which makes talking about the intellectual content of this project quite simple. On the technical side of things: because of my involvement with Endings at UVic, we were able to work with the programmers at HCMC who provided infrastructural help. In terms of communicating these kinds of projects as a whole: I use the Winnifred Eaton Archive quite often as an example of the kinds of things you can do with your pile of texts — You want to do something with them? Here’s an example of how you can organise them, display them, and make something usable.</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	And I would just add that the other hat I wear is that of Academic Director of UBC’s Public Humanities Hub. One of its missions is to help scholars figure out how to share their work more broadly so that research doesn’t just live on a dark, abandoned shelf at the library but actually reaches people, whether it’s in the classroom or shared with media at public events etc. So I’m always on the lookout for audiences who need a way into this material and, as Joey says, because Winnifred is so multifaceted, she’s actually very easy to share.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Joey, you were talking about examples there and I think that’s a bridge to the next section. How much success have you had teaching scholarly editing and how does that relate to the project and what lessons have you learnt?</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	I taught an undergrad course that used the Archive. In that course, with help from Joey and Sydney, I taught students to use digital tools to make StoryMaps and timelines relevant to the two Eaton sisters, and then each student transcribed and encoded a short work using TEI. There were 11 students in the class and each of them chose one text and by the end of the two hours several students were almost finished. So they learned how to use Oxygen text editor and TEI and they uploaded it in the form that we needed so that Joey could add it to the repository. In the process, they gained a new appreciation for what goes into creating an edition, i.e. that there are decisions to be made. It’s not just a transparent photocopying activity. In the grad course that I will teach this term, I’m hoping students can produce annotated digital editions of several of Winnifred’s screenplays which very few scholars have worked on so far. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	At Simon Fraser University, I do introductions to TEI or workshops on digital scholarly editing and, again, I tend to use the Winnifred Eaton Archive as a really good example, since, in terms of the actual scholarly apparatus and the encoding, it is really quite simple. One of the approaches that we took from the beginning was that we’re not going to represent all of the bibliographic codes to make the encoding more efficient and more straight-forward. And this is one of the reasons why I have really enjoyed working on the Winnifred Eaton project too: Mary has been very decisive and attentive to the kinds of questions the project ought to ask and does not go down large experimental encoding rabbit holes, which are so easy to go down, especially when teaching with the Archive. It’s been quite a good example of how to do a project in general just because, in a year and a half, the project went from nothing to having a hundred texts encoded; it also has a lot of good examples of good but fairly bare-bones and simple encoding. As part of that undergrad course Mary mentioned, I gave a guest lecture. I would say the students started to engage in the kinds of questions that digital scholarly editing requires, asking “Is this a line or is this just a random break?”; “Why is this a heading versus a title?” etc. So I think there are really many good opportunities to teach with that Archive and I think it has been easy to teach with.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	To wrap this up a little bit, so when you’re reflecting on the wider field of digital scholarly editing and publishing, is there something that you feel we’re missing in the field? Is there something you think the field needs to develop regarding issues like sustainability, or accessibility, just to name a few examples?</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	The peer reviewers who looked at our site encouraged us to keep expanding the capacities of the site. One of their suggestions, which has been in the back of our minds as well as a priority but we just hadn’t gotten around to it, was to build in more pedagogical supports: What are the kinds of assignments you can do with this Archive? How easy is it, given that Joey has written documentation and made lots of the code downloadable? What else could be done? So that’s something we’re going to build out in the coming years. Textual editing for print is no longer really taught at university. If somebody is invited to do a print scholarly edition, they have to learn everything from scratch, but one benefit of DH courses is that they’re reintroducing students and grad students to editing and, if that’s been missing in the past, that lack seems to be beginning to be filled. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	For me, I think sustainability is a big issue for digital editions and this is, again, why the Winnifred Eaton Archive came to be the way it is—because of the lack of sustainability in the early 2000’s alongside standard technological churn and digital degradation. So that’s something I’ve been keenly aware of, especially because I’ve been working with this project and trying to create static editions and more formal structures for preserving these sorts of digital editions. But part of the trickiness I think with a lot of the sustainable technologies is that you have to balance the new and exciting and the innovative with sustainable technology. It’s through my work with The Endings Project that we’ve shown that there are many things that can be done, and projects can be duplicated in sustainable ways, but it’s not necessarily easy and you have to really consider it from the start. There needs to be quite a bit of support from the institution whether that is through the training of graduate students or the creation of a Digital Humanities Lab; that’s why I think Simon Fraser University is very lucky to have its own Digital Humanities Lab with dedicated staff who know about the digital humanities and understand the specific and sort of esoteric set of concerns of the digital humanities. So I think it’s mainly an issue of support and making sure there are good supports institutionally for digital humanities projects, whether that’s in granting institutions or within university administration in general, and really being able to make it clear that this is scholarly work, it’s work that goes on a tenure dossier, it’s work that really counts. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. One final question here from my side: So, ideally, what does a future digital edition and future publishing platform look like to you? If you could make a wish, what would the ideal edition be?</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	I think each writer or text requires its own kind of edition. Winnifred Eaton needs a platform versatile enough to showcase the multiple genres she worked in and the various stages of her career. I’m not sure there’s one ideal. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	I think the ideal edition or platform is something that is able to be supported and made individually, whether that’s at the level of the subject or the person who’s creating the archive. I definitely agree that one size fits all models are complicated and they are, by definition, subject to future creep and scope creep .... the TEI is a really good example of this because it formally tries to define text but every day we learn new things about texts from different traditions, from different languages, from different cultures that radically alter a western conception of text. It’s nice that the TEI is so flexible but it is also hard to even think about one formal standard of encoding text in general. So I think, in terms of a digital edition platform, an ideal one would have to be one that is so flexible, so fluid that it could allow for all sorts of experimentation and attention to the particularities of a particular author while also being sustainable and archivable, which are again quite often at odds.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you both so much for being here and taking time. Is there anything else you would like to add? Maybe there is something that you feel we didn’t talk about that comes up from your work in digital scholarly editing?</p></sp><sp who="#MC"><speaker>MC</speaker><p>	Joey mentioned earlier that we got a lot of support from the University of Victoria because the infrastructure isn’t yet in place at the University of British Columbia. We also got to be an early project supported by the Recovery Hub for American Women Writers, and that NEH-funded initiative at Southern Illinois University was created to help people at institutions lacking DH infrastructure. Initiatives like that have been really invaluable to our project. Not everyone is going to be working at a university with rich infrastructure for DH projects, so collaborative ventures that can allow people across a number of institutions to get support from others actually gives newbie DH scholars the fluency to advocate at their own institutions for greater support and to make explicit to administrators the scholarly value of what they’re doing for tenure etc.</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	Yeah, infrastructure is very important. I think also understanding infrastructure as not just meaning the individual institution, but rather more about sharing expertise, knowledge and a mutual understanding of what the concerns are in humanities and what is necessary in order to be able to provide the best support possible without being locked in to a particular technical infrastructure.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>
