<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Gimena del Rio Riande</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on April 10th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_GR.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>GIMENA DEL RIO RIANDE is Associate Researcher at the Instituto de Investigaciones Bibliográficas y Crítica Textual at CONICET, the main government agency that fosters the development of science and technology in Argentina. She holds a MA and Summa Cum Laude PhD in Romance Philology (Universidad Complutense de Madrid). Her main academic interests deal with Digital Humanities, Digital Scholarly Editions, and Open Research Practices in the Humanities. Among her many academic activities, she is the director of the Laboratorio de Humanidades Digitales (HD LABB) at CONICET and the first Postgraduate training in Digital Humanities in Argentina (UCES). She also serves as Chief editor of the journal Revista de Humanidades Digitales. She coordinates the Asociación Argentina de Humanidades Digitales and takes part of the board of directors at the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) Consortium. Since 2020, she is one of the DOAJ (Directory of Open Access Journals) Ambassadors for Latin America. Since 2011 she has been involved in many different digitization, digital humanities, open science and digital scholarly editing projects in America, Europe and Latin America.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly editing and scholarly edition mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	Ok so scholarly edition means like what I’ve been studying a long time and on the one side I think it’s, for me, it has always helped me to understand my subject of study so much better. I’m from Argentina and here people who study art or let’s say a course related to literature it’s called ‘Letras’ so in Spanish it’s really general and it’s more related to literary theory than philology. I have always been interested in medieval text, Middle Ages, Hispanic Middle Ages etc so my approach has always been really philological so that part was missing here in my studies that’s why I went abroad, I moved to Spain, well, I did my PhD in Spain and I really focused on scholarly editing during those times and, for me, as I was saying, it’s understanding better the context of any text not only literary but any text. Also, what is really interesting in this sense is that this way of understanding text, the material side of text has also helped me as a researcher to work in texts but any kind of edition. I mean, this kind of scholarly editing work also led me also to think of, let’s say, edition in general so I really in this last ten years let’s say or something like that I got a lot involved in for instance, journal editing and anything related to how we edit text, understand text in different media, well, yeah, I would say this more philological approach also helped me understanding any other kind of work with text in general.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do digital editions do well, and what might be done better?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	Well, that question is really… I need to put it in my context. So, one of the, let’s say, the issues with working with digital editions in general in South America… I… the context I know better is Argentina, is infrastructures, the lack of infrastructures. So, any time that we are working with scholarly editions or even journal editions that is why I also got involved a lot with journal editing because these people were really thinking of infrastructures for journals so I really got interested in how they were thinking, how to edit and how to access and preserve this kind of text and how maybe it could help me understand scholarly editing here. So, when I started working here in Argentina in 2013 one of the problems with starting a digital edition was mostly infrastructure. It wasn’t about, you know, knowing the TEI or taking courses, it was difficult but somehow that could be done, the problem was ‘ok, where are you going to put your digital edition and how people are going to access it and who is going to take care of it?’ because this is all about preservation and not only about preservation of the data I would say because this has happened to me before, it’s not just having a repository for your files or anything but it’s also all the work that it takes to make a digital edition that, you know, when it’s lost it’s a big problem because you are losing a lot of work so that was one of the biggest challenges here. I tried many things, first I tried putting my editions abroad in a laboratory in Spain then in another project in Germany but I really had problems when the people in charge, let’s say, on one case of the library, on the other case of the lab changed because I had problems in both cases with my editions and the materials, most of what was there on the site got lost. Here in Argentina, the problem was I couldn’t access the server of CONICET, that is the National Council of Research, that is where I work. We don’t have anything similar to the National Endowment for the Humanities or you know, this kind of grants specific for DH. So, it’s very difficult every time I ask for a grant ‘I need this, this and that for a digital edition’ because that is not… I cannot even put it in the form for the typical grants that you could ask for here in Argentina. So, my… the solution that I found and it is something that I… it has its pros and cons the good things and advantages and disadvantages, is minimal editions, that is what I have been doing in the last five years, minimal computing and it’s working with specific static sites in which I am sure that I have control over not only the data but over the site that I have created. Of course, that has a lot of disadvantages because the problem is the scale, you’re always working on a very small scale and any chance of working on a bigger scale it’s just putting a brick over another brick it’s not… we are no somehow not building being sure you have the big infrastructure for the future it’s just in the moment you are adding something to that minimal infrastructure. But it’s not minimal it’s really complex but it’s minimal in the sense of technology. So that’s why I was saying that this answer is specific and it’s really you know it’s this very much situated answer.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Infrastructure comes up a lot, and usually in the context of problems for the field. Do you think that there are feasible, broadly applicable models through which the infrastructure problem can been resolved? Or even, philosophies of infrastructure, like, say, minimal computing?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	One of the problems with minimal computing is that honestly for working on a good digital edition in the sense that I try not just forking a repository or doing something over it is that sometimes there is a moment in which you need an expert, it’s not just the humanist all by herself or himself working. I have got lost many times in this kind of infrastructure that you download in your computer and you need to understand exactly what… why it is failing and you go to stackoverflow or anywhere and you don’t find that answer and every computer is a world so sometimes your system or sometimes it’s there some kind of things that might be there being the real problem for you working with minimal computing but on the opposite when you have the structure then it works really well I think and somehow this has happened with my students too. At the beginning… and maybe I’m leaving your question but I think it makes sense, at the beginning when I started here, I am a researcher but I also teach, do some kind of teaching at universities because here you have to do both things in Argentina to work as a researcher, you need to research and teach at the same time so I taught TEI basically and now I coordinate a master’s degree here in Argentina in digital humanities. I’m not teaching TEI but one of the professors who works with me teaches TEI but we both work on the syllabus. But one of the things that happened to us before was that when you teach simple courses on TEI or digital edition and this is not the part of a big project or a big master’s degree or you know the goals of a whole department you only teach encoding that can be something not really much inspire for most of the students. For many students it was an activity which they couldn’t, you know, it was cool learning for a course in which you learn something else but they didn’t find the challenge there about just encoding a text and then maybe not continue working on transformations or HTML or CSS and for teaching that you need a long course you are not going to learn that on a let’s say one month course or something like that so that is also a big challenge when you don’t have a specific let’s say DH context in which to put digital scholarly editions because this is not learning a tool say for visualisation maybe you can take a course and then do something with the data this is a lot of work and it takes a lot of time so in that sense teaching minimal editions was really satisfying for our students. We started two years ago a grant with the University of Maryland with a programme that is called Global Classrooms and we taught minimal editions to students in Maryland and here in the University of Salvador in Argentina and even though many times we needed to help a lot of students you know, downloading things, understanding what was there, working with a command line and even you’re not sure if they have understood everything it was… their answer was they felt all of this more satisfying than just encoding for a project, getting a certificate because you have participated on a project. The problem here in Argentina is that you cannot pay students for their work, that is forbidden, you can invite the students to take part in a project to learn to participate in meetings, to publish, to go to conferences, you know, to offer them small funding for all of that but it’s really different to how many other people work in the world in these funded projects in which you can hire students for their work, for doing this specific tasks. So, what I also feel is that really the specific, you know, the academic context really makes scholarly this field really different from place to place. And another thing that is also… I am leaving your question but what I have felt in this last year is that many people in South America are trying to copy this model from abroad, you know, about hiring students and it doesn’t work because we don’t have a tradition for doing that so it’s just you know when you are trying to put into practice things that are not part of what students are also used to at their universities who are also researchers so well, I don’t know if I have answered your question.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Very interesting, thank you. Across all of this work, what the tools and platforms are you using?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	Ok, so firstly we started using GitHub and Jekyll for the static sites, for encoding and for doing some, well, all the process of the editions we work with Visual Studio Code the S-Code so what we try to do and what… well, I haven’t mentioned this but here in Argentina and in many countries in Latin America there is more interest in different researchers about Open Access and Open Science as, you know, maybe as part of your work but also maybe related to advocacy or making better science or democratising knowledge. Our universities most of them are public universities so all the research is publicly funded. We don’t outsource any kind of services related to journal publishing or anything to big publishers or anything so everything is done inside the university with public funds. And by the time I was starting my laboratory my DH lab here in Argentina my project related to Digital Humanities, a law, a national law on Open Access was signed in which all the data and results of any research must be, you know, open so my idea related to DH was how to put Digital Humanities in the context of open science so the idea is to revise the tools that we have been using for digital scholarly editions and finding that open tools sometimes it’s not like Libre tools because you don’t find Libre software for everything or hardware for everything but to, you know, for instance I learned TEI in Europe in many courses and what we used was Oxygen and the day that you lost your access to Oxygen you were lost because you didn’t know what to use instead of Oxygen. Well, it was after doing research that I found there were other options in which you didn’t have to pay for the software. In some cases, they weren’t very useful because for TEI you need a lot of information to know exactly the codes that you need to use and Oxygen is really helpful with that. I have read here and there people who will say ‘ok you are going to use Oxygen’ there was a big debate in Twitter one day and they say ‘why do you complain, use other software’ and I said ‘ok yes I can use it’ but imagine a Spanish speaking student or researcher who goes to the TEI that everything is in English and has to go to the guidelines (laughs) all the time to find out what the hell is that code that needs to put… it’s really, you know, it’s not something that you would like to do, it’s not helping anyone. In the last years (?) developed a plug in for a visual studio code in which you can see all the different definitions of the codes for the TEI and that was really helpful. You know maybe of course with Oxygen you can do so many things at any level working with transformations, with XQuery with HTML but not everyone can afford eve buying the student licence that is something that Europe don’t understand. In my country the currency has depreciated to buy a dollar I need 250pesos today that is a lot of money. So, you know, I understand that it is cheap for a university, Europe is cheap for researcher in maybe a Northern country but it’s not cheap in many cases for people working in other latitudes so that also should be taken into account if you want to build a more global digital scholarly field. So, I have been trying that, not only that, it’s also related to infrastructure how you build. How I could build a field here in Argentina from nothing was like making it the most open I could, so I paid a lot of attention to the tools and, you know, even I could buy them I would prefer to work with these tools because I would make sure that anyone who is working with these tools is working on the project maybe reproducing these kinds of projects could do it without having to spend money on software. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that the international field is developing and progressing without an appreciation of the national and local contexts the type of which you are describing?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	Yes, well to give you an example, I have been on the TEI Board for now, I think about four years or something like that because I’m really interested, you know, I think that standards, markup and languages are really useful and the problem is not the language of the meta language you are using, the problem is understanding what is there in different languages. So, I got involved with a specific group in the TEI related to the internationalisation of the TEI. The TEI decided to ask for a Mellon grant. I was involved in the writing the grant and this, this and that but partners from abroad of the States cannot have any funding or money or anything for developing anything in the project so yeah, a lot of things are being done internationally but this is not international collaboration, you know, this is… I am invited as a guest to participate in a project but this is not collaboration. Collaboration is when, you know, equally we are participating in a project so I know that I can do this in my country and I can maybe pay for something or for people to work or for a specific project but it’s not… ok, the Mellon talking about the Spanish TEI, inviting people from South America but this is our grant not the grant from the north and the south. So, a lot of things are being done internationally but we need to revise a lot how because you know honestly that’s not collaboration, it’s grants for doing let’s say something… not even globally, on international terms, you know, and that’s replicates old models of research that I really hate.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	On the subject of language, I know that you’ve written on teaching and learning with the TEI in Spanish; could you share some of your thoughts on that, on the current state of digital editions in terms of multilingualism?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	Well, I think that that is something that in many cases it has been, I wouldn’t say neglected but people haven’t paid a lot of attention to the language thing. I remember, you know, I studied, I did my PhD in Spain and I worked as a researcher in Spain for a long time so, let’s say, people could speak Spanish but in Europe. But I remember taking this TEI courses in Italy, in Switzerland, not even in the United Kingdom, let’s say, in the other side of Europe and for instance in Italy I remember asking the Trainer why we were using text in English and not maybe in Italian, that would make so much sense if we were in Pisa taking a course but no one was paying attention to… I really believe that… it’s like when you went to school what were the books that you were using to learn the subjects, were they written in other languages? No, it was written in your language and your specific examples related to your specific cases. Of course, you can move to compare we are researchers, we can compare examples from Italian literature or English literature or whatever but if you want to teach someone, I believe a lot in what I was saying in situatedness in situated learning, in specific examples that can help you understand better theory, you know, we need not only teaching but all these things related to transculturation to making things also more useful to people I think that related to multilingualism is really important. Obviously, if I hadn’t learned English in some moment of my life I wouldn’t be talking to you and, you know, I think its useful but its’ not enough and as humanists I think that we should all be making a bigger effort to not only to reach to a wider audience or to make research more global but honestly if you want to teach something to your community you should be making an effort to teach in the terms of your community and not just taking examples of Women Writers Project and bringing it to here because no one is going to understand what the texts are about and in many cases how these people selected these examples, so I think that is really important and is something that needs to be done if you want to, you know, at least to do something that it doesn’t feel like ‘ok this is what some people do in Europe, let’s do it here in Argentina’, you know, you need to find out more also things that are useful to your community. Going back to journals, just to give you a small example, in Latin America the markup language that we use for marking up journals is not only HTML but it is a markup language that is called JATS XML and there was a moment in the history of journal editing in which were just about to choose the TEI for journal editing but no the TEI found that it wasn’t… they preferred to stay with more literary texts so the Board in those moments and the Council didn’t get too much involved in journal editing because in other countries that wasn’t used, so you just published in a PDF and HTML. Here in Latin America, we use this markup languages because in many cases what you have are public meta publishers that consume the journal text from the different journal infrastructures and we publish this again so really big loss of the TEI, it was a battle lost because that could have been adopted by 22 countries, that’s not a little thing, so yeah.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You are speaking here and really framing your work in a specific national context. To what extent can digital editing and edition making serve national contexts, serve local contexts, and serve the specific cultures of communities and nations that might not necessarily be reflected within dominant academic perspectives?  </p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	I don’t know if I’m understanding your question but one of the things that I have always thought that digital editions would serve a lot is opening texts, for instance, a lot of digitisation has been done in different libraries around the world so for me it has always been, you know, one of the things that I think that digital scholarly editing has served a lot is in improving the digitisation in digital editions. So, making a text more discoverable more useful in many senses so in that sense I think that the field could help a lot by opening what libraries have been doing or should be doing. I know that the National Library of France has digitised everything also in many other countries or, you know, you find great digitisation of everything but for instance in many countries in Latin America the digitisation is really slow, it has started late and it’s not on a bigger scale but it could really help libraries reaching better other people. Sometimes if you go to the national library and you just download a pdf and it’s just a pdf from the 19th Century it doesn’t, you know, it’s with an old typography or well it won’t be too interesting maybe to younger audiences but a nice digital edition in which you have links and images and it can enhance the digitisation and it can also help reaching other people. And also, I have always imagined people who maybe cannot afford to buy books, you know, digital editions could really help in that sense. Imagine in all our countries that we have these canonical texts that are parts of national literature, in many cases students have to buy those books to then read for their classes, not in every school or university here in Argentina you will find the books at the library so having these open, good, nice digital editions could help also students to find good and nice not only the digitisation but also a more a nice text online I think in that sense digital scholarly editions could serve a lot at many different levels.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I know you’ve written a lot about open access and that in 2017 you contributed to a paper which for a more open digital humanities. You claimed that the field is not yet open by default, do you feel that this is still the case, that it is not open by default?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	What I feel is that in many cases the hard sciences have started at least best practices for making things a little bit more open or recommendations but we are not doing that. What I feel is that sometimes it depends on the researcher and what he or she feels about their project about also the reproducibility of their project because people really want others to adopt or to reuse their text but for me it has always felt something very individual I would love the TEI and I would always have insisted on that why don’t we write a best practice for people to adopt the TEI and work with the TEI or best practice for, you know, working on a… because there are many things for instance if you go to this project called TEI Pelican in which this man is harvesting the data from GitHub or all the things done in TEI that is really, you know, it’s making data open and accessible and reusable but, you know, to get to that project sometimes it’s just someone is telling you ‘oh why don’t you check this project from someone who has been doing this and that’ so it feels… it’s like what in Spanish we call this caso en concreto case there are just some specific cases and other people are not even paying attention to that using the tools that their university has developed and you know and then they publish their edition or maybe when they decide to open their edition, this has happened to the Women Writers Project that has been closed for a long time and then they decide to open the final digital edition but we don’t have a set of, as I was saying, best practices recommendations or at least suggestions to, you know, not only thinking of openness because in the last years also the label open has been put onto many things but in this idea of, you know, if we are always talking about a global DH we shouldn’t only be thinking of conferences or people representing in different languages, we should be thinking of other more long lasting ideas and in that sense I really believe that best practices, recommendations is what can strengthen the field. And that is something that we need to make together no one is going to pay attention to some best practices that only a small group in, you know, Ireland has said it has to be something that’s global, global organisation of DH needs to coordinate and call for people that are working here to join and to think together because that is also something I have read here and there this is what we should be doing, ‘ok, who says it, four people working on a project in someplace?’ Yeah, that’s what I mean by open and, yeah, it’s not just the idea of opening everything because that is not exactly what I believe that we should be doing but making the field more even more equal, more collaborative which you can participate in knowing that you will know how also what you are bringing to the game.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do It seems like everyone embraces but doesn’t always practice openness in the digital humanities, and of course the wider humanities and social sciences. Is this a consequence of individual attitudes? Are there other barriers? Is it just that DH is not open because of various economic realities, a lack of processes and infrastructures suited to supporting a more open humanities? Why is DH not open?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	I wouldn’t say that it is not open. In many cases it has been a very, let’s say, in many cases it has been a really open field for instance, I’m a medievalist and I remember in the first years in which I tried to send a paper for a conference of medievalists here and there you needed to you know someone needed to sign that you were a good student to present something or in many journals in which they prevented you from sending an article if you weren’t, you know, if you didn’t have a specific position. So, I’m not saying specifically that DH is a closed field, it’s not that, what I’m saying that I really feel and this is also a problem of technology, technology is different all around the world and our disciplines are different all around the world so… and that exists but on the opposite we have been insisting for a very long time in creating a global digital humanities, what I say is that it’s not enough in saying that we need a global DH in you know getting together and accepting proposals or texts in different languages it is about how we make the global DH and it’s really a lot about thinking the technology. What I really believe is these recommendations and also recommendations about what technology we are using in our different approaches around the world. What I feel is that that conversation never happened on a global scale and what happened was that ‘ok, you got your project, that’s… now we’re talking because we’re talking about your project and you have specific goals related to your local context and I have mine and individually we want to find out what we are doing to learn from each other but that has always happened in this very small and individual scale so and it’s ok but it’s ok for a moment the thing is that I think we cannot continue to do this forever in DH. If we really want to continue believing that we are building a global community because ‘ok with this Covid thing we go back to everyone working in their different universities, not travelling, not going anywhere, not polluting the air with flying’ and this and that and we change our ideas but it’s taking this, I don’t know, I think we need more, as I was saying, more long-lasting conversations not with this really very focused or individual thing. For instance, just to give you an example for this really unbelievable that after so many years the ADHO is still publishing its journal in a paywall service in Oxford. Like I cannot read Oxford journals from Argentina I can use the SciHub of course but that and everyone is using it in the global south but I know that they have been putting a lot of effort paying for open access so many of the articles published in the journal are open access but because people have taken money from grants and paying for open access. But I don’t think that is global DH that is, you know, because I think that is the typical thing that is individual you can pay for open access you could publish and it makes it open but I cannot if I want to publish in the journal, I cannot do that so that is not global. That’s the kind of thing that I think we need to solve, or not, maybe no one wants to solve that anymore.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Magic wand scenario, if I gave you unlimited resources and technology either existing or imagined, you know, what would the ideal future edition look like, you know, what would it do, how would it function?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	I think that digital editions should be objects or artifacts that anyone could use. In some cases, I think, you know, you can see really great work done in digital scholarly editions but sometimes it’s so difficult to understand how to find something or if you are searching correctly or if you are missing something so in that sense, I have always felt that sometimes in digital editions sometimes, you know, less is better so if you give so much information to a person that arrives to your digital edition that person might leave. Also if I had unlimited resources for a digital edition I would really focus a lot on multilingualism and languages you know in many cases it happens with my students, for instance, we were once working with the Canterbury Tales and you know the digital edition of the Canterbury Tales well, the Canterbury Tales are let’s say the English can be difficult for a person who is not proficient in English from a Spanish speaking country but if you don’t even have any information in different languages to help someone who is reading the text that is also not helping people to stay there to understand your digital edition. And then what I think that is really missing and I don’t know how to solve this but I also started one day a debate on Twitter that wasn’t very useful is like ‘ok, we’re producing all these digital editions but many times and I cannot find them’ if you don’t tell me ‘Oh, I have this project’ or ‘I know this project about this and that’ I don’t even know about them. So how can we solve that is the internet archive something we should be using you know I would really love to think of a project with someone on how to find this because for instance I know where to… if I want to look for books I know I can go either to google books, to WorldCat I know the resources to look for that but in the case of digital editions I randomly start looking or I send a message in Twitter ‘hey do you know about any troubadour poetry digital editions?’ because in many cases the indexes or the catalogues that we have are incomplete not because the editors have failed but because I know the Sahle spent a lot of time doing this catalogue and Greta too. I think that it’s cool for a moment but a human cannot be paying attention to all the data validations around the world that are being published from time to time so how do we solve that? Because why are we starting all this really sometimes long complicated projects on digital editions if then they are lost or you only get to know them because you have attended one conference and you get to know the project in that panel so that’s the problem too if I had unlimited resources I would, I don’t know join with internet archive or someone really powerful that can do that you I know not human work but machine work and make the digital editions more visible.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That idea of machine work is interesting, and I know that you’ve published on automatic recognition and tagging of named entities in digital editions – do you think machine learning will be more central to future digital editions?</p></sp><sp who="#GR"><speaker>GR</speaker><p>	In my case, for us, it helped a lot our work also the infrastructure that you need for annotating that is so much is involved than for encoding and the type of work I know the pros and cons about annotation and annotation tools but for my project it was really useful to start you know from there also for the people who were involved in the project as the hermeneutics of the work, for them it was more interesting for them it was more simple to go to the text and annotation reading and annotating but in many cases just encoding so I don’t know I know that annotation tools are really being developed right now I use a lot of Hypothesis and I think that it’s a great annotation tool but for instance if you leave google chrome and you work with Mozilla that is a more open web browser it doesn’t work so that’s a limitation. You need to work with google to work with hypothesis perfectly. Recogito is a really good tool but it helps you annotating specific features, you know, you can’t annotate people, events I know the developer is working on a more open tool right now also for images that is a notorious tool so what I feel is maybe in five years annotation tools are improved and I am really in favour of them and I would continue using them. I am using them but there are limitations right now but I think they are really, really useful and in my case and in… I have been teaching DH before I teach encoding, I teach annotation, that is how I have been teaching digital edition for a long time and while I could do, I haven’t started any project on you know user experience but most of the students find it useful for their work.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>