<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Samantha Rayner</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on March 14th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_SR.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>SAMANTHA RAYNER is Professor of Publishing and Book Cultures in the Department of Information Studies, and Vice Dean Wellbeing in the Faculty of Arts and Humanities at University College, London.  She is also the General Editor for the Cambridge University Press Elements series on Publishing and Book Culture, and a co-Director of the Bookselling Research Network.  </p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do the terms digital editing and digital publishing mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Well, that’s a question to start on, isn’t it?! Digital editing itself as a skill is not something that I would say is within my, you know, something that I know how to do so I know there are very specialist tools that people do that, that is not something that I do. Digital publishing I’m more familiar with because of course that is kind of my day job as a lecturer in publishing, we obviously have to keep on top of what is going on in the digital realm and just to throw my project in, I suppose that’s why I’m here, The Academic Book of the Future project that I was involved with very much we looked at, you know, exactly that kind of blue sky thinking so if you push that envelope as far as people could, what would they imagine the digital could actually do in terms of the academic book in the digital realm more generally so scholarly editions were part of that discussion but obviously we were looking at the whole rainbow of different kinds of academic books. So that really opened my eyes to particularly things that performance academics were doing and how they wrestle with what is a book and it’s not a text based combination of paper and cardboard to them it's sort of looking at how a live performance can be turned into a book that their kind of audiences would understand and that would meaningfully represent the kind of research that they do so yeah it was really eye opening to work with them and then with the technology companies who were trying to see whether they could make that happen in reality. Lincoln University got quite far actually, they had an amazing idea about a book that was these sort of tables that you could get that you could put your hands on and you could move things around digitally on the table so a really sort of ambitious idea about having those in libraries that they would be sort of loaded. So that was where I suppose… because I do work with editions of texts more kind of old school in terms of… so this is where I’m hoping you will take me in terms of your questioning and how those editions of scholarly literary works come to us as readers and as scholars but they were really thinking about the end user very much and how could an academic library utilise the digital to make a digital book more exiting than just a PDF or an eBook but which are still quite static things.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Can you tell me a bit more about the Academic Book of the Future project? What were the key findings?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Yeah so, gosh it’s funny isn’t it we’ve all lost a few years, it ran from 2015 to 2017, it was a call set up by the British Library and the AHRC so we didn’t come up with the title we had to kind of pitch to be the team that ran the project and our pitch was quite ambitious because we went in and said right if we were going to do this knowing upfront that it’s going to be impossible to cover everything we would none the less want to try to talk to as many different arts and humanities fields as possible, we want to involve the publishers, the librarians, the book sellers, the general public, you know we really want to find out what people think an academic book is and what it could be in the future. There was at the time and I suppose that is still true, my sense was that it was political agenda underneath it was very much to do with open access but we managed to stand firm throughout that and say look this is not a project which is just about open access books, we will look at that in the mix and the findings pretty much confirmed that for Arts and Humanities in 2017, open access was still not something that the majority of the people that we spoke to either understood or really got behind which I don’t think was the answer that the funders really wanted us to come up with. And here we are five years later and there’s still a lot of debate around that and I think publishers and Arts and Humanities academics are still catching up with the whole wait, what will happen if we have to publish open access and of course that’s suddenly become more precious because the next REF is supposed to bring the books into the equation and so we are going to have to figure that out. But yeah we work with lots of different people across the communities, university librarians are particularly interesting in talking about digital publishing because of course they’ve got a big vested interest in the future of where academic books are going so yeah there was a lot of discussion about the role that an academic library should play in the production of an academic book, that was something I hadn’t anticipated being such a big a part of the project results as it was. And then the role of the intermediary so not just the publishing companies but particularly for digital books, you know, publishing companies work with tech companies to produce a product so nobody had really looked at the role that those intermediaries played in the whole process and how important they were going to become and what kind of people they were going to be and how did publishers and libraries need to work with those people to make the academic book of the future a viable thing.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that the constellation of disciplines and practices that you’ve pointed to there, fields like editing, libraries, publishing, do you think they are all sufficiently integrated?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	No, not to the level that they really need to be. So the subtitle of our project was ‘communities of practice’ and it was very much about bringing those different communities together and seeing if we could connect them a bit more coherently I suppose because you realise that librarians talk a different language, they have different imperatives going on than an academic has and then a publisher has different imperatives again so there were times when… there were certain words and they were very simple words, edition might have been one of them but that I hadn’t appreciated mean something to me as a humanities scholar, to a librarian it means something completely different and to a publisher it means something different and until you got us all in a room where you were discussing that there was suddenly this lightbulb moment where it was like ‘ah that’s why we’re not getting anywhere’ because you don’t understand what I mean and I’m assuming I understand what you mean by that term and I don’t at all. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think those attitudes towards open access have changed any bit since?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	I think from the publisher’s perspective, particularly with university presses there have been amazing strides forward in what university presses do. So one of the research in practice things we did when the project was on was to test our own idea with UCL Press of what the academic book of the future could look like and we came up with - don’t laugh - ‘The BOOC’, B-O-O-C, so five years ago, James, you might not remember these but MOOCs were huge things so we thought well if you can have a MOOC what about a BOOC; Books as Open Online Content and this would be an online platform so UCL Press worked with their technology partner and we did one for Academic Book of the Future. It’s still up on the website if you want to have a look at it and it’s supposed to be a live book so it’s completely like a normal academic book would be in terms of peer review and that was a headache in terms of trying to figure out well how do you peer review something like a blog post, we wanted it to be content wise a little bit more ambitious as well so not just traditional articles but you know we’ve got all this material and content had been generated by the project and we wanted to be able to capture that as an academic output but things like videos or blog post are not counted as part of an academic output unless you’ve come up with a way of doing that and so BOOC did manage to do that, there were DOIs for every entry so it was REF countable and there was a lot of interest around it and people liked the kind of whizzy platform you could just go in and just download the bits that you wanted and of course it was open access so it was all free and I understand the press have had enquiries since then. But what’s interesting is that perhaps from a user’s perspective, we’re not as keen as we might think we are to actually have a go at some of these more bells and whistles type outputs and for me at the moment on sabbatical and trying to do the research for my own book, I mean a lot of it is obviously in archives because it’s historical research but even the stuff that isn’t, it’s making me reflect again, it’s so much easier just to get a physical book and just get on with the reading than it is to try and figure out from an online thing how I need to sign in and get access and then how I use it and then how do I cite it, you know, my head is like I just want a straight forward way through this. That’s just a personal reflection I don’t know how in tune that is with other A&amp;H researchers certainly I’m sure my Digital Humanities colleagues would have a completely different perspective but I haven’t seen as much movement forward from the academics in my field as you might expect even within the field of publishing studies actually.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It sounds like you feel your work as a book historian isn’t sufficiently catered to; what’s missing?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Honestly James, it’s back to basics, I mean it’s really basic digitisation stuff which again now I’ve looked, I’ve dipped my toe in the water because I’ve been banging on why can’t we… I mean The Bookseller for example is as very key journal for book studies research, it’s been running since 1858, it isn’t digitised at all and there’s no index which means if I want to go and see what The Bookseller said about bookseller training in the 1920s, I literally have to go to a library, call up all the copies and go through it page by tortuous page and that is fun but none of us have got enough life in us to spend that amount of time but I also know how much time and how expensive it is to digitise something properly and by that I mean taking images of each of the pages and then tagging everything so it’s searchable and findable and that’s really… I don’t know how we get around that because it costs money, it costs a lot of money and a lot of time so who are the people that are going to do that kind of activity?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	As someone who has done much work on publishing, both digital and pre-digital, do you feel that publishing practices have changed at all? Have there been radical changes, or has it really not changed at all? Are doing things now that are transformative or are we just putting things online? </p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Yes, I mean bottom line is there are little bits of transformation. The other series that I’m involved in is Cambridge University Press’s Elements platform and the whole reason for setting up that series on that platform for publishing and book culture was again as a sort of research in practice thing to see how willing the press as a very old and established university press how they would work with me to make that platform more flexible for people but again at the moment still, again, five years after we’ve started, the limits of the platform still seem to be that you can stick up online additional documents or video content but you know that’s kind of the level of the innovation that’s going on and I’m not blaming the Press for that, again, I think it’s a user thing so the users themselves, we could go out to the editors and the authors and say what would you like, nobody really knows what they want, they would like something exciting and new, I’m not really sure what that looks like.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s a great way of putting it, that nobody really knows what they want. Do you think that the present moment is one in which we have come to re-appreciate the book?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	I think the pandemic has definitely pushed people back more towards the physical book and I mean that’s borne out by the evidence, the fact that we’ve got more independent book shops in the UK now than we did before the pandemic started which is an incredible thing when you think about the amount of other retail shops that have shut down during the pandemic, book shops have actually thrived and grown larger in terms of numbers and they’re more successful. So the interesting thing about that is of course the other thing that’s launched recently is bookshop.org which is the online version, it’s not digital books, they’re selling physical books but the other thing the pandemic has made us aware is that it’s that panic of how do I get hold of my physical book, people are still wanting to buy physical books even though at some points during the pandemic actual book shops were shut they were still doing quite a large amount of trade through people ordering books from them online and then posting them out which because we’re so close to it I’m sure somebody is doing research on that but don’t you think that’s fascinating, you’d think that people would just totally switch to the kindle or the eBook because it’s instant but that’s not what’s happened, people seem to have been buying more physical books even though they were hard to get hold of.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Why do you think that is?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	I think that because this is where my wellbeing hat comes in as well, I think that sense of when you’re reading something for pleasure or to escape from something there is something about holding a physical book that the feel of the pages, the heft of it in your hands, I don’t want to get too poetical but you know the smell of the paper that makes you feel that you are in that experience. I’ve got a PhD student at the moment who is looking at the experience of children during the pandemic who were read to by parents or grandparents who were not in the same room so using digital devices, how did that work, what were they doing and interestingly, she started off by thinking well obviously they were reading like digital children’s books, right but no most of the people that she surveyed and interviewed the grandparents or the parents were reading a physical book to the child and the child in many instances had a copy of that physical book whether that was printed out pages or whatever but it seemed really important for them to have the physical book rather than to be working from what must have been an easier option to just have a digital book to work from so that research will be very interesting when she’s finished analysing all that later.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You edit the Cambridge University Press Elements series, Publishing and Book Culture, which publishes books as both print and open access. Is the importance of the physical object the motivation behind the Elements model?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Well yes James thank you that’s exactly what I was going for so it was really important to me that that particular series and boy did we have a fight with CUP to start off with because they’ve got hundreds of years of design history at that press and I said look these are little books, we price them right and we put a jacket on that is distinctive in the way that Penguin had those pocket classic series, then people will buy them and they will collect them and they will look lovely on the shelf as a physical collection of books, right. And we did win that battle so our Element Series is the only one that’s got that bespoke cover with the Baskerville Ampersand in the different colours for the different strands and they do look nice now I’ve got to say, I don’t know how many there are now in the series but over twenty so there’s a nice kind of block of them on my shelf and they do look nice. But we are still fighting with the press because they see the whole Elements thing as a platform that they sell in its entirety to university libraries. So the other big lesson that I learnt was that university presses/academic publishers, the shift there is that they’re selling to libraries they’re not selling to individual people anymore and I think there is a cost there in terms of… well there is a literal cost in that you know if you try to buy an academic, there’s just some of them ridiculously expensive if you want to buy a copy. The benefit is of course for those of us who are lucky enough to be part of a university with a respectable library budget you know we do have access to a lot of books online now so you know UCL has got access to I can’t remember what the Cambridge platform is called but if you’re part of an institution that can’t afford that then what does that mean, it seems to me, I know this is quite controversial but you know in some ways there’s nothing more open access than a physical book on a library shelf that somebody can walk in you know anyone can walk in and borrow that whereas digital books, even if they’re open access it’s no good if you can’t download them because your institution can’t afford to have them then it’s not open access it’s the opposite of open access because you’re shutting people’s ability to get that book out unless they can afford to pay for the copy themselves which is again why the £9 keeping it under £10 for these little books was important to me.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Could you envisage a future wherein some of the material aspects of books that we value might be remediated to the digital?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Well, I did. I did hope this in my naïve kind of ‘this is what the future is going to be like’. I have done some research, so my textual edition research has been on Sir Thomas Malory’s ‘Le Morte D’Arthur’ which has some very interesting textual history and a very fascinating academic scholarly editing history as well and whereas it was feasible to do research on the early twentieth-century edition of that text because Oxford University Press have got archives and there was a lot of correspondence in there that I could look at and then suss out where there might be other places. The recent edition which was actually edited by my old supervisor, I thought, well this is going to be quite straight forward because I know Peter Field I will just ask him and his editor at Boydell and Brewer to save all their email correspondence, so just to tell them please do not delete anything because I know what the value of that archive with the letters in it from the older edition was and I interviewed both of them and I’ve got notes and things but it became impossible because actually your emails are so difficult to hold, you’ve got to ask the person who wrote the email, it’s on their system it’s not a physical thing, right, so people would say ‘I’m not sure whether I’m going to, you can have these but you can’t have these’, so there’s a kind of curation that goes on and then the masses of correspondence that we have these days. I was looking at your project website and the example it gave about Trumps Tweets and how that’s feasibly something that people might want in the future and I thought yeah, that’s exactly it. I mean, how do we start and I worked with somebody in my department called Jenny Bun who is an archivist specialist because it’s a real bugbear of mine why aren’t publishers and people saving stuff, it’s all being chucked out because there’s not space and she taught me from an archivist perspective an archivist is not looking to save everything, it was like ‘wait, what?!’ and an archivist in a digital age has to make some really hard decisions about what they’re going to save and how they’re going to save it and how they’re going to tag it and I think perhaps that is one of the biggest challenges for conserving histories of particularly digital editions not just the doing of a digital edition but the paratextual elements which are really important actually if you’re looking at how this scholarly editing chose this particular part because the text itself changes depending on that editor’s view and you need to have that explained to you and then what happens if they’re an elderly academic and you know they die before they’ve got a chance to tell anyone we’ll never know the answers so there seems to be more danger now of researchers of the future just being completely stymied of the fact that there’s been this digital death of stuff because I don’t know, you’ll know more about this than I will James but yeah it’s worry I think in terms of conserving stuff in today, it’s going to be a lot harder than it was in a time when people would just save every memo and every letter that they wrote. Yeah, does that help.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Saving stuff, that’s interesting. You mentioned performance. Performance is often intended to be ephemeral, or certainly, they’re not developed with edition-making in mind. How do we actually turn something that is based on performance, particularly, born-digital acts of performance, into something more bookish? How do we preserve forms of digital writing that are based on systems that are now becoming or are already obsolete? We no longer have epistolary evidence because people send emails rather than letters. Do we just need to accept that we will lose a lot to digital rot?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Yeah that’s really where we’re at now so there is this big emphasis on how do we get all the different parties involved to keep the stuff around the digital editions and that brings me back to the communities of practice so I mean publishers these days it’s kind of less chance that you’re going to have an editor that stays in post for twenty/thirty years, they tend to change jobs quickly because the companies are reshaping themselves so there’s that kind of element of today’s working practices works against you and do they understand and appreciate how important it is for scholars to have that stuff? No. Why should they really that’s not their job. Should it be part of their job? That’s a big question which you know we’ve asked. Maybe some of the traditional older presses do understand the importance of their history but I’ve sort of said to UCL Press they’re already perhaps nearly ten years into their life, who’s keeping records of, you know those early decisions would be really interesting to a scholar of the future in terms of how they develop their open access vision and who was the driving force behind some of those things. Perhaps we’re just going to be in a different age where those kinds of researching practices are no longer done, there’s going to be new things that we’re researching instead.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	If I gave you unlimited resources and technology both real and imagined, what would you do, what would you change, how would you envisage the book of the future or the practices surrounding publishing?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	If I had unlimited resources I would use them to figure out a way of… if we can’t, we can’t, not even with a magic wand realistically keep everything but we could put in place a system where we could capture enough of the paratextual stuff and the conversations that go behind any text to make that often very complicated layers of talk, of the effort and the work that goes into some of these especially digital editions, you know, that finished product that you get with that edition of that work is literally a tip of an iceberg of work underneath it and I know there’s a lot of tools now that will, that you can see the different iterations of how the text evolves and that’s great but I suppose my scepticism now that I know more is just thinking even if I had a magic wand I’m not sure how we’d do it because we’ve got too many different disparate groups, who would be responsible for it, publishers haven’t got the money and it’s not really their role, the scholars want it to happen perhaps but we our funding pots are being shrunken more so maybe the magic wand would give much more money to us humanities researchers, more than we’ve got at the moment so there could be more projects like yours going on because presumably your project will end in a report but your project will end when your funding ends and so my question back to you James is and then what, what are you hoping to achieve with your project then?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	We’re going to come up with far more questions than we began with, I think that is clear, and if we’re lucky, we might be better positioned to answer the questions we started with this time the next time around. And so the cycle of funding, research, funding, research continues. And maybe that’s the issue here, maybe our problem in this space is cultural rather than technical?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Yes. I’ve no doubt that there are people out there with amazing technical skills who could produce whatever vision any one of us could come up with in terms of this is what we want to do, the trouble is the technical people need to be told what we want them to do and there aren’t enough of us and I’m embarrassingly one of those. I couldn’t really tell you what I wanted, I would know it if I saw it and I would say that’s amazing but I never knew I needed that but apart from saying I keep banging on about the fact that people should keep their correspondence somewhere safe, I definitely would want them to do that, I can’t really imagine what the bells and whistles bit what’s the next stage of the academic book. We didn’t really come up with any answers either you know it would need a… even those wonderful tables which would transform the way that we use libraries, you know Lincoln was saying they would need to find a sponsor like Microsoft or Google or somebody like that would need to come on board in order to make it a reality because it needs to be a cultural change, it doesn’t need to be just a local this is just for one library, right, we need to teach our students these skills and how to use these new things and nothing is joined up at the moment.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Speaking of students, do you bring this stuff into the classroom?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Yes.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And how do students, particular younger cohorts, respond to all of this?</p></sp><sp who="#SR"><speaker>SR</speaker><p>	Students have lots of great ideas and of course ours is a publishing MA so a lot of them go into the publishing industry and I think there’s increasingly a sense that if they go off to an established company there’s then a kind of ‘oh’ moment when they realise there’s just such a structural, cultural blocking points to get to the point where they could make any change. A lot of our students now interestingly are starting up their own businesses are trying new things themselves from scratch because that’s the positive about where we are right now, it's much easier for you to start up your own thing online even if that’s something like a book boxing service, a subscription service where you curate books and I think that is exciting. So we can teach students more skills about that, about how you use the online world to power yourselves, you don’t have to wait to be employed by Penguin or Faber, why don’t you do it yourself, you’ve got a dream, do it. But we’ve watched companies like Unbound arrive on the scene with the crowd funding model which has been quite interesting, they’ve been quite successful BookBoxing is still quite successful they’ve had somebody, I don’t know whether you saw on Dragons Den this week who didn’t get funded by the dragons interestingly but there was an article in the Book Seller today which said their sales went up hugely in the ten minutes after the programme even though they didn’t get the funding from the dragons so there’s that. There’s bookshop.org which is an interesting new model which you know puts money back into the independent bookshops and the whole push at the moment in the publishing industry for diversity, for more diverse voices to come through will hopefully bring new talent in terms of what those voices are going to have in terms of what they want to see come through in new types of books so it’s not all a dreary picture. I think it is exciting and obviously my students have now reached the age, James, where my students are actually younger than my son and he’s pretty digitally savvy you know he works for Oracle and he’s very good at the digital stuff so I completely understand and know that they will have these tools deep in them in a way that my generation never did because we weren’t born with computers around and things so yeah I’m hopeful for the future even though I don’t have the vision to see what that future might look like but I think it all depends on getting all those different communities to really talk to each other more than they do at the moment because publishers have a really sometimes in academic publishing a really old idea of what we as researchers want.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>