<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Christopher P. Long</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on September 29th, 2021</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_CL.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>CHRISTOPHER P. LONG is a Michigan State University Foundation Professor and Dean of two colleges: the College of Arts &amp; Letters and the MSU Honors College. He is committed to the transformative power of a liberal arts education and is a leading advocate for public scholarship, community engaged participatory research, and a values-enacted approach to academic life. Dean Long is also an expert in both ancient Greek and contemporary continental philosophy, and his extensive publication record includes four books. He has over $7M of funded research projects, including the Mellon funded Less Commonly Taught Languages Partnership with the Big 10 Academic Alliance, a participatory research initiative and teaching framework developed in reciprocal partnership with Indigenous communities, including Indigenous faculty and language instructors; the Public Philosophy Journal, an innovative online publication for accessible scholarship that deepens our understanding of publicly relevant issues; HuMetricsHSS, a values-enacted initiative committed to transforming higher education by aligning indicators of academic excellence with core personal and institutional values; and the Charting Pathways of Intellectual Leadership initiative designed to empower staff and faculty to align their core values with the processes of promotion and advancement that shape their academic lives. </p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What have digital editing and digital publishing, however it is that you interpret those terms, given us?</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	Well, the first thing that comes to mind for me is the public nature of digital publishing, the opportunities it affords for openness and publicness. There is this combination of the oral tradition with the written tradition that we get with digital editing and publishing. The dynamic aspects of the oral combine with the more stable static and potentially preservable components of written work. So, when I think just in these broad terms as you have presented them, about what digital publishing and editing have given us, it is this capacity to capture the best of the dynamic side of the oral tradition with the more stable component of the tradition of writing. Of course, the infrastructure for that is ever evolving and has to be developed. In fact, the earlier work that even you and I were trying to do when we were at Penn State was, I think, committed to the public nature of some of this work but there are all sorts of habits that have to be developed. I’m talking not only about technical developments but new habits of scholarship and habits of creativity and scholarly writing that we need to cultivate in this new environment; well, I suppose it’s not so new anymore but it’s still very young if you compare it to the beginning of writing as a new technology.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s interesting that you say habits; I saw on the Public Philosophy Journal that one of your ambitions is to cultivate habits of collaboration and collegiality. How are you doing this?</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	So in the Public Philosophy Journal what we’re trying to do is structure a formative review process in which colleagues can enter a space of collegiality, of trust, of friendship to develop ideas more fully. So, we are really trying to push away from the notion of a truth emerging in combat, where ideas are combatting one another, where you have this agonistic framework. We are trying to move it into a framework of creating a space in which because people care about each other and trust one another and can say hard things to each other we can actually get at a deeper, more robust way of articulating the work, a deeper access to the truth. There is this ancient Greek idea that the truth will out through this agonistic battle of wits and ideas and I think that that has caused all sorts of toxicity and negativity. So what we’re trying to do in the Public Philosophy Journal is to invite people to imagine themselves engaged with a friend who they want to help make their work better and then also to do that with ideas and with content that is relevant for public communities, for communities beyond the Academy and the vision is for us to see if we could actually do scholarship with colleagues, with the public itself so that we are gaining the wisdom of the public as well as bringing the wisdom of disciplines and more academically inflected view point.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Can you speak more to that, the relationship between things like medium, digital publishing practices and the cultivation of particular habits?</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	Yeah so, one of the things we’re doing in what we’re calling the Collaborative Community Review which is how we’re thinking about our formative review process, is we have a Review Co-ordinator, somebody who is charged with navigating and managing the relationships and so what that person is asked to do is to is sort of the opposite of anonymous review in the sense that people know who they are and you have to be willing to put yourself behind your feedback and be wholly who you are in giving your feedback. When you think about habits, the habits that have historically been part of the Academy have often been about how you appear, how smart you appear to be and how witty and cunning your insights might be in a public arena. Here, we’re really trying to cultivate habits of openness, habits of vulnerability, humility that are not necessarily things people have historically been rewarded for in higher education. I mean, and I think to our detriment because when people can be vulnerable and humble, they learn and we can together move closer to some kind of articulation of the truth. I mean it’s interesting when you think about digital scholarship and writing and publishing in, you know, you can see it in Facebook, you can see it on Twitter, you can see the reduction to the lowest common denominator, people forget that there are actually human beings on the other side of these, you know, tweets or of these view posts and I’m hoping that we can turn the public arena into something where it would be more caring for lack of a better term and human really.I mean of course the human has the ugly in it too, so the trolling is in one way humanity expresses itself. A good example of this from my own experience is that when I am asked to do an anonymous review for a journal and I know that the author is not going to see my comments, actually, I don’t put as much thought into how I’m actually going to articulate this position because I don’t have that sense of accountability that would come from another… the person who cares about this and who has written this actually hearing directly my viewpoint and especially if I’m not going to have to own it as who I am, I can be anonymous. So, I try in those contexts to actually imagine that what I say will be read and will be associated with my name because I find that it requires me to be more thoughtful, and not only more caring but more careful about exactly articulating what I want to say in a way that can be heard by the person who is writing the piece or who is the author of the piece so that’s what I want to leverage. How can you get that? How could you get a journal or even interactions digitally and publicly that foster that kind of engagement?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And to achieve this, must it be digital?</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	Um no, probably not, I mean what I would say on that score is that in some ways we can get at that more interhuman dimension when it's not digital when we are face to face and actually engaged with content together. On the other hand, what I would say is because so much of our lives together is mediated through the digital, we need to learn how to be human in this medium and that’s really what a lot of my work has been focused on. So when I was at Penn State, before podcasting was all the rage, I was podcasting back in 2006 &amp; 7 &amp; 8 and I was inviting my colleagues onto this podcast that was called the Digital Dialogue to talk about the things that they’d published as I was writing my book on Socrates and Plato. Those podcasts became part of that book project. The tagline for the Digital Dialogue was ‘cultivating excellences of dialogue in a digital age’, the idea was to cultivate habits of real dialogue in a digital age, and I felt like the podcast format actually captured the oral dimension very well, even more than the written component of it. I wanted to invite my colleagues who had just published something that I was reading that related to Ancient Greek Philosophy to come onto the podcast to talk about what they did, that way I could amplify their work and make it more public and maybe get more readers for them but of course, I was also learning at a deeper level what they had written. So I had read their article and I had invited them onto the podcast and just by putting the microphone between us the conversation was elevated because people kind of knew ‘oh this might be actually out on the web’ and there was a kind of accountability there. Some of the best conversations I’ve had, you know, are in those podcasts, I don’t know I think I did 73 or something, so I do think it’s incumbent upon us in this time to teach ourselves how to be how to be… how to leverage the affordances of the digital for the kind of human engagement we want and to advance research and scholarship to be more specific but we have to do that while we also recognise the limitations of these technologies. And that’s where, you know, the trolling, the kind of performative pieces that are corrosive that sometimes come into the digital also or at least the public dimension of the digital. I guess I’ve emphasised that public piece of it because I’m very interested in the way public conversations hold us accountable, but obviously the digital can be very private too.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You’ve written a great deal about public scholarship and you practice it in much of what you do. What does public scholarship look like in its ideal from, and what does it achieve?</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	So, I would probably separate it from the digital per se.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Okay…</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	So in its ideal form public scholarship would be a collaborative endeavour in which people entered into it in good faith to try to articulate together something that is true that is just in terms of creating, building community that is functionable and fair and equitable and then I would also say, I know I’m talking to a poet too, beautiful, I mean the aesthetic dimension of beauty has to be in there. So I go back to that socratic, platonic idea of the just, the beautiful and the good and if I were going to articulate the ideal public scholarship I would say also say that ideal scholarship generally is oriented toward the just, the beautiful and the good and that means that we have to cultivate practices that embody those values in the way that we interact with one other. I’m going to say this, and I think I really do believe it, you really are not going to get something just, beautiful and good if you are embodying habits that are corrosive and ugly and nefarious and duplicitous. So I mean, I suppose maybe accidentally something could happen, some ugliness could lead to beauty but what I really am trying to model and put my weight behind and theorise and practice is a way of being together with others that generates just, beautiful, and good work and in order to do that I think we have to be wholly honest, we have to be whole beings as we enter into that space. In terms of public scholarship, we have to create a public space where people can be who they are and where they don’t have to be constantly fronting so that they appear to be something that they think they need to appear to be in order to seem smart or to seem credible. It’s not an easy project.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And where does pedagogy come into this?</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	Well, I think you can learn to do it. I think you can learn to do scholarship in this kind of way, and it requires the kind of pedagogical practices that create the space for students to bring their whole selves into relation with one another and to see how meaning can emerge from that. That’s the pedagogical project that creates those spaces and then gives assignments that structure ways of engaging work, structure experiences such that students can practice that and also be supported when they fall and they fail and they don’t do what they wish they had done or make a mistake. I mean to me it’s almost as if people sometimes I think ‘well students should just already know how to write’ or already know how to all these things. But they’re in the class and that’s why they’re here: to learn how to do that and if we berate them for not knowing how to do what they’re there to learn to do we’re really in a bad way. So, we need to create the environment where people can feel empowered to be who they are and to bring their best selves forward and to fall flat on their face if they have to. That sometimes can be the biggest leap forward in terms of their own learning and it certainly doesn’t help if they do fall flat on their face for us to then kick them further, it’s just ridiculous. So, I think the pedagogical side of it is really important and what I’m focusing my work on both as an administrator and as a scholar myself but in administrative work is how can I create the culture of care that allows for that kind of learning environment to emerge and where faculty are rewarded for that kind of teaching and where students are recognised for the kind of risk that they are taking when they engage in that kind of work.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, this idea of the public scholar; you are obviously a public scholar in that you embrace open research and open modes of communication, and you yourself work and present yourself quite publicly across all these different digital platforms. Someone once told me that some people grow up in public and it seems to me that, from a professional perspective, Chris Long has done that. You consistently attempt to share your thoughts, ideas and research in open and transparent ways. But do you worry that there is a tension between the figure of the public scholar and the reality that much of our cultural conversation is now happening on digital platforms that really aren’t designed for longevity and preservation? Do the ideals of public scholarship exist to the detriment of knowledge preservation and research sustainability?</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	So there’s at least a couple of components here. One component is the question of preservation and archiving, which I do think a lot about and which I want to make a comment or two about. The other piece of it is, you know, the process of ideation and idea development and I think there’s a whole range of challenges that we’re moving, I hope we’re moving beyond and I think somebody like Kathleen Fitzpatrick has been a really wise help in modelling some of this. When I would encourage my graduate students to blog and to write publicly about their ideas, they would inevitably come back and say ‘well, Professor so and so says don’t let anything out there until its fully baked because somebody is going to look at that and might be looking at you for a job and say this is just a half-baked thing not really valuable’ and I would push back on that and say ‘no’ what they’ll do is they’ll say ‘this is clearly a blog post’ or, you know, ‘something in process’ and ‘look at how this person is actually willing to think out loud about their work’. So, I think those are some of the habits that we need to cultivate and then that cultural change we need to make in terms of how we think about higher education. It’s true that I would like people to read my books and to look at my published articles that have been edited and refined and revised though feedback as the more canonical parts of my work but I also want them to find interesting what I find interesting when I study somebody whose work I care about; how did they come to that idea, where are the tensions in their thinking, how was this idea developed over time? I mean if you look at any great thinker, you’re going to find a development and that’s part of the great joy of scholarship into those thinkers because they’re human beings and they develop, so there’s that piece. Now the other thing that I think you’re getting at is the infrastructure question with things like Twitter, things like Medium, even blog posting, when, you know, depending on your platform, it might go down, how are we archiving that kind of stuff? So, I’ve been thinking a lot about that which is why I’ve been trying to focus on things like the Humanities Commons and other kinds of repositories but particularly ones that are not for profit so that’s why the Humanities Commons as an infrastructure for me is really important. As I think about the Public Philosophy Journal, you know, we are trying to build that into library quality archives so that that work is captured and maintained. Personally, I spend, you know, not an insignificant amount of time making sure that my blog and all of that infrastructure that I have around the blog is backed up and that I can preserve that, I have spent a lot of time putting my own published pieces in repositories, first at Penn State in the ScholarSphere and then when I got to Michigan State I put a bunch of it into the Humanities Commons because we didn’t have an Institutional Repository although now MSU has the MSU Commons which is based on the Humanities Commons. So, I want to have that kind of longevity and preservation to the work but then you worry also about well, you know, sometimes you get to thinking ‘well, what happens if the whole internet goes down and all that goes down?’ I mean, of course libraries burn too, you know that’s true. Yeah, those are questions that… ‘what happens to the cultural history when we heat the planet so much that we can’t sustain life on it or at least not enough of an infrastructure of life to maintain the internet?’ Those are important questions to consider.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you worry about the ecological impact of this model of scholarship?</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	Yes, I do but mostly because it’s so opaque to us, I mean, it seems so easy to just upload stuff and it’s so abstract and the energy and the heat and everything that goes into the infrastructure to support that is completely invisible to those of us doing the work, not completely but it’s very abstract to me. I know that Amazon has tons of data from me and Google and Apple with all the pictures and everything else and I know, a not insignificant amount of my own income goes to annual costs of some of that stuff and some of it is free so to speak but I think we need to do a lot of work around sustainability for this, you know. I don’t think people recognise how much of an impact on the environment that we’re having and I know it’s even worse with stuff like crypto and stuff like that I was just reading some things about that, it’s a whole different level. </p><p>I think because it is opaque you just think pfft I’ll just post this stuff…My stepfather is a Methodist Minister, spent 38 years preaching and I probably don’t have all of his sermons, but I have certainly the last 20 years and it fits on a thumb drive. They’re all word documents it’s not as if its taking up a lot but I know increasingly its not just a word, it’s not just text documents, it’s videos all kinds of other stuff and I’d be interested in knowing, I mean, obviously regular paper scholarship also has an impact on the environment in terms of trees and paper and shipping and producing of physical journals but I don’t think we adequately recognise the impact that digital forms of scholarship are having on the environment.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Blue sky situation, what would you like future digital publishing to look like? What would you like the future of this field to offer that we don’t have now?</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	I think platforms that are sustainable both in terms of the climate sustainability that we were talking about but also sustainable in terms of, emotionally and psychologically sustainability, that is to say platforms that don’t drain you of all your energy and sap you from some things that are generative and hopeful and thoughtful. So a lot of that has to do with how are we creating the space each time with pedagogy, how are we creating the digital spaces, the publishing spaces that foster the kind of engagement that is enriching, that is encouraging us to think in creative ways, to push beyond our limits, to be humble, all of those, to be collaborative, to recognise that we are interconnected at a core level an ontological basic level that needs to be nurtured. One aspect of this that is more of a philosophical component that I’ve been thinking a lot more about which is this notion of relationality, the notion of our interconnection. The modern atomic individual has dominated scholarship in terms of the sort of ontological framework that we’ve been using to understand things and there are some positive dimensions to it, individual liberties and freedoms and things like that, but what we have to come to terms with at the deepest level is that we are interconnected with one another and not only other humans but also other organisms both organic and inorganic, living organisms but also inorganic matter that is impacted by everything that we are doing. And so I would love to create ways of doing scholarship that is attuned to that complexity, to the inter-relational dimensions of the human condition and of, I would say, the natural condition and really push out toward a lot of the kind of more theoretical work that people are talking about like Rosi Braidotti and others around the Posthuman and recognising our, you know, the fact that we’re interconnected and I mean that also digitally, there’s interesting ways in which the digital probably can give us insight into that deep ontological relationality that is at the core of not only life but I would say the cosmos broadly. So I just went really big and really broad but you said blue-sky, so I went into the deepest darkest part of the cosmos.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That idea of relationality is particularly interesting…</p></sp><sp who="#CL"><speaker>CL</speaker><p>	Well, I think the challenge, where it goes back to very practical questions of scholarship is ‘ok well, what counts as an author? I mean there’s no text that I’ve written that I’ve put my name to that was just me, you know, and how do I recognise my relationality with those that have given generously their feedback who have, and those would even be the things that I would notice, you know, somebody who would have reviewed a work and who gave me feedback or who I’d had a great conversation with that I could put into a footnote to say nothing of the teachers who helped me understand even how to think about things in a certain way or other modes of support that I have that allow for the work to be done. So that really, you know, even something as basic as, you know, how we’re thinking about authorship becomes a real important ethical question and it’s something that we’ve done a lot of thinking about with the HuMetrics Grant because if you’re really committed to putting your values into practice in doing the work that you’re doing, you have to recognise that this work that’s been produced has been produced because of your encounters with others and how do you recognise that while also taking ownership of, you know, the work as well. I’m not saying well this is just the result of a conglomeration of forces but it actually is also my work or ours together.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>