<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Matthew K. Gold</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on January 27th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_MG.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>MATTHEW K. GOLD is Associate Professor of English and Digital Humanities at The Graduate Center, CUNY, where he is Advisor to the Provost for Digital Initiatives, and where he directs the MA Program in Digital Humanities and the MS Program in Data Analysis and Visualization. With Lauren F. Klein, he co-edits the Debates in the Digital Humanities series at the University of Minnesota Press, and has recently co-edited Digital Pedagogy in the Humanities and Debates in the Digital Humanities 2019. His collaborative digital humanities projects, including Manifold Scholarship, the CUNY Academic Commons, and The Commons In A Box have been supported by grants from a the National Endowment for the Humanities, the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, and other funding institutions. He is Past President of the Association for Computers and the Humanities, the US-based scholarly society for the digital humanities, and the Association for Digital Humanities Organizations, the international association for DH organizations.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Where are we right now in the wider field of publishing?</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	I think we’re at a bifurcated moment, where conventional print publishing retains the value it’s always had, even as we see a range of experimentation in digital spaces. That experimentation involves a number of different models. In its simplest form, when someone publishes a printed book, they might create a website to share ancillary materials related to the project. It’s not a replica of the published text, but rather an online accompaniment to it containing images, background materials, etc. Another model thing that we’re seeing – which Manifold tries to do – is what we can call hybrid publishing. In a hybrid model, the book may be published in print, but it also appears online in an interactive, web-based version. With this digital copy, users can virtually annotate and highlight a text that mirrors a standardized printed form of it, and that also contains ancillary media and research materials. Finally, we also have completely online publishing, where no print edition exists. These experiments might be text-based, or they might eschew linearity altogether, as we see with platforms such as Scalar, which really try to disrupt the linearity of the printed text in favor of a web-based, multimodal interactive experience. Here, an attempt to rethink the form of the book is made in hopes to have people read the text in different ways, interact with it in different ways, and to really incorporate a wide range of media. Personally, I still tether a lot of my thinking regarding the field today to the printed book because, even amidst experimentation, it still remains strong. To me, that’s not a problem – it’s actually a good thing.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Tell me about Manifold.</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	Manifold was conceived in 2012 after I published ‘Debates in the Digital Humanities’ with University of Minnesota Press. When I was talking to Doug Armato, the director of the press about the book before I signed the contract, I made the case that we needed an open access version of the book since many of the key texts in digital humanities – the Blackwell’s Companion to Digital Humanities and the Alt-Academy text on MediaCommons, among other DH publications, were readily accessible online. To my surprise, the press agreed and let me develop a virtual addition of the book. My university funded a developer and a designer to work with me. Together, we collaboratively created an interactive version of the book which allowed people to highlight and to comment.  But this created a site for a single, interactive book. In about 2014, the Mellon Foundation came to the American Association of University Presses and requested proposals for grants to help think through the future of the digital scholarly monograph. In other words, Mellon was asking what will a monograph look like when digitized. Working with my editors at Minnesota and partners at CUNY (my institution), we proposed Manifold, which would basically take the ‘Debates’ site as a kind of prototype and turn it into a platform that anyone could use. In our original proposal, we had two major concepts: one was this idea of hybrid publishing, of trying to make it easier for presses to distribute edited files digitally after the publication of a material book; the other major concept was iterative publishing, an attempt to make visible the process of a text’s cultivation over time. Regarding this second concept, we followed the thinking of Kathleen Fitzpatrick, and hoped to help scholars share early versions of texts for review and commenting as a way to share materials before the book was actually published. This is what we thought of as a kind of iterative publishing process. Since scholars were already publishing blogs and sharing early versions of texts among peers, we thought this would be a helpful resource. We hoped Manifold could help illustrate a text in the process of its own creation over time. Minnesota has published several of these projects in the past, including Whitney Trettien’s ‘Cut/Copy/Paste’, which features the published copies of texts previously made available online. The ‘Lab Book’ is another book that is coming out from Minnesota that took this approach. Ryan Cordell’s ‘Going the Rounds’ book as well. In these projects, Minnesota has been digitally publishing parts of the book along the way. We were interested in how this method of publishing effects the cultivation of a book over time and what impact social media had in its development.  These are the ideas that really led to the creation of Manifold as a platform. </p><p>	What has been interesting to me about Manifold is that we started out with a very tight use case – we were thinking about (a) Monographs and (b) University Presses. These emphases spoke to our audiences and indicated the content we were publishing. What we’ve seen over time, however, is an interest in using it for other things as well. This inspired us to expanded into two new areas. One of them being the publication of open educational resources, which is a huge movement in digital pedagogy to (a) reduce textbook cost for students and (b) to publish more work openly. To do this, we’ve been working with a lot of publishers to create open educational resources through Manifold. This is one of the ways we’ve been using it at CUNY. The other site of expansion is journal publishing. We haven’t released this yet but we’re going to be releasing some major future journals that we are publishing very soon. [note: the ability to publish journals on Manifold has since been released on a version of Manifold released after this conversation was recorded]</p><p>	I could say more about Manifold – how it works, etc. – but these are the sort of concepts behind it I would say.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Tell me more about the social aspect of the platform.</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	When we were thinking about how Manifold should be constructed, we decided that the overall container would be called a project. Each project has kind of a home page. Here, you can include text – the book itself or other supplementary content. You can also add social media links like hashtags. This creates a surface on the site of the text itself, facilitating discourse similar to what is seen on social media. This is one of the ways we are thinking of this being a kind of social digital environment, The other side is the annotation and commenting. There’s a very rich and well-designed annotation feature that allows readers to comment or take notes on the text. It can even help establish reading groups (both private and public) around certain texts. A way to think of the space is through layers: there’s a base layer of the text and then there’s a media layer that can include additional resources like videos, interactive visualisations, and even interactive elements like Gephi forced diagrams or interactive data charts. The last layer is the social layer, which includes reader interactions with the text. Here, we’ve seen people use reading groups around a text just to read together and classes use reading groups to interpret and unpack a text together. The larger idea is just that when you’re reading the text you’re also reading it in concert with or alongside other readers if you want to.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What’s the underlying support model for Manifold, how is it funded and sustained?</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	Manifold is extremely lucky to have received three grants from the Mellon Foundation to support its mission. Each of these grants has been around $700,000 to $850,000. Thus far, they have been our main source of support. On our last grant, the foundation requested that we formulate a business plan for Manifold (it’s a non-profit project). This has forced us at Manifold to work on a model where we hope to sustain Manifold and keep it as a open source. We want to ensure that it will always be able to be downloaded and installed for free. Fortunately, we have a number of prominent self-hosted installations at places like the University of Virginia Press, Cornell, University of Pennsylvania, Liverpool University Press, University of Virginia Press, Concordia University, Arte Publico Press, Verso, and Reanimate Publishing currently. We offer hosting services wherein we install the software, we keep it updated, we troubleshoot – that sort of thing. On top of that, we’re offering packages of training. These can include editorial or production work to help with Manifold or teaching and OER related work. We also offer a la carte technical support if needed. Basically, we’re hoping to develop a business model around Manifold to ensure its sustainability long-term. We’re also continuing to seek grants. We’ve received a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities to develop features for using Manifold in the classroom and for OER projects. I would say also that the core funding institutions – the University of Minnesota Press and CUNY – have been contributing staff support and monetary support as well. We’re hoping to build it upon this foundation not to make profit but so that we’re just able to sustain the project and be active in its development. We don’t just want to maintain, we want to keep building.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	We can’t build everything into our platforms build; during the design and development process, were there particular key decisions that come to mind now? Any matters of infrastructure, interface or anything like that? </p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	That’s such a great question. We had to make an early decision on licencing, whether to go with a GPL licence or the MIT open-source licence which would allow for more commercial uses of the software. We went with a more restrictive GPL licence, which was just in line with our core beliefs about open-source software. Keeping to these core beliefs has, in some ways, inhibited us – but I think in good ways probably. We were actually contacted by a venture capitalist company who was wondering about monetarizing Manifold. But because we had the GPL licence, there wasn’t much they were going to be able to do with it. So, that was one big decision, Another big decision early on regards what we called ‘where to place the fork’ – we wanted to allow presses to publish both in print and digital without much pain, we wanted them to be able to easily get text that they had produced for print and then ingest it into Manifold. This decision was really fateful in both good and bad ways. What we decided is that most presses wind up with an EPUB as their files that feature the output from their editors and tracks the production processes. That’s what they send on to the printers. This is where we put the fork, wanting presses to be able to send the EPUB file on one hand to the printer and on the other hand to our team to be ingested into Manifold. That assumption turned out to be – if not a complete mistake – overly ambitious. We didn’t consider how variegated the landscape of publishers is and that there are many university presses that don’t produce EPUBS. Instead, many utilize InDesign and are just literally creating everything for a print layout. These files wouldn’t work for Manifold, since it prioritizes responsive web-based interaction. We wanted it to work as well on a phone as it works on a laptop – all the content has to be flowable, meaning the layout can’t be static. This is all to say, we underestimated the diversity of the publishing ecosystem and how many publishers are really just like producing PDFs or InDesign files and don’t actually understand how to create EPUBS. Another fateful decision we made was to say that Manifold is a publishing system and not an authoring system – this differentiates it from something like WordPress, where you are writing the text in the Backend or at the very least you’re editing it or changing there. Manifold differs in that you’re writing it elsewhere and then you ingest it into Manifold. One of the things we did was allow users to upload EPUB files. Then, we enabled the upload of everything from Google docs to Markdown, to Microsoft Word docs, to HTML…there’s now a much greater set of kinds of documents that one can ingest into Manifold. It does currently still retain that ingestion only and not authoring side of things although that is something we’re thinking about changing if we can find the funding for that [note: a forthcoming version of Manifold, set to be released in Summer 2023, will allow for backend authoring]. The other positive decision we made was for a kind of way of working. We decided early on that we wanted to be very public with our process, so we started a blog. We did everything openly, we tried to let the larger scholarly ecosystem know about what we were doing through social media, etc. – that has been good in bringing momentum and attention to Manifold. We really focused heavily on design and that has been a key differentiator for us. Manifold is really elegantly and beautifully designed -- it looks good. I think people like using platforms that are well designed and are thoughtful – that’s been another key decision. </p><p>	Lately, Manifold has started to be used for different purposes. It’s really difficult when you build a platform and then the potential use cases for it start expanding. We want to meet the interests of users and have received feedback regarding the potential inclusion of other features. However, we have to be careful not to build a Swiss Army Knife – we don’t want to build a platform that doesn’t do any of the things well that it’s supposed to. The question becomes how can we do something like enable journal publishing on Manifold without introducing all this new complexity and making the platform and its basic use cases more difficult to achieve. I’d say that’s one of the ongoing tensions that we’ve been navigating.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And speaking of uses and potential future uses, have you ever considered something like support for dominant critical editing practices like the TEI, that kind of thing?</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	We’ve had some interest in that, I think one of the major issues we face has to do with the web text – the sort of the static layout versus the reflowable content issue. A lot of the textual editors who have contacted us about Manifold had very specific things they wanted to do like displaying text side by side or really thinking about the way the text looks on the page. These concerns are, however, easier to consider in static publishing – or static layouts, I should say. Layouts don’t change as much in print publishing as they do with HTML. first reflowable content model web browser model, This has been one of the difficulties. We’re definitely still interested in it and we’ve seen people build out kind of critical editions of texts where the model is less a textual edition – or an edition that a textual scholar would put together – but is more like a critical edition, where it’s a version of the text with lots of additional resources to help amplify and understand it is featured. This kind of edition is very easy to create with Manifold. [note: work on TEI publication is likely to be forthcoming in Manifold].</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned born digital, how platforms like Scalar are trying to rethink the form of the book – do you think that, both in terms of Manifold and the wider field, do you think that we’re doing enough of that, enough rethinking of the book?</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	When first hearing about Scalar, I thought that was undeniable, that it was great – yes, let’s rethink the linearity of the book, let’s have people explore! In practice, however, I find those types of text experiences somewhat difficult to navigate myself – or to read. There’s a way in which Manifold accepts the linearity of the book as a tried-and-true form. I think that there is more to think about in regard to Manifold. Specifically, I want to see us improve the way the interface incorporates something like data exploration –people are doing a sort of integration iframes now – and stuff like that into the text so that one can do things like explore data in a Manifold text. I’ve only recently in my classes started to assign videos on a regular basis and I think that’s something to continue to think through. I still see that as a challenge that DH generally needs to address. I continue to feel like the book is just a tried-and-true model. And while experimentation can be fun and generative and don’t think it should end, I also don’t think we should abandon the book.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	How do you decide what to publish?</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	It’s different for each publisher. This is actually one of the other interesting architectural things about Manifold. Two examples may help illustrate this. We have university presses like the University of Minnesota Press using Manifold. They have a specific process for deciding what to publish on Manifold but they in the backend they don’t allow, to my knowledge, they don’t allow authors into the backend. Because of this, it’s really the press that is controlling what is published since they have a list and they want to be in control of what is published. In CUNY – a twenty five college system in New York City serving about 500,000 students across all 5 boroughs – we have focused our installation on open educational resources and on teaching and learning. To do this, we give our faculty and students accounts and just basically train them a little bit and get them going to publish. We exercise almost no control over what is published there, so it’s the complete opposite of the system instituted at the University of Minnesota Press. Our Manifold installation is really community software, it’s a way of empowering faculty and students. We’re seeing a lot of collaborative student publications, where students publishing end-of-the-semester papers are working together instead of writing individual publications. In other words, they are collaborating on a project that they’re writing together. In this case, we aren’t really doing much quality control because our main focus is on empowering the community. And while this is a very different model than the presses, the larger point is that anyone who is running a Manifold installation can decide for themselves what model they want to use.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	If you were to say there is one major motivation behind the development of Manifold, what would that be?</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	I mean it is to think through the future of the book, I would say.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What does it do well and, more importantly, what could it do better?</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	What it does well is delivery. The word that came to mind is amplify – it amplifies the book content. However, there may be more to the story because it’s book content with additional resources in a kind of interactive, well designed, easily annotated interface. It encourages people to come together around a text and that can be used across platforms. What it does well is publishing open access books in a pretty easy way that looks like a professional publication. That’s why our students are so excited to use it – they’re writing a term paper and suddenly they’re publishing something and they’re like wow this looks really nice. What could it do better? I think there is a desire for people to, at the very least, edit documents after they have ingested them. I think that’s something that we want to work on. I wish we had the funding to be able to offer an instance where anyone could just create a text in Manifold and just publish it there. Unfortunately, we just don’t have the funding for that. Basically, a lot of the buy-in that we have had is from the institutional level for our hosting services. I still think there’s a significant need on the part of individual scholars who don’t want to pay an annual fee for Manifold and don’t have the technical knowhow to install it themselves. They do, however, want to publish one book or one thing. I wish we had a better way to address that kind of use case of the individual scholar without funding and without technical knowhow.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What’s next for Manifold?</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	I think in about a month we’re going to be releasing a new version of Manifold that’s going to allow for Journal publishing, improved OER features, and improved accessibility features. That’s sort of the immediate things we’re working. On in part grant funded work to do all that. I think what’s next is just a continued work in the directions we’ve been going. We’ve got, I don’t know, something like forty-seven installations roughly that we know of that are going – everything from Brown University to Concordia to Indiana University Press. There’s a lot of publishers that are using Manifold to publish content. One of the things that we’ve just started recently is a sort of set of quarterly community meetings among Manifold Publishers. I think part of what we want to do is listen to that community as they use Manifold. This will help us figure out where to go next. We are also talking to other platforms like Humanities Commons and Fulcrum trying to figure out ways to interact with other platforms. For example, we want to find out ways to have, say, people who have a Humanities Commons account to authenticate against a Manifold installation. Or a way to create a book or something like that and find a way to share information between both platforms. That’s something else we’re thinking about.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	If we can go back to the wider field again, what to you, ideally, magic want scenario, does the future of digital publishing look like?</p></sp><sp who="#MG"><speaker>MG</speaker><p>	I mean it’s so hard to separate where we are right now from this current moment. It’s so hard to tell the future of anything considering the pandemic and its effects. But while things seem so crazy right now, I do think that Manifold is on the right path, where things are going – where the text itself becomes like a node or a space for interaction. The idea is that it’s not just that a scholar is publishing something but the scholar is opening a space for readers to connect with the text in various ways. Whether it’s a connecting space exploring data or it’s connecting with and reacting to other readers, Manifold represents a version of social community scholarship where the author is coming into contact with readers in a new way and the presence of readers can be felt. Aside from that, we’ve seen a huge increase in open access publishing and that’s been really, really satisfying and wonderful. I’m really hoping that we’re going to see more publishers move away from only sharing a kind of static PDF version of a book and to embracing these more interactive, multimodal, social spaces of publishing.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>