<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Justin Tonra and Lindsay Reid</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on March 29th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_JT_LR.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p><list><item>JUSTIN TONRA is Lecturer in English in the School of English &amp; Creative Arts at the University of Galway. His principal research interests lie at the intersections of literature and technology, and comprise work in the fields of digital humanities, book history, textual studies and bibliography, scholarly editing, and poetry of the Romantic period. He is the author of a monograph, <title>Write My Name: Authorship in the Poetry of Thomas Moore</title> (Routledge, 2020), and peer-reviewed articles on topics including network analysis, crowdsourcing, stylometry, text-encoding, and digital bibliography.</item><item> LINDSAY REID is Lecturer in English in the School of English &amp; Creative Arts at the University of Galway. Her specialism is early modern English literature, and much of her work centres on classical reception. She is the author of two monographs,<title>Ovidian Bibliofictions and the Tudor Book</title> (Ashgate, 2014) and <title>Shakespeare’s Ovid and the Spectre of the Medieval</title> (D.S. Brewer, 2018).</item></list></p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do the terms digital editing and digital publishing mean to you? </p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	Sure, in some ways, maybe it’s better for me to begin because this is not my field. I come at this as an early modernist, and I’m someone who has a background in book history, as well. I have become increasingly interested in textual editing, but the digital aspect of the current pedagogical project that we’re working on is something that’s actually as new to me as it is to the students and they, at this point, actually know more about it than I do. I mean, from my own perspective in terms of what does digital editing mean, my sense is that it could mean a whole variety of different things. My very non-expert take on this is that the exciting thing about digital editing is that it allows you to potentially interact in different ways with texts that you might not be able to if you’re dealing with a printed edition. So these sort of obvious things like hyper linking can happen or different ways of potentially viewing texts or viewing annotations or comparing texts. And so, with digital scholarly editing it’s about kind of additionality in terms of the sort of functionalities of the editions that are possible. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	So, from my perspective, I have a bit more training in the theories and practice of scholarly editing and digital scholarly editing and that started out during my PhD which was in the first decade of this century, but still when something like Jerome McGann’s rationale of hypertext seemed like a new thing at that point. So, I did learn quite a lot of, well, I guess analogue theory of textual editing and I have a good background in that but from the very beginning of my acquaintance with either textual editing or digital scholarly editing, I was taught the idea that the digital offered just the opportunities that Lindsay was talking about to extend scholarly editing beyond the boundaries of the book and to enable different approaches to editing, editing texts, incorporating multimedia, visualising variation in different ways, just a whole range of new affordances that the page either didn’t offer or offered in more reduced or economical way. So, from the very beginning I was introduced to the idea that ‘digital was better’, right, it was a new way of scholarly editing. So, at that time, the downsides of it in terms of obsolescence and bit rot and preservation were not as apparent to me in the glorifying rhetoric of the digital but those have become I think much more prominent and I’ve gained a much more balanced sense of what the digital can do well and badly in the years since.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s really interesting, this idea of the glorified rhetoric of the digital, what the digital does well and what it does poorly. Could you speak to some of these?</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	But yeah, just upkeep of digital scholarly editions can be difficult and maintenance and moving from one technology, an outdated technology to a new one. I think in McGann’s article he writes about SGML rather than TEI XML so he’s not even talking about P3 or P4 version of the TEI guidelines, he is talking about that kind of markup and he’s even written about it as well in The New Republic of Letters; he talks about, semi tongue in cheek, if he was editing the Rossetti Archive again he would do it on paper or he would do it and then just print it out, which I don’t think we need to take entirely seriously but it does emphasise that there is a lot more care and upkeep needed for a digital scholarly edition than a printed edition, which, when it’s finished, sits on the shelf. Now obviously, a digital scholarly edition can be updated and superseded as new information appears which the print edition can’t manage as well, but yeah, there’s a trade-off in terms of manageability there. I’ll just say very quickly that we had first-hand experience of this in Galway last September when the university was cyber attacked and the university systems went down for several months and one edition I’ve worked on, Ossian Online, disappeared: disappeared for six months and was inaccessible. Now, the files were safe and were eventually salvaged and it’s back online now, but that’s  just one example of the precariousness of digital technologies and their longevity. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Lindsay, you spoke to additionality of functionality; Justin, you said that digital promises to extend the scholarly everything beyond the boundaries of the book. From both of your perspectives, do you think that the digital has done this? Do you think the digital has got us beyond the cultural logic of print? </p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	Yeah, I mean, I’m trying to think about this very much from my personal perspective as an early modern researcher, and, truly, I have to admit that most of the time the editions that I work with when I’m dealing with scholarly editions are actually print. When I think about other digital resources that aren’t necessarily scholarly editions, I’m using tonnes of other digital resources. Things like EEBO are absolutely central to my research activity—but, in truth, when it comes to the question of how many scholarly digital editions do I use, not many. That said, I think it partly has to do with a lack of availability of things that would be directly in my field that would be potentially relevant. It’s not that I have an aversion to them, it’s that I have a hard time thinking of what is an example of a really good digital scholarly edition that would be relevant. I can think of a couple of examples like The Pulter Project, which is Hester Pulter’s poetry. This is a fairly new one which looks like it would be great for teaching, and I can imagine using it for teaching sometimes. I can think of a few examples of things that are kind of on my radar that I might potentially use mostly for teaching more than for my own research activity, though. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	It’s a good question. I think in some respects it obviously has. I mean, if you think in very basic terms about something like the Shelley-Godwin Archive which is bringing together portions of the Frankenstein Manuscript that are located in different libraries around the world in colour. Previously that was available in Charles Robinson’s Frankenstein Notebooks Edition, which is a black and white facsimile with a facing transcription. Now, even with the same kind of basic layout of facsimile and transcription, the digital edition is so much richer and more useful in that regard. Now it has obvious additional elements and really, really neat things, where you can isolate Mary Shelley’s contributions from Percy Shelley’s contributions and the visibility of the facsimiles is so much better, you can zoom in, stuff like that. So even in those very basic terms, yeah, the digital certainly has made improvements that, I guess, are possible in certain instances in print but difficult and expensive to achieve. I mean, the Robinson Notebooks Edition is really expensive as it is and it’s in black and white. But I think other examples of extensions beyond the book are the Devonshire Manuscript Edition that’s done in Wikibooks by the INKE group in Canada, I thought that was a really interesting approach to social editing that would be difficult to imagine in print. But I guess if you’re thinking about a spectrum of editions from ones that are doing complex things to the visualisation of texts, that’s one side, the other side is the digital allowing the production of an edition that you can’t imagine a university press publishing, so smaller authors, authors of less fame and renown that you just can’t really see warranting a print scholarly edition. So, something like Romantic Circles, which has been around for a very long time, is really good at doing this. Producing interesting editions of minor literature and making those available. So, I use digital editions quite a lot in my teaching like Lindsay said but if I’m citing a line of poetry from a romantic poet I will by instinct go to an established printed edition rather than the digital edition, but that’s for doing something basic like a citation, right, so I think if I were doing something more connected to the added value of a digital edition, I would have no hesitation in citing digital editions and I have done so as well.</p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	But it probably speaks actually to the ease of citing a printed edition versus a digital edition as well. Given the choice, it’s just going to be easier.</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	Some do incorporate ‘how to cite’ features and will generate automated citations for you but I guess it’s just traditional. I’m also thinking that ‘what if this goes offline’, my citation is going to look a little, well, it’s not going to be very helpful down the road if this disappears whereas the printed edition will be there on the library shelf.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned Ossian Online; Justin, I wonder if you could speak to any of the key decisions you took in terms of how that project is structured? What were the major lessons you learned from that project? How would you do it differently were you to do it again? </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	Well, this is a good case in point as well because it’s unfinished and the main principle that we began the project with has not actually been realised in the edition, and that was due to a lack of money, so we got a small Irish Research Council New Foundations grant to start up work on it and that created the basic text TEI encoded versions of a range of different Ossian editions published in Macpherson’s lifetime and under his authority so that was the first step. The second step that we wanted to do was create a social annotation platform which would allow people to highlight portions of the text and add commentary. And we did that in a very basic form with Hypothesis, that annotation system, and we trialled that on a couple of occasions but the money ran out, we applied for more money and we didn’t get it so there is a version of that social annotation system hiding behind the existing website but we didn’t have the time or money to implement it and I think it is something that would need dedicated time to monitor and to implement successfully. So yeah, this is another problem, some people might assume that a digital edition is something that, because it’s free to publish or freely accessible in some senses, that it’s low maintenance or inexpensive but that’s really not the case. If you want to produce something to the same kind of quality as a printed edition it can take you years, as any printed scholarly edition will do. So yeah, Ossian Online has proven very valuable and we know there is a user community out there and that’s great, but that’s because there is one scholarly edition of Macpherson’s Ossian, it’s out of print, it’s not a very complex scholarly edition; and just having these texts out there freely available has been a boon for lots of 18th Century scholars and Celtic Studies people, so we’re very pleased about that but yeah, we’re kind of sad as well that we weren’t able to finish it to our satisfaction. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Thank you. So if we move to your classroom project, my understanding is that you received funding from the National Forum for Enhancement of Teaching and Learning and Higher Education to design and deliver a postgraduate module on the theory and practice of digital scholarly editing. Could you tell me a bit about this module and some of the things that you covered? </p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	Sure. Can I just clarify our funding source? This is actually a really tiny part of a much bigger project that’s I guess done now but was happening in the School of English and Creative Arts. It was actually a project that was kind of spearheaded by someone in Drama and was really about developing innovative modules where students would perhaps interact in more hands on ways. There was some sort of theme that had to do with creativity and canon, as well. So, this was the one module that the Discipline of English developed in relation to the project, but just to clarify it was actually part of a much larger scope thing. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Ah, what’s the name of that project?</p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	Curriculum and Canon I think it was called, yeah.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And the PI?</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	The PI was Patrick Lonergan.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Thank you…</p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	So in terms of how we interacted with the project, we got some funding from the project to put on a webinar which happened when we were still in the development phase for the module. One of the things that kind of inspired this more generally is, in early modern studies right now I have heard of lots of colleagues who are developing versions of this sort of thing, some of them not digital. So, some colleagues have developed textual editing modules that include classes that might collaboratively edit a play together at either undergraduate or postgraduate level. I think very recently there are a few more experiments that are happening that have a digital component to them, as well. This is, I mean, there’s not tonnes of it, but this is something that is happening in a few places. So we actually realised as we’d been talking about developing something like this, we realised that at the Renaissance Society of America, I think it was two years ago, there were a couple of linked panels where people were presenting about digital scholarly editing projects that they were doing in the classroom. So we invited some of those people to come and give a webinar as we were still in the developmental phase for our own project. This was quite helpful, and we actually have a recording of the webinar online as well. It was really helpful to hear from people in terms of what they had tried, and some people had tried launching whole modules around this. For other people, it was a very small unit within a module that might be a survey of early modern literature or drama or something like that. I don’t know if you want to say any more about that. <stage>[Turns to Justin]</stage></p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	Yeah, they varied in scale and ambition as well so some had tried to edit a full play, whereas others would focus on a particular act or a scene and maybe tie that into how you interpret early modern dramas. So, there are lots of different pedagogical approaches and ideas about what textual editing can do whether as a discipline in its own right or as an aid to interpretation and in some degrees and it was a really interesting session to put together and see a sense of why people were doing this and from there we got some ideas about how to begin our own version of it. </p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	I have to say our version is quite ambitious compared to what some other people have done with this. And I think it’s ambitious in a couple of ways. We have all of the students in the module working collaboratively on producing a single edition and so in some ways that’s easier, but in some ways it’s hard for students to actually collaborate and really kind of meaningfully collaborate on a single project like that. And also, just in terms of the length of what we were trying to do, it was quite ambitious in that sense as well. So, I guess another dimension to this is that we have here at the University of Galway an MA in Literature and Publishing which Justin is the Course Director of and so because of that MA we have a lot of students who are potentially interested in this sort of offering. So it was a really appealing offering for the students and we’ve got, I think, 13 is it who took the module? One MA student in English, but the rest are all from that MA in Literature and Publishing so they’re quite interested, particularly in the kind of digital scholarly editing side of things—a little bit less, I would say, in the Renaissance Drama side of things, which I was kind of anticipating. What that also means is that none of them were Renaissance Drama specialists at the beginning of the module. I think a few of them have read a few Shakespeare plays, maybe, and that’s the extent of their familiarity with the period. So, it’s been, a pretty steep learning curve for the students in terms of both the context of the text they are working with, but then also the other skills that they’ve been learning along the way. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	I think they’ve been enjoying it: we have our final class of the semester tomorrow and they’ve been doing a lot of independent work in the last few weeks and they seem to be getting along reasonably well with it, and I think the major constraints are really on time rather than understanding or desire or enthusiasm, so the fact that they are Literature and Publishing students is helpful insofar as they also produce, that cohort produce a literary journal during the year so there they have experience of organising themselves into working groups and getting on with independent tasks so I think that is quite helpful. I mean, the scale of the thing is quite ambitious in that we hope to have an edition of a play by the end of the semester, but…</p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	I think we will, though.</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	I think we will. We’ll definitely have something. <stage>[Laughs]</stage></p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Tell me about the edition. What are they editing? What platforms are they using?</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	So, they’re editing a play from 1638 by James Shirley who is an English playwright with connections to Ireland. He managed the theatre in Dublin or ran the theatre…?</p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	He was recruited by the theatre manager of the first permanent theatre in Dublin to come over and be the resident playwright for what was actually kind of the first significant theatre outside of London where plays were produced in English. So it’s a historically significant theatre that he was working in, and the play is a historically significant play in that it’s the first play of James Shirley’s staged in Dublin. We tried to pick something that had some sort of Irish connection to it, and our intention in future years would be to continue with early modern plays that have a Dublin connection in that same sort of way. Also the play is basically unedited at this point: the most recent edition is from 1833, so this was another kind of benefit for us, although the plays of James Shirley are being edited right now in a big editing project. So a few years down the road there will be a new print edition, but, for the moment, it’s got that advantage of only being available in the 19th Century edition. The students can look at that alongside the early modern edition, but there’s no good scholarly edition that’s out there. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	So, they are doing a predominantly diplomatic edition of the 1638 volume in which it was first published. They’re including some critical elements; they’re including a lot of annotation and introduction to the play; they’ve encoded to play in TEI. We’re going to use the EVT platform to publish it, with some customisation. But they’re learning to use GitHub as well for version control and it’s initially going to be published by GitHub Pages. Eventually we’ll will move them all over to a university site and hopefully build up a collection of early modern plays that the various classes have published. It’ll be a facing page edition with facsimile images of the 1638 volume that have been digitised by the British Library, I believe, and are available for Open Access, and there will be facing transcription as well. There is a version of transcription of the play in EEBO TCP, but with errors, so they’re going to produce a more accurate text of that. So, they’re learning a lot of different technologies in, I guess, a relatively superficial way, they have an introduction to scholarly editing theory as well but not hugely in-depth. We’re trying to fit a hell of a lot in, you know, early modern contexts of drama and theatre as well, we’re trying to fit a hell of a lot in the space of 12 weeks and for that reason we designed a lot of open educational resources and video lectures for them to watch outside of class time because we simply couldn’t fit it all in in 12 two-hour meetings. So, part of what we’re trying to figure out after it’s done is what we need to prioritise, what they’ve learned too much of, not enough of, that kind of stuff. So it being the first run, it’s very much a learning experience for us as well. </p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	Yeah, and I think it’s already clear to us that we need to do things in a slightly different order the next time around in terms of introducing some of the things at slightly different stages than we did this time. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That sort of pre-empts my next question, I was going to ask about the pedagogical learnings for you both. If someone came to you and said, look, we’re thinking of teaching a similar module on digital editing wherein students collaborate on a relatively ambitious project, what would be the key things you would advise them on?</p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	I have to say that one of my big takeaways from this is that I think very idealistically at the beginning we wanted to make everything the decision of the students in terms of all of the choices about the edition. So okay, like, let’s have them decide what kind of edition they want to make, let’s have them decide what they want it to look like, let’s have them decide which sections they’ll put in the introduction or which kinds of information to engage with. And I think that one thing that I have taken away from this is that you should have some of these parameters drawn up beforehand. Part of this has to do with how compressed a 12 week semester actually is, and they’re spending time making each of these decisions along the way. And I would say, by and large, they’ve made the decisions we expected them to make… with some gentle guidance… and I think in some cases they haven’t had strong opinions and so we've wound up sort of guiding them. But had we started the semester and said you’re going to make a facing page edition and it’s going to use these images from the BL, I think if we had just set some of these parameters for them instead of offering some of these things up as suggestions or choices, this would have streamlined the process a bit more. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	We did teach them a session about the different varieties of critical editions and we talked about critical apparatus and variorum editions and these are possibilities and it very quickly dawned on both of us that, if they decide to do a Variorum edition we’ll be here until Christmas of 2023 just because of the complexity involved. This exists in, I guess, three or four printed witnesses over the course of a couple of centuries, which isn’t a massive number, but still it would be a mammoth task, so I fully agree that we can still tell them these are the different possibilities of edition, we think the most suitable thing here is the diplomatic edition, I don’t think we would receive a lot of push back from students on that. </p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	No.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	From that student perspective, were there any particular frustrations that you picked up on? What did you feel worked well with your cohort and what didn’t work so well?</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	So I can say that the GitHub has been a bit of a struggle for them, with many not having used it before. That’s the technology that has proved most challenging and we realise now that we need to introduce that earlier in the semester and give them exercises to familiarise themselves with it. Surprisingly, they love text encoding. They absolutely love it. They all wanted to, couldn’t wait to do more TEI encoding of the play. EVT has been a little bit challenging, not as much as GitHub but I think an issue is, I guess, non-technological issue, is communication between the different working groups. So, we do separate them into four different work packages and it’s crucial that they interact with one another and talk to one another about their decisions and they’re doing that to a certain degree but I think we have agreed that we need to do a little bit more oversight on that; we did think about project management software like Trello or something like that but I think that would be overkill. I think we just need to have a little bit more supervision and oversight of their meetings, that kind of thing. I don’t know if you thought there were things that worked well or didn’t. </p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	One of the things that I’ve been thinking about is that next year it’s going to be incredibly helpful that we’ll have this year’s edition to show next year’s group. So I think, looking forward to next year, being able to show them at the start what it is that they are trying to make will conceptually make it much more real to them when we’re going through the steps. I think one of the challenges that we may have faced is that we tried to be very selective about what we were exposing them to, but as we were going through the first few weeks of the semester and talking about various issues, sometimes they didn’t necessarily see how all of these pieces were going to fit in and be things that they needed to come back to. And so, I think that maybe conceptually seeing that from the start and seeing how everything comes together might help them to realise that all of these components are really important and you need to pay attention from the start and see how these things are building. I think that sense of what they’re building towards will just help.</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	Yeah. Yeah it’s the larger version of a problem that people start out with TEI encoding have is that they’re working on encoding but they can’t see what that encoding will turn out like in a digital edition so I guess having EVT is quite useful or TEI publisher has something similar where they can drop their files in and very quickly see how it’s going to turn out but yeah I agree that having an exemplar edition for next year’s cohort will be very helpful.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What were the four work packages?</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	So, two of them are more interpretive, so there’s one on introductory materials and paratexts for the edition prefaces, historical background things like that kind of stuff. The second one is annotation of the text the third one is TEI Encoding and the fourth is visualisation and publication. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It seems that you really thought about publishing practices, and obviously a lot of the students came from the MA in Publishing, so I assume had an interest in that side of the project. Do you think there is sufficient connection between the theories and practices of digital scholarly editing and those of digital publishing? </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	Good question. I was really surprised in one of the early classes when one of the students asked a question about monetising it which I hadn’t really thought about in any great detail because, and I realise that there are some editions that have paywalls and stuff but I would by instinct be for Open Access and I really haven’t thought about it in any great depth. Now I know someone who has studied this is Aodhán Kelly, who is based in Belgium working with the Beckett Project. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yes, I know the Beckett Project and I spoke with Aodhán a couple weeks back, as it happens.</p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	Okay, right and maybe he and Elli Bleeker as well had done some research on financing and paying for additional editions. But no, I mean I don’t have a very sophisticated answer for this. I think there are probably opportunities there for people with greater expertise and publishing to help out academic side of digital scholarly editing, but it’s not a topic I’ve thought a huge amount about.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	How did you get on with TEI Publisher as a platform? </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	So we decided to use EVT this time around, primarily because I’ve used it before and I was quite familiar with it but I would consider looking into TEI Publisher and others for future runs. I don’t know if you have a preferred version? </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I do think there is a disconnect between how one edits and publishes using TEI. One of the issues we’ve had with students is that once they’ve done all of their editing, the answer to the question, ‘how do we now make this publicly available in an intuitive and sustainable way?’, well that’s not so clear. And of course we haven’t actually seen many, if any, commercial, even university, publishers adopt TEI-encoded texts as a standard part of their production workflow, but that is, as you say, a much bigger topic. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	Yeah. Well, there’s a degree to which, when you’re doing this work and you’ve committed to using TEI, that you are working within a particular conceptual frame and a particular view of what texts are and how there are marked. I’ve had occasional moments where I’m trying to visualise something or dropping something into one of these publishing platforms and there is a disconnect and I find myself either working against TEI, encoding something in an invalid way just to get it to work or making a compromise on the editorial side just for something to happen. It does happen occasionally, but I can’t say it’s a huge problem in my experience but I do recognise that there are types of editing where encoding features that you would want to encode would not be possible within TEI. So yeah, I think that’s certainly valid point. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Moving beyond this classroom project, if you were to reflect on digital scholarly editing and publishing in the wider sense, what are we missing? What does this field need? </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	I can begin by saying, and it’s an old complaint as well, greater recognition for the intellectual labour that is involved in scholarly editing and recognition of that work for promotion and tenure and things like that. I mean it’s an old complaint. I don't think it's much closer to being resolved, but it's one of the reasons why people are sometimes reluctant to do this kind of work or are not as enthusiastic about it because they don’t see the rewards. In terms of academic profile, the intellectual rewards are of a different kind. I don’t know if you concur with that? <stage>[To Lindsay]</stage></p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	I think that seems fair to say, but it also makes me think back a little bit to earlier in this conversation when we were talking about how both of us might be more inclined to use digital editions for teaching rather than to cite in our own research. I mean, I wonder if that too is part of this puzzle where, you know, if people want to get cited, they’re well aware that they are more likely to get cited in a kind of traditional book format. And so, it may have to do with visibility within research as well. And, you know, it’s much harder to track where things are contributing to teaching, especially if they’re open educational resources. It’s much harder to kind of chart that impact that the work might be having. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, in a magic wand scenario, given unlimited resources and technologies both real and imagined, what would the future digital edition look like to both of you? </p></sp><sp who="#LR"><speaker>LR</speaker><p>	I have to say—and, again, this is kind of going back to something from earlier in the conversation—it would be really easy to cite and would be consistent with other digital editions in terms of how you cite it. Like, for me, the citation thing is huge: the specificity with which you can cite things, but also just the variation across different editions in terms of how you would go about citing it. I know that’s kind of a silly answer, but citeability is huge for me. </p></sp><sp who="#JT"><speaker>JT</speaker><p>	I don’t have any kind of specific wish list that I think will resolve or improve digital scholarly editing as a whole because my approach to editing is that each editorial task is different from the next one and each work that you edit presents a different set of requirements and needs that are determined by the work itself on the available materials and your editorial approach and design is guided by those things that are available to you. So, I can’t think of any one single thing that would make the task easier except more time and money to be able to think those questions through in a more comprehensive way. I mean, yeah, those are the two things that would enable me to edit to my satisfaction in a more consistent way. Time to think. Money to buy that time. I mean, it sounds like a like a bit of a mercenary answer but if there’s one thing it’s, yeah, it’s just time and that applies to so much of our research but I think it applies in particular to these kinds of tasks. </p></sp></body></text></TEI>
