<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Kevin Ohe</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan 		 on April 5th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_KO.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>KEVIN OHE is Academic Publishing Director, Bloomsbury Digital Resources.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Could you speak a bit about some of Bloomsbury’s digital publishing initiatives?</p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	Oh sure. So, Bloomsbury is a multifaceted publisher. We publish trade books and materials for the general marketplace, but that’s just a part of what Bloomsbury does. A big part of Bloomsbury is called Bloomsbury Academic, and we publish basically for the higher ed market, globally, and we publish a wide range of materials. Most of what we publish resides in the Humanities and Social Sciences, and we publish with different aims in mind. Some of our aims are to publish monographs and research materials to further intellectual thought in various disciplines, but we also publish pedagogical materials. We do quite a bit of textbook publishing, so, materials intended for use in the classroom. Within our pedagogical publishing, we publish materials spanning from the beginning stage, the fundamentals, to the upper levels of undergraduate courses. We’re also branching out. We just purchased a company called ABC-Clio that specializes in the US high school curriculum. Quite a bit of our textbook publishing is aimed at students in the United States, including community colleges, and sometimes FE in the UK and other places. And finally, a small bit of our publishing starts at an academic point and then tries to reach out a bit broader beyond the Academy into a general readership. That’s a small part of our publishing, but it’s an important part, and it indicates our commitment to make compelling, accessible, scholarly perspectives widely available. Broadly, we publish materials that will help people engage with the Humanities in some way. That’s the high-level overview let’s get more specific. </p><p>Much of our research publishing takes the form of monographs or collected works on topics in the Humanities. We are particularly strong in areas like Literary Studies, Philosophy, History, Religious Studies, Theology, Biblical Studies. Recently we have brought in new elements to the mix, like International Relations particularly with the acquisition of Zed. We are a dedicated publishers in the Visual Arts and Visual Culture; we’re particularly strong in Fashion. I actually spend a lot of my time working on fashion. That’s one of my areas of oversight--fashion textbooks. Anyway, the monographs are books that are primarily aimed at higher-level research for graduate students and professors, instructors, academics. Most of these books are purchased by college libraries in either print or ebook format. </p><p>We publish textbooks, including Fairchild Books in US, which is a traditional, Higher Ed textbook operation and we publish core textbooks covering the entire four years of the US curriculum in fashion and interior design. All of the books that we publish in Fairchild Books contain a full complement of instructor resources, ancillaries for students, the pedagogical package in print and/or digital formats. </p><p>We publish a lot of books but when we say we publish books, it’s not just print of course, it’s ebooks and print books. Our ebooks tend to be standard issue ebooks to the degree that there is a standard. We publish ebooks for our own platform. We also publish or sell through aggregated ebook distributors. Our books need to fit into file formats so they can be sold by various vendors and rendered by various delivery systems. </p><p>And in terms of digital publishing, I also oversee the editorial team at Bloomsbury Digital Resources. That is a group that we started as a boutique within Bloomsbury Academic about 5-6 years ago with the idea that we wanted to create a suite of library-based digital products across our own publishing output and beyond. So what we do in Bloomsbury Digital Resources is create and distribute products for institutions, including ebooks either individually or topic-based collections, a few archival products—like the Churchill Archives and the Fashion Photography Archive, and aggregated collections of scholarly materials that come together to form digital research environments. Drama Online, for instance, is one of our flagships of this product type. It’s actually a combination of many related products. Drama Online is kind of a product line, if you will, and within it we publish full-text plays, literary scholarship on drama, along with providing streaming video of recorded productions. The content can be purchased in various product configurations, and it’s served from a single platform, so depending on what a library has access to, users can find multiple formats of related content within a single search. And we replicate that model by subject area. in addition to Drama Online, we publish a product called Bloomsbury Fashion Central which contains five individual fashion products. We publish Bloomsbury Music and Sound which covers popular music and sound studies. And so it goes down the line. We produce digital products in areas of our publishing strength (drama, fashion, music, history, religion, philosophy, design, architecture, and related visual arts); we tend to publish multiple products in the same area, and within those products we often feature different content types. As I mentioned with drama, there’s full-text plays, there’s streaming, there’s also scholarship. There’s also some reference work in there, so we publish a variety of content types supporting a variety of desired outcomes. Some are pushing in the field forward in terms of thought, some are secondary in nature, or pedagogical in nature, and so we pull these various pieces together, and we index them to a subject-appropriate taxonomy. We try to help people make connections, and we hope to lead them to create their own avenues of inquiry. Students can follow a journey, whatever kind of learning journey they want to undertake. We’ve put together an environment where a student can do any number of things in a subject area. We try to make that process as easy as possible through search and through indexing and through browse trees and various ancillary and supporting materials for students, for instructors, for librarians. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You’ve outlined some of the key opportunities presented by the digital. I wonder if you could if you might also speak to some of the challenges?</p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	Sure. There’s a lot of challenges. Bloomsbury is a publisher, and we’re situated in a transitional period. Within the scholarly world there is a mix of digital and traditional scholarship, which is book- and article-based, in the Humanities. Bloomsbury has a long history and a deep backlist in book publishing. We’ve probably got 20,000-30,000 books in our backlist, so that is where we come from. One of the challenges is that the world is not simply a book-based world anymore. So how do we deal with that, because books are our bread and butter. The print book itself (I like to say this, everybody likes to say it and people like to hear it) is a fantastic technology and print fits the Humanities subject matter and use cases very well. Place that within a society that’s becoming overwhelmingly digital, and we’re working toward a new balance where you’ve got forward-thinking people thinking about what scholarship could be or should be, how it should optimally render on the digital side. That vanguard has to balance with the mainstream which is, the book. It’s is a wonderful technology for longform scholarship and thinking. In light of this, the question for us becomes how do we put materials together for libraries because those are our buyers, and for our users, like scholars, who are both authors and researchers, and the students themselves. What we want to do is provide a service to help people in the humanities think about how to come to terms with what it means to be a human. And we attempting to do that during a transitional period. We’re trying to move from books to something that’s broader, that’s different. But in that sense, Bloomsbury, and most publishers, are not vanguard warriors. We’re not doing some of those really interesting exploratory kinds of scholarly undertakings because that’s not exactly what our mission is. Our mission is a little bit different than that—it’s to publish well and to make our materials available to a global market. It’s a perpetual challenge to publish books well.  We want to support the communities around our subject areas. We want to publish efficiently and tie into the existing publishing and distribution infrastructures that enable us to effectively serve our communities and fulfil our role in the scholarly community along with libraries and scholars and publishers and others that fill out that community. We try to publish well so that we can succeed, and by succeeding we can help others teach and learn.  </p><p>But then you get down to the everyday challenges of publishing, and we’ve got lots of people who work really hard on getting manuscripts in good shape, and obtaining proper file formats, and indexing, and testing, and 500 other things. In other words, the process of publishing is a challenge. It’s also a challenge to sell academic materials. Always a challenge. They need to be marketed, and distribution has to be coordinated. With digital, there’s a different buying process in that you go through libraries directly. Libraries often trial products, so you’ve got a long selling period to manage. And the sale itself creates on ongoing relationship between us and our customers. You’ve got to provide your customers with supporting materials. Technical support, ongoing information, usage drivers, and more. It’s an ongoing sale an ongoing relationship with customer, so that’s a challenge because you also want to keep producing new products. With digital products, the publisher makes a commitment to the community that it’s going to be there for community to support that product and that area of study.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Are libraries your main buyers as far as academic projects are concerned?</p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	Yes, for the bulk of our products. Again, digital textbooks are little different. In that case, our buyer tends to be the student or the university, depending on where you are in the world and how the university sees things. Our end user is the student, plus the instructor, who uses the books to shape the course and uses the ancillary to help support teaching and assessment. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you see any trends with libraries? Are libraries shifting more towards digital forms of publication, are they staying with print books? What do you feel the library of the future is going to look like?</p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	Oh gosh, the library of the future. I don’t know. I hardly know the library of yesterday. [laughs] So what we saw, interestingly, in first year of the pandemic, was a massive switchover to buying digital. It made sense because with no students on campus, you didn’t have people wandering around the stacks to look at a print book. As a result sales of our print books took a bit of a hit. Digital, especially ebooks raced forward. Now last year we saw a bit of a comeback in relation to print books. When students and librarians and professors came back to campus for the school year our print book sales came back a little bit. Not to where it was, but there was a limited bounce back. It seems like in the past few years that the balance has definitely shifted, from print books being core. During the pandemic, I think a lot of people were forced to engage with books differently. It’s hard to break habits, but when you do, then the world looks a little different. I think we’ve see that digital scholarship in the form of institutional purchases of ebooks is now firmly established. It will likely grow, at least a little bit, at the expense of print, and people will realise how they like to incorporate ebooks into their practice. If they’re lucky enough and they’ve got options to use print and digital, they probably will, at least for a while. I’ve seen lots and lots of studies that show even students who’ve been raised in the digital world, when given a choice, would often opt for print. Ideally, they’d like access to both print and e formats. In many cases, that’s not an economically feasible option.</p><p>So, I think it’s safe to say that the library of the future will be more digital. And digital products of multiple types and models will continue to make their way into the general workflow of a librarian. Collection development depends upon a digitized workflow. There are thousands of libraries, and they need efficient ways to acquire content to help their communities. Journals, print books, ebooks, aggregated digital collections, streaming, open scholarship are all flowing into library collections. Collection development is as much a mindset as a process, and as the mindset changes, I think there will be knock-on effects that we don’t quite know yet. In essence, libraries fund a great deal of humanities scholarship.  Whether it’s via open access or whether it’s through purchasing from university presses or commercial publishers like Bloomsbury, you could argue that the scholarly enterprise in humanities is largely funded by libraries, and the library as a de facto source for funding has proven to be very effective for many years. It’s still going to be effective, I suspect, for many years to come. It’s hard to know exactly how Open Access humanities monographs, for instance, may change the mix. Other entries may appear on the scene and change the mix as well.  But my hunch is that libraries will be central to funding humanities scholarship. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And what about Open Access? </p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	We think about it a lot. I have a colleague, Ros Pyne, who was brought in a year or two ago for Bloomsbury as our Open Access point person, and her role is to help shape our strategy in relation to Open Access and explore how we can participate effectively in open publishing. At the end of the day what we want as a commercial publisher and what people who are pursuing open publishing want is to disseminate information widely. So that’s a commonality, and perhaps we can say, “okay, even though it seems like we might be on opposite sides of the fence, we share this common interest. Is there some way for all the parties to purse their goals successfully?” Because in essence, nothing in this world is free. You can say things are open, but you can't say anything is free. You need investment. That’s investment in money, certainly, but also in time. If we look at the world differently, how can we do it in such a way that a commercial entity can help the process and get to that endpoint which is sharing scholarship? Open Access is not my area, so I can say that we’re very active in working with any number of scholars, we’re thinking about funding, we’re thinking about scholarship types, we’re thinking about models. However, that’s probably as much as I can say that’s accurate.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think there’s a disconnect between the needs of some kinds of digital scholarship and the ways in which publishers are implementing models for digital publishing? </p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	Disconnect? Maybe. I hope not. I guess it goes back to what I was thinking about earlier—the vanguard  and mainstream There is a lot of scholarly digital experimentation. On the technical side, it’s often highly customized to the project at hand. It’s like these are the ‘advance scouts,’ to use a military metaphor, trying to figure out how things can work and potentially how they can be scaled. I mean, what publishers do in a lot of ways is tie into an existing pathway. We talk about workflow structures, buying processes, infrastructure. We tie into those to enable efficiency so that we can publish, you know, works on, say, Samuel Beckett, which are not going to sell 100,000 copies or even a thousand copies, so we need to tie into the structures to enable efficiency through volume. The trick is to keep your mainstream in balance with your vanguard. So you’ve got your scouts out there saying, “hey, you can do this,” “you can do that.”  Eventually what tends to happen is you, as a publisher, figure out that you can do something, which is hard, very hard work, and it takes time. It’s what those pioneer scholars have been out there doing for 20 years or more and have continued to push that envelope.  Then the second part is to say. “now that we can do it, can we scale it?”  If so, what are the trade-offs? When you when you get to scaling, there’s almost always a conflict between bespoke and efficient systems. That’s the balance that businesses and companies and cultures are always trying to achieve. What’s the benefit for a single piece of scholarship which could do something that’s absolutely magnificent, versus something that is maybe dialled back a little bit but could actually service a wider audience?  So where do you fit? Mainstream publishers tend to play that latter part as opposed to the former part, and it’s the academicians that are out there often doing those one-off’s that are absolutely brilliant. They’re pointing the way to what might be coming down the road. When I mentioned transitional, in some ways, that’s what I was thinking about. Then where do we sit in that chain? You know, publishers like us tend not to hang out in the vanguard, we tend to sit in the main part of the chain. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that some of the practices that scholars employ could be more publisher friendly? I’m thinking here about things like workflow and production. For example, a lot of scholars in the digital humanities would use of TEI-compliant XML, which isn’t something that has been broadly adopted within the commercial publishing industry. Could scholarship and publishing be better integrated so practitioners are creating texts and things that publishers actually want? </p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	Well, some of our XML is TEI based. Much of it is DocBook-based. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Oh, I wasn’t aware of that.</p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	Yes, but remember, there are multiple mark-up styles, and even within that, there are different house styles for forming XML documents. Just because a file is in XML does not guarantee that it’s interoperable in all XML-based systems. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So if you had a scholar who crafted a digital scholarly edition using TEI, there would be no issue in taking those files and publishing them as print or otherwise?</p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	There are always issues.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Relatively few issues?</p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	Well, real issues. Think about spoken language. You could have two people who speak English but, due to geographical or cultural differences, they can’t really understand what each other is saying. There’s a similar challenge with XML. So,  if you delivered a TEI-based corpus we would send file to our data analysts, and they would review  that corpus to see how those tags are rendered and then figure out what would need to be done, and then potentially write a transformational script to get it into a compliant forms that we use in order to store the data and then have that data sent out to the front end that's going to render it. Or we might have to send the file to a conversion vendor to convert the file so that it’s compliant with our specs. So, it can be done, but there's certainly work, it’s real work. XML is just one piece of the puzzle. There’s still publishing involved to handle the transformation from manuscript to something that will behave the way you want it to out for a customer, for a viewer, for a learner, for audiences. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s really interesting, thank you! Time for the blue sky part: as a publisher, what, ideally, does the future book look like to you?</p></sp><sp who="#KO"><speaker>KO</speaker><p>	Oh. Well. I don’t know. It’s funny. I work in digital; I don’t spend a ton of time thinking about blue sky because there’s so much work to be done between now and … the future. Well, it’s kind of like if you’re hiking up a mountain: you’ll want to keep the peak in mind every now and again, but you need to be looking down your feet frequently to make sure you’re making progress. I think at the end of the day, what the “book” looks like will depend a lot on what people need to accomplish. So if it’s long-form scholarship in the traditional sense, then that “book” is probably going to look just like a book; it may well be print. If you’re going to read 100 pages, print book technology works beautifully. So, in some ways, the book of the future may well be the book of yesterday and today. Speaking of today, we already have digital to integrate text, audio, sounds, sharing, assessment, student grades, and school records. Continued improvements in all of those areas will likely occur. Tying ever more effectively into workflows. I think as more and more people will use the technologies, people will think about how these fit into their own personal workflows, and then that will come back to publishers, and publishers will be thinking about how to make their content more work more effectively. Even though it tends to be less visible, sometimes it's improvements in infrastructure that prove to be more momentous than front-end technology features. So, as you can see, when the thinking gets more diffused and less precise and that’s when it’s better for me to look down at my feet and figure out what I have to do on my ‘To Do List’ every day. [laughs]</p></sp></body></text></TEI>