<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Ben Brumfield</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan, UCC		 on January 11th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_BB.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>BEN BRUMFIELD works with cultural heritage organizations through Brumfield Labs. Prior to Brumfield Labs, he spent eleven years leading software development teams building fundraising and constituent engagement solutions for non-profit clients at Convio, Inc. Ben is the creator of the FromThePage crowdsourcing platform. He has presented on the intersection of technology, crowd-sourcing, and digital editions at the American Historical Association, Society of Southwestern Archivists, Digital Humanities, the American Library Association and SXSW. Ben brings deep technical expertise in the area of digital documentary editions. He has a BA in Computer Science and Linguistics from Rice University.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing, in the broadest sense, mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Sure. So scholarly editing, leaving aside digital scholarly editing, is…I think Dan O’Donnell’s definition of “a critical representation of a primary source text” is the definition I tend to use. Elena Pierazzo has a great definition of digital editions, but I don’t have it memorised right now. That is my take on any kind of scholarly edition: it’s re-presenting or re-presentation of some text or sometimes other cultural heritage artifact.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do digital editions do well and what might they do better?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Digital editions do a great job of embedding different kinds of scholarship and making the scholarly editing process more transparent to users of the editions in ways that print editions don’t. You’ve got a book, it kind of flattens a lot of the details of scholarship, a lot of the decisions into (at best) editorial notes but oftentimes not even that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I like that idea of flattening.</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	What their problems are–I gave a talk on this at the AHA about three years ago–-is preservability. The book is on a shelf in a library, and we understand how to preserve paper books, we’ve been doing it for thousands of years. Digital media is really hard to preserve and that is the biggest problem with it in my opinion. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	The talk at the AHA, is there a record of that?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Yeah, if you take a look at ‘https://content.fromthepage.com’ and search for AHA, all of my slides and my transcript of my talk are there. I think the title of it was something like “Preserving Scholarly Editions” or some such thing.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	We’ll get to FromThePage, but beyond your own work, what are some of the tools and platforms that come to mind when you think of digital editions and what are some of the primary affordances and limitations of these platforms?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	I see there as being three different suites of tools for working with digital scholarly editions. There is the publication side of the work (I tend to think in data flow and I’m actually going to work downstream and then work my way upstream, alright) so there is the presentation side of things and we see some interesting work coming out of say TEI Publisher, out of definitely EVT is lots of fun and some, at least in the States, we see a lot of editions in that. We work with a couple of different projects that are publishing on Omeka-S with a number of specialised plugins for presenting scholarly editions in usable formats. Then there’s the other two sides of things, the other, I guess, two halves of the scholarly editing process which would be tools to support research and tools to support transcription and digitisation of the primary sources themselves. So, moving upstream, to research tools, one of those might be Textual Communities that lets people collate different versions of different witnesses to the same text (that’s at Peter Robinson’s lab in the University of Saskatchewan) so doing that kind of collation and stemmatology particularly in the literary world. </p><p>	In the United States there are two separate professional organisations for literary editors versus historical editors and they don’t talk much, so that is one of the things we see in the literary world and in the historical world; tools to enhance research. A lot of times 19th Century documentary editors in the United States, especially right now, are trying to essentially come up with biographies or at least prosopographies of people who are mentioned within documents that were not historically written a about lot, so, people who are women or slaves or indigenous people who don’t have Founding Fathers levels of documentation. Well, you know, doing research on these people can be pretty hard, so tools to harness that…and sometimes those are just interfaces to census records or Ancestry searches or genealogy searches…but ways to make that process easier and more scalable on the research side is what I see historians needing. </p><p>	And then of course you get to the primary source transcription and digitisation, and there you have the whole range of TEI based tools, you’ve got crowdsourced based tools like FromThePage, and those are all about making that transcription process more accurate, more scalable and–frankly, you know, cheaper is debatable. Switching to large scale parallelisation means there’s less transcription for staff to do but there’s suddenly this whole new suite of things they have to do, managing volunteers or reviewing contributions that oftentimes they’re not used to. So, it’s debatable whether this is actually less expensive than outsourcing transcription or something. But one thing that is really interesting is that these projects have the ability to involve the public and publicise themselves much, much earlier in the editing process than a print publication would. With a print publication, you only have staff working on the project; it’s practically secret until the volumes can show up in a bookstore or a library. Whereas now we have some really interesting opportunities to publicise projects and expose people to whatever is being researched as part of the early research project themselves.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Transcription is obviously a key feature of FromThePage. Do you think that crowdsourcing transcription is one of the most important aspects of current digital editions?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	It’s a good question. There are really three models of transcription that I can think of right now: one is very traditional, staff-based offline transcription, one is collaborative or crowd-based transcription (which could be crowdsourced or it could be a smaller research group or something like that), and then the third option is machine transcription…you see that with projects like Transkribus and for printed 20th Century material–obviously OCR can help people out there. There is a big question that we run into which is… let’s assume that you have 99% accuracy coming out of machine transcriptions: is that good enough for a scholarly edition? And what do you gain in saved cost versus what you lose in the by-products of human transcription, in the sense of new research questions being formed by the person transcribing, new knowledge being imparted to the person transcribing.? I mean, the process of transcription produces a digital artifact but it also produces a tremendous amount of…I hesitate to even call it by-product…of knowledge in the person doing the transcription’s head about the material itself, about the people mentioned.  It opens new questions and, that’s a balancing act because if you get machines to do all this for free and they do it perfectly, you still lose that by-product of the knowledge about the text. I do… I am concerned about a world in which we produce… in which things are so automated and that we produce things that we call digital scholarly editions that are made up of texts that no one has ever read which is something–perhaps it’s a reductio ad absurdum–but that’s a fully automated future, right, that’s a possibility! You know, you’ve got this volume of correspondence that was digitised automatically, it was transcribed by a computer, that the only people to read it would be search engines…this can happen. It’s not a terrible world, right, it’s not awful!</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Obviously you have a lot of expertise in building platforms for digital editions through your involvement with FromThePage. I wonder if you could speak firstly to your vision for that platform from a design and functionality perspective? Why did you build FromThePage the way that you did?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	I built FromThePage originally because I needed an editing platform for an amateur edition that I was working on which was a set of family diaries–my great, great, grandmother’s diaries–and at the time I started working on this, I was really influenced by Wikipedia so I’d gotten involved in Wikipedia in around 2001/2002 but also by Pepys’s Diary online which was one of these early retro-blogs in which someone was posting an entry from Pepys’s diary I guess 343 years later to the day and the comment section on each one of those entries was amazing because you had people who were arguing, they were looking at letterpress editions to see what perhaps had been redacted from the public domain edition which had been posted, they were getting caught up in the drama of Pepy’s love affairs or what was going on politically and they would go off and find contemporary diaries from other people or news events about what was going on.That community that was formed around the primary sources I thought was just incredible so the idea of being able to build a wiki-like platform that allowed people to transcribe texts and to discuss them was that was the origin of FromThePage. And that’s when I really started…I did some early proof of concepts but I really got serious about it in 2005 and really focused then on this amateur edition I was working on.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What you’re describing there goes beyond transcription as many people understand it. It seems to me that you’re describing a social edition.</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Yes, yes and I very quickly saw examples of this social edition happening both in terms of the collaboration and enhancing the documents. We found that we had mis-transcribed some words in an earlier print edition of this particular diary: there were words that we transcribed as “drugs” which were actually the word “drugget” (which is a type of fabric that was used in tobacco agriculture a hundred years ago), by people coming by and commenting. We also found the social and the public power of transcription at the same time because one of the early volunteers working on this was the diarist’s grandson’s widow and she used this project to connect with the memory of her husband and to connect with the family members. She would call her mother-in-law and they would talk through everything that she’d read that day, everything that she’d transcribed that day and in part that enhanced the text and enhanced the edition because she had more information about the people who were mentioned or the technologies and the terminology so we got a more accurate text at the other end. But that was not entirely her goal, right, this was an incredibly meaningful leisure experience for a homebound person with a degenerative disease, and that doesn’t count for nothing! Providing meaningful remote opportunities to retirees and caregivers and other people who are homebound, that’s really important.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It seems that meaningful engagement and the idea of impact are central to your thinking. There is this sort of fetishisation of so-called impact now in academia, so do you think it surprising that we’re not seeing more social editions? Or am I wrong in that we are seeing loads of social editions? But my sense is that digital editions still they tend not to be social.</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Yeah, it’s hard to tell because the people who talk to me are the ones who are already doing things or interested in social editions so there’s this bubble effect, so I’m not a good judge of that at all. What I see is tremendous interest in the library world and these are people who are not traditionally making scholarly editions and who are dipping their feet into this for the first time. In the archives world, again, these are people who are not used to doing public outreach. And then, in the United States at least, I see a lot of interest from historians, largely because the incentives of the American academy in History as I understand it, you know, you have publishing scholarly monographs at the top of the prestige heap and well below that are two things that are fairly neglected. One of those is publishing documentary editions and the other one is public history, and so we see interest in these social editions coming from scholars who also have their heart in [public] history. We see documentary editors who are running scholarly editions who at some point in their career have [worked] at a historic site firing a flintlock in front of a bunch of tourists, right, and I have not seen the same thing from the Literary Studies school. I have seen it with the Medievalists; the Medievalists are very interested in that but they also have a pretty good history of public interest and social engagement but yeah so at least in the let’s say, definitely US and possibly North American context, there’s a real disciplinary variation in the uptick that I’m seeing.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Why do you think there has been limited uptake of the social edition as a model? Is it a tension between the idea of the social and the edition versus the scholar as the authoritative figure? Or is it something else? Is it just disciplinary cultures?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Well, not being an academic I’m very hesitant to say, but I do think a lot of it comes down to different disciplinary cultures and the difference between an English Department and a History Department. At least in the United States there’s quite a bit of difference. But there’s also a much more fundamental difference, which is that the kinds of things that a historian versus a literary scholar wants to do with an edition may be very different. In history there is very little emphasis–in fact sometimes this may be counterproductive–to going back to an Urtext. If a literary scholar is looking at three versions, three witnesses to the same text… there’s this history of wanting to know what the original was…authorial intent, stuff like that. If a historian sees that an order was typed out from a General to a Commander saying, “move your troops North” and it was sent via telegraph and you have a copy of the text that was corrupted that says, “move your troops East”, the historian wants to know what that Commander actually got that explains why they moved things in the wrong direction. It may be useful to know that the General or whoever originally wrote “North” and their intent was North but it’s even more valuable to know that the document that was received said “East”. And what that means is that there has been a great emphasis in the literary world on developing a much deeper tool set to do that kind of analysis, to do text criticism that the people in the historical world have not had. So, if you present a historian with the question, “could a member of the public do this kind of task?” they’re thinking, well deciphering handwriting…maybe? researching who’s mentioned, typing things accurately whereas a literary historian will think that but also will be thinking about these other steps of collation and creating a critical apparatus and those may be foremost in their mind and so they’re less likely to say, well yes, sure, anybody off the street could do this. So, it’s not just culture, is what I’m saying.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you feel, from your experience, that crowd-sourced transcription works in practice?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Yeah, I do. Yeah, I absolutely do. I mean, there are challenges, it’s really important for the editors to establish a consistent culture. The problem isn’t that volunteers or ”yahoos” are going to come in and they’re going to do the wrong thing or they’re not going to care about quality, the problem is–and the quality problems that we run into–is when there’s not enough examples and there’s not enough editorial… it’s not necessarily oversight it’s almost modelling and forming examples of what to do. And so, what you have is, one volunteer will come in and they will do a really good job and they will be very strict about marking up superscripts or textual things using XML, another volunteer will come in and they previously worked on a non-XML project in another project altogether and they’re not going to use XML at all they’re going to use some altogether different set of conventions like letterpressprint conventions for marking superscript or gaps or things like that. And both volunteers will be trying to do a very good job and they will be doing a good job of representing the text but unless there is somebody watching and guiding the project and providing that oversight and saying ‘oh, no, no that’s how we do it here, this is an XML-based project, let me teach you how to use XML tags to mark gaps in the text or unclear things’ and get all the volunteers on the same page, then you end up with this, I hate to say eclectic edition but this very eclectic, erratic, inconsistent encoding all by people who are trying to do good work, but they are probably doing good work but they are doing it independently and you end up with something that’s a mess. That is the real danger in these big collaborative crowdsourced projects and that’s why I said that this requires a very different kind of oversight from running a traditional, in-house, staff-based project. You got maybe three or four people and you’re bringing them all on board carefully saying ‘ok here’s how we do this’ and they run into a problem and they ask you a question ‘so do it this way’ and that gets everybody on the same page. It’s a lot more difficult to do that in a crowdsourcing project, especially if you think it’s just going to run itself.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	How long has FromThePage been in development now? Ten, twenty years?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Yeah, it’s… I mean, I started working on it in ’05 and I guess it was first in Alpha or Beta in ’07, so, sixteen years, I guess.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And what unique insights have developed from working on this project over those sixteen years?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	You know, I don’t know which of my insights are unique and which ones aren’t. I mean, this is fundamentally a cross-disciplinary project and so, I’ve learned a tremendous amount about volunteer management and volunteer motivation from people in other parts of the crowdsourcing world and I try to bring that to textual scholars. I’ve learned a lot about textual scholarship from editors and I try to bring that to librarians and museum professionals. But I don’t think there’s anything especially unique… there are concerns that I have, and there’s things that I’m interested in researching right now that relate to repurposing scholarly editions for different needs, seeing how libraries and scholarly editors can collaborate together to produce things that are useful to both of them (which is actually a pretty hard problem), these issues of preservation is a hard problem. And then I’ve been doing a lot of research this last year on the lessons that traditional textual criticism have for modern online transcription, so looking at the kinds of errors that modern volunteers make and seeing how they map onto the errors that we theorise medieval or ancient scribes made, with the goal of attempting to come up with ways to minimise or catch those in modern systems… we’ll see.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You obviously have this inherently interdisciplinary background and you’ve worked with inherently interdisciplinary groups; has anything ever surprised you about the kinds of different objectives and perspectives of those various groups you’ve worked with?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Yeah, I’ve gotten a lot more humble in what I have to say about textual encoding because there is a huge difference between the kind of encoding you need to do for enabling full text search or corpus analysis and the kind of encoding you need to do for digital editions and the kind of encoding you need to do for preservation. I no longer am willing to stare at a project and say ‘oh, they’re doing a digital edition and they’re using print conventions for their emendations–that’s doing it wrong’. I no longer say that. It has been fascinating and humbling to see the kinds of things that people are doing with texts that I’m not going to say there’s one right way to do anything anymore.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And what about sustainability, then? Do you think this space has a sustainability issue?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	It absolutely does but we’ve been paying a lot of attention to the work that the minimal computing community has done–so folks like Alex Gil in Columbia but also a number of other projects that are looking at digital preservation–and so to that end we’ve been doing a lot of work on… we just developed (I’m not sure if we’ve announced it yet) a static site export from FromThePage so that the entire… so that all the work ideally can be exported as something that is human readable and machine readable at the same time, and in addition to that I actually think that ‘the book on the shelf’ is a pretty good digital preservation format, so also this last year we’ve added Word and PDF exports. I’d really like to beef those up and make them look a lot more like letterpress editions to be able to take our XML and convert it; you know, you’ve got a person who’s mentioned that someone has written a biography for, well, I’d really like to have that show up as a footnote and being able to produce print exports from digital systems that are as lossless as possible is a big goal of mine right now.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And does machine learning play a role in that? Say, adding a footnote of someone’s biography…?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Yeah, we already have the ability to have, to create biographies, you know, to… you essentially are able to identify any subject that’s mentioned within the text as it is transcribed in FromThePage, because my goal was essentially to be able to create a back of the book index from a letterpress edition when I started working on this sixteen years ago and using… that’s one of the reasons why Wikipedia was so exciting to me was because you had this ability to link from the text and one page to an entry about people who are mentioned within that so that’s been a core part of the tool for a long time but it’s only, it’s not used by libraries very much it’s mainly used by scholarly editions, so it’s probably only 10% of our projects use that at all, it’s not very well known.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Where do you think the field is going in terms of new forms of cultural material, things like social media data, born digital creativity and so on?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	It’s hard for me to say; it depends on which field, so there’s the crowdsourcing practitioners who, as yet, are doing very little with born digital material and then we have scholarly editors who might be doing work with born digital material but who, I don’t know, I only see people who are scanning paper so, again, I don’t have much insight into that world.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Magic wand scenario, what do you think the digital edition of the future should look like?</p></sp><sp who="#BB"><speaker>BB</speaker><p>	Ok, the digital edition of the future: what I really want to see is digital editions that are sustainable, interoperable and useable and the way to get there, in my opinion, is to use standards like IIIF and TEI to produce sites that both have a human readable interface–they are publication venues that have an interface that has all the fancy digital affordances–but that also expose their raw data, right, so if you’ve got something like EVT that gives you a standalone publication of a TEI file, well, I’d like to have that, I’d like to have a simple, stripped down, human-readable version of that same text and I’d also like to be able to get at the TEI XML document, like for scholarly reuse, all of these things I think together are that’s kind of my magic wand if I could change the field today, right, and I think people are talking about doing this a lot right now so I think we’re getting there.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>