<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Stephen Gregg</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on September 21st, 2021</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_SG.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>STEPHEN GREGG is a senior lecturer in English Literature at Bath Spa University and specialises in eighteenth-century literature and the digital remediation of old books.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly editing and scholarly edition mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Yeah ok, so, I guess these questions for me come from or rather I should think focus around bibliography and textual studies. So, when I think about scholarly editions, what occurs to me is that attention to the materiality of the print edition. You know, so, I’m an Eighteenth Centuryist so I like to see, if there’s a scholarly edition, I like to see an attention, a bibliographical attention to that kind of detail, to textual variance but also things about, any kind of things. Ideally, I’d like to see the kind of information in there about provenance, if there is any, about its I suppose what you might call descriptive bibliography, that is to say the kind of issues of the book copy or the source book copy. Of course, we get into all sorts of problems there between copy editing and the kind of ideal copy but nevertheless I think those are the kinds of factors that, I suppose my expectations, when I see the phrase scholarly edition. I guess what alongside comes with that and I’m thinking about some of the examples of scholarly editions might come extensive critical apparatus so that you’ve got things that trace the critical history of the text. And that might include either or, I suppose, an introductory essay…sorry…and or, I should say an introductory essay and extensive footnoting. So that’s really basic, I mean, but largely because my own research practice does not involve creating scholarly editions so you’re asking me about my expectations and that’s, that’s a pretty basic, I think, kind of, my immediate understanding.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Keeping that sense of what an edition is in mind, what do you feel current editorial practices do well and what might be done better?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Are we thinking more generally or are we thinking in particular print or digital?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Entirely up to you.</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	It’s a good question actually because some of those concerns that I’ve identified actually comes from my experience of, I suppose, remediated books and I guess my particular thing about the materiality, particularly of your copy texts, are, come from the lack of that materiality in digital remediations and I won’t call them editions because I’m talking quite broadly now. So, in terms of print scholarly editions… (oh my god a huge dragonfly has just burst into my room, laughs) print scholarly editions, I don’t often see an attention to, the same attention to materiality. There’s lots of attention to what we might call textual variations, which I guess is a form of materiality but it doesn’t do the same thing as, for example, the bibliographical attention to a particular book copy. Now editions because editions can’t do that, it seems to me, because editions try to present an ideal text broadly speaking and one version of that text, admittedly with various textual apparatus but what you’re seeing in any edition, it seems to me, is an ideal text. And those questions of an ideal copy in a sense disappear or kind of reappear in a different form when you look at digital remediated books because of course you’re not looking at ideal text, you’re looking at one specific copy, you know, it’s been remediated for one copy that’s sitting on a library shelf somewhere in the world. So, the questions that I was particularly focusing on about the materiality of the copy text, you know, the book itself is something that I suppose print can’t do, print scholarly editions can’t do by definition it seems to me because they want to produce an ideal text. And so (where am I going with this?) so this opens up a bigger question about digital editions and not just digital remediations so you know, so I’m moving on from the digital remediated book in general to think about digital editions here and there’s a lot of, as you might imagine, a huge variety of practices. So, I might be preaching to the converted here already or you know what I’m talking about already and I suppose I’m trying to think off the top of my head are examples of best practice. I do remember some time ago the MLA did a kind of white paper on best digital scholarly practice, which was very good. I think I’ve yet to see it put into practice particularly in terms of trying to give a sense of the materiality of its source copy. Importing from ESTC yeah, ok, that’s some example of I suppose of bare bones kind of data which you can surround a digital edition with but it seems to me that when people talk about digital editions they’re talking about TEI XML that seems to me to be what a lot of practitioners think about when they’re talking about digital editing as opposed to digitisations for example which I don’t think, I don’t think would fall under the rubric of digital editing though I might come back to that actually because I do want to talk about student’s perception which introduces a whole variety of complexities to their conception of what a digital edition might be. But anyway, let’s talk about scholarly digital editing so TEI XML and particularly those encodings which attempt to also encode something of the materiality of the source copies or even textual variance. I suppose off the top of my head and in my own period, Romantic Circles would probably offer a pretty good example of TEI XML encoding in terms of a scholarly approach. Yeah, that would certainly be the one, say for example, I would show my students if I was going to say ‘ok if you want to do some TEI XML this is a good example’. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	There are two things there that strike me as interesting… The first is this idea of a remediation versus an edition, and the other is the idea of the ideal text. Is that still a dominant notion in book history? Where is the discipline now in terms of the critical divide between the idea that every edition is a textual construction in itself and the idea of being loyal to some sense of an original?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	To be frank I think that’s going beyond my own research knowledge and I think that’s a great question for people who actually do scholarly editing, I don’t and therefore I think you probably know more than I do in that respect and I’m not sure how much I can actually offer on that. I think it’s telling though that, so for example, the CUP edition of Swift the print editions are amazing, conceptually however you’d have to ask Ian Gadd for example, who would be able to better talk to these theories of scholarly editing much better than I can. I thought it was telling that they did a digital edition that is to say they put some bare bones, what I would call bare bones text, digital versions of the scholarly editions online. Now, these are without any textual apparatus or without any kind of explanation of how they’ve come to be which struck me as, I think, probably as much as they could do with CUP in the sense that CUP just didn’t want to put it all online. It will be interesting to see how the Aphra Behn project is going on that line, I think, because I think they are doing some really exciting things there and you probably know who to talk to about them, I’m sure. But yeah, so the question is a bit beyond my, kind of, scope of knowledge.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So this idea of remediation versus edition then, that’s an interesting tension – what’s the difference between the two?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	I guess I’d see edition as a subset of remediations, I don’t think it’s versus so much as a subset so you can imagine a Venn diagram and it would have remediations and inside it would have various other ways of doing that all the way up from, I don’t know, Project Gutenberg through Eighteenth Century Collections Online to Romantic Circles, TEI editions, you know, so I think that’s what I meant by that. Because a digital edition is still a remediation.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And when you say textual apparatus, what do you mean?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	What was the context of that?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You were speaking about how some remediations, they lack textual apparatus. I’m wondering what that terms mean to you specifically in this context.</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Yeah, so, you know, well, a good example would be Project Gutenberg where you get texts where you’ve no idea where they’ve come from some texts will actually tell you that it’s based on a, you know, edition of Dickens from 1789 or whatever that’s a minimum form of textual apparatus of course, it’s an indication of its source. A more detailed textual apparatus would form the practice of print editions so you would get a full list of variants, you would get a kind of a perhaps even an essay which describes the choices made by the editors and what they have done, what are their source copies for producing the stable text you see in front of you.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And so, is it…</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	And I guess that would vary for a digital scholarly edition because you might also include in that details of what you wouldn’t have, you wouldn’t be choosing, well would you?, you could be choosing between various different editions. So, some indication of that process, that kind of, ahm yeah, and of course if you go into TEI I suppose the textual apparatus is built into, might be built into the header to explain how you’re using alternative readings or whatever.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	In our correspondence before this interview you described your current research trajectory as an examination of how we understand the history and nature of digital archives – I wonder if you could expand a bit on that, particularly how you think the idea of an edition and an archive differ and how they relate?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Yeah, that’s I mean this largely comes from my teaching and largely comes from, you, know working with students who are working with online collections I don’t even want to use the word archive it’s so loaded!</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	[Laughs]</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	And actually, to get them to tell the difference between the different kinds of digital remediations that are out there so it’s a very, it’s a question which I’m constantly grappling with and constantly trying to teach. A good example, and this is actually what I try and get my students to do actually, is to look at the Blake Archive which calls itself an archive but of course it’s also an edition, you know. They’ve made certain choices about how to present the material and what data to highlight and to include so the archive as a whole is a kind of edition even though and a kind of, and of course individual works become exploded across its various different copies. I’m sure you know the Blake Archive yourself, so you know, and one of the difficulties for students to grasp in that particular teaching moment if you like is to see how although we can talk about, I don’t know, for example ‘The Marriage from Heaven and Hell’ that’s an example, so in their minds that’s a book or a text but when they see it on the Blake Archive, they see it exploded and we have to explain that those are editorial decisions. They see it fragmented across different copies held across the world, various different kinds of bibliographical data are attached to that but those are editorial decisions it seems to me so in some senses the Blake Archive is both an archive and an edition. The word edition therefore doesn’t become applicable so much to individual works as a process for thinking about collecting works. I don’t know if that makes sense but that’s…</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Very interesting, thank you.</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	So yeah, it’s a huge, it’s a really loaded question isn’t it that, this kind of terminology which sometimes is used for convenience’s sake by people who come up with big digitisation projects and not necessarily has any critical meaning. And even I use it when I say I’m interested in Digital Archives, I mean, I include stuff like Paywall Collections, you know, it’s a shorthand term and also, you know yeah, it encompasses everything really it is just a shorthand for describing collections of digital books, I guess. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What might scholars of book history want from the digital, specifically in relation to how archival materials are present and/or interrogated, that isn’t currently possible, or at least, easily facilitated?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	I think I’d like a way of interrogating metadata; bibliographical metadata about the texts or the books in that collection. It seems to me that as someone interested in materiality of books when you’re thinking about digital editions the one thing that is difficult to get at is of course is what it looks like, how it feels, you know, all those kind of sensory, haptic kind of signals and, you know, you get the image, yeah, great, but most digitisations are flat, some are coloured, raking light would be great, it gives it that, again that sense of the materiality but beyond that it seems to me that there are limited things that you can do with images, digital images. So, I think metadata is the place to go, you know, how much information about a physical object can you put in and make it so we can interrogate the collection along those lines? And you know, this is, a lot of this is born out from using big paywall digitisations which were constructed in the 90’s which rely on the ESTC which, as I said before, is ok but to a limited extent. And, you know, there’s understandable reasons why the ESTC is an easy way of porting in that kind of metadata rather than recreating a whole bunch of new metadata.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is the look and feel of a book still something you consider important?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Yes. Yeah, I think so. So, you know, a good example, ESTC information will give you a format, so, tell you whether it’s Octavo or Quarto or whatever, it will give you a rough idea but it doesn’t tell us how big it is really. It doesn’t tell us what kind of paper it’s made out of. It doesn’t tell us where red ink might be used. Sometimes it does actually, sometimes it will give you an indication but it doesn’t tell you where in the book. You could look, I guess, but you can’t interrogate that as data. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And why are things like that important? The paper is a great example, why is it important to you as a scholar of book history what paper is used?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Yeah, well, quality of paper, the type of paper whether for example its elephant paper or the kind of, any indication about the kind of paper it will tell us something about the costs of production, expected audience and these kind of economic and social economic factors in the book’s original circulation and production. It tells us about the choices of print or the publisher might have made in relation to the book’s value or perceived marketability and saleability. It might even tell us, together with other data about… we can follow that paper quality alongside a particular printer or publisher, perhaps they had more stock of that particular kind of paper and it needed to be used up, you know. Why is this printed on sheet paper? So, a lot of this kind of detail, you know, can be quite revealing it is as you say blue sky thinking because sometimes, we don’t know and it’s all very difficult to tell but if I was blue sky thinking about bibliographical metadata that’s the kind of thing you could start cross referencing and imagine building up a kind of, some interesting searches.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I’m very interested in your experience working with students on some of these topics. I know that you have presented several times on DH tools and methods and pedagogy. In December 2014 you gave a paper at the University of Reading entitled ‘Digital editing: students, building, sharing’, in which you discussed the extent to which undergraduate students were able to use digital technologies to build and publish their own online editions of literary texts, and I know that you spoke sometime after that at Cardiff where you spoke to digital textualised pedagogy. I wonder if you might speak to these topics, specifically the role of digital editions in pedagogical settings, and indeed any successes or failures that you might have experienced as the convenor of any relevant courses?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Yeah, so I mean this came out of my experience, quite a few years ago now of learning how to edit using TEI and XML and for me I thought it was part of (and this is probably a little bit of a recurring theme here) to get students to recognise what it is they’re handling or doing when they read a book whether it’s a print edition or something online and it seemed to me that teaching students to take a text and remediate it in a digital format would teach them quite a lot about the kinds of decisions an editor makes to produce a stable text and that would be applicable whether it’s print or digital. It was basically, first of all, ok, transferring a material text into a digital format in a sense enables the student step back and realise that the book on the desk is artificial and by doing it in a digital format it would raise the stakes of artificiality and therefore is actually a great teaching moment. ‘Artificiality’; the edition is an artifact. After that I thought the next step would be to teach students some basic TEI XML particularly if they found a text which had more than one variant so again, they could do some coding that would actually demonstrate what a digital edition can do that a print can’t which is to hold two editions simultaneously so that they co-exist. It also had some practical professional knock-on skills; the students that did those editions, actually, most of them have gone on to work in some sort of digital media or digital publishing context so there was a kind of professional development aspect to those projects I initiated. It is interesting that no one has picked that project up for a couple of years and I’m not quite sure why. It might be actually that I’ve kind of put more, there is more digital stuff in the syllabus as a whole in English Literature at Bath Spa although no one’s doing any kind of what I would call critical or scholarly editing, not least in digital forms. So yeah, I’m not sure if that’s answered your question or left something unanswered.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I think there are two things there that are really valuable – one is this idea of getting a student to think about the book as an artifact and the other is that practical side of things, the idea that students use these skills to go on to work in relevant industries like publishing…</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	I’m quite sure that in the job interviews if they’ve…the projects were all open so they existed on the open web so they could actually, they were portable and they could take them and show their URLs to their, you know, build it in their CVs. The projects varied of course in quality and in depth and that’s natural but I think even just to be able to say to an employer that you’ve worked with a digital platform, you’ve learnt some basic kinds of skills of working with broadly speaking some form of encoding that you know what a digital file is, things like that, you know. These things, I think, probably helped. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And do you think did the students appreciate the difference between sharing and editing? This kind of gets back to the remediation versus editing piece?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Yeah. That’s an interesting question actually. One of the things I did emphasise in the projects I kind of initiated was that these were going to be open therefore they were going to be shared on the web and that really, I guess what I was trying to also get them to engage with was the open access debate that, you know, remediating books that might be noncanonical and editing them had a public knowledge value and I think most of them grasped that actually, I think they felt that was, there was nervousness around that. I think most of them, to varying degrees again, really took that on board and ‘yeah this is a chance for me to contribute, to actually show something to the public’, you know, it has a use beyond an assessment. I think that was again something I was really keen to talk about that, you know, what you’re doing here is not just for this assessment but it might have some public knowledge at least, at the very least, it has value for you beyond the degree.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that’s an important aspect of the digital edition, this idea of canonicity and how we can potentially disrupt it?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Well, yes and no, certainly one aspect of it, though one could argue that, as I have done earlier on of course, that even some digital editions of canonical texts aren’t doing as much as they could do. But I think given the current arguments about the whiteness of the archive which are still relevant, you know, I think there’s considerable arguments for certainly taking on board the kind of input from digital scholars of colour.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that there’s a danger that the digital is just reinforcing canon?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	There’s always that potential there and it’s certainly been well documented for the past ten years.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Ok…</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	And again, that might come down to the kind of framing of the digital edition. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do you mean by framing?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Well, I’m thinking about an article by Adeline Koh who talks about the Blake Archive and that she felt that the lack of contextualisation of Blake alongside issues of colonialism, empire was a missed opportunity. And I guess maybe not only framing but again back to what terms and what kinds of tagging you might want to put into your digital edition, what kinds of things are you searching for in a collection, what ways can you search it and again I think I’m thinking about Roopika Risam’s comment and I can’t remember where it is now, that good tagging or rather kind of a creative tagging might enable us to find different things about texts which will expand the, kind of, that whiteness of an archive.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is there anything specific you’d like to add that you feel I’ve missed?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	One of the things that actually struck me when I was thinking about this a few weeks ago was the overlap between editions and curation. Now curation is becoming a big word in certainly in how, I think, for example, public history courses are thinking about how you put materials together and there’s something to think about because we’re having to revise our, for want of just a, short term, a short phrase, calling it a digital humanities module, I haven’t got the title right yet but it’s going to involve students not just in English Literature so the question of scholarly editions are going to be differently inflected there. And so, thinking about what curation might mean from a student point of view and how that’s a form of editing, but it has a, it comes from a very different kind of disciplinary area and involves a kind of version of editing which is quite far away from scholarly editing. The idea of the scholarly edition in fact probably gets closer to the idea of an archive I suppose. But it, I suppose, conceptually involves some overlap in a sense but less about the individual work and more about the collection as a whole but it does overlap because of course you’re still thinking about, well, how do you search those works, what kind of ways can you, what kind of terms are you highlighting, to kind of be able to find your works in your collection. And so, it does overlap with digital tagging and coding and the metadata that you can search, so yeah. I don’t know, I’m not quite sure where I’m going with that but it seems to me that when I’m going to teach this module, I’m going to have to pay some attention to those kinds of differences so it’s another term to bring in alongside editing or the edition so that’s the only thing that stuck me or has recently struck me. I have no answers to that by the way it’s just a, it seems to me that if you start evolving different disciplines then these other terms become something to play with.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I agree. I teach a curation class and I often find when I’m explaining the role of the curator in the process of developing a collection, I’m essentially describing the role of an editor, it’s the person who has made these critical decisions and constructed the thing, and it’s interesting that the disciplines are very, very close, especially in a digital context where a lot of the practices and processes are essentially the same, but they’ve kind of come up with these two very different vocabularies and practitioner norms and I’m not quite sure why that is…</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Yeah, yeah and I think it’s going to be really obvious that our current module which has a focus very much on remediating literary books that that focus is going to have to shift because some of the context and some of the ideas are going to be meaningless for historians or people working in the social sciences. But clearly those people do work with digital texts of some sort, they get their stuff from and how they get them and how they appear and the way they appear and how you can search them online those questions do overlap what we’ve been doing with English Literary students so yeah, you’re right I think and also by the way I’d love to know what you do on your course so maybe you can talk about that some other time but yeah that’s going to be really interesting, I think.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Where do you feel disciplinarity comes into the conversation here around things like digital curation, editing, archiving, social sciences, literature, text that’s not literary? Are these things that we need to negotiate? When we talk about digital scholarly editing in the future is that going to be based on the idea of disciplines? Because right now I feel that’s a very literary practice. Will we ever get to that broader textual context?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	Yeah, I do think that’s going to break down and I think necessarily from a variety of different pressures and partly the way the disciplines themselves work their subject you know. But also what strikes me and it’s a really great example here of how issues of editing and the textual choices you make overlap with questions of race and violence in the archive and it’s the Early Caribbean Digital Archive which is really fantastic because what they’ve done to kind of try and reanimate the voices within archive is they’ve got a bunch of white texts but quite often they contain the voices of slaves, ex-slaves and they’ve deliberately excerpted them, they’ve kind of bracketed them out from the text which to me as a textual scholar I’ve kind of gone ‘oh no’ but actually, from I suppose a post-colonial digital editing point of view, is a fantastic move (where was I going with this?) and that archive is a wonderful example of the overlap between historical curation and editing and I think demonstrates what happens to disciplinarity I think when you start asking different questions of what your discipline is supposed to do. That was a bit of a rambling answer but that’s the example that really struck me to kind of, as something which overlaps with literary scholarly editing and historical curation as well as these issues of historical violence and race.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Not rambling at all, it’s a really interesting depiction of how disciplinarity can be a barrier to some of these practices…</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	I mean, I speak on this from a very personal point of view because when I did my history of ECCO which was on digital humanities and bibliography, I later discovered actually that one of my examples was a history of Jamaica and I’d kind of ignored its kind of wider context and wider resonances since colonialism so I’ve since wrote a paper which traces a very different history with goes beyond bibliography and digital humanities because those were actually pointing me, were narrowing my conception of what that text meant. I’m sorry, I’m writing this now so that’s why it’s… these issues of race are really uppermost in my mind and why they keep coming back so my apologies if that’s kind of taken this conversation off track.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Take it where it needs to go…</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	And indeed, actually if I was going to be, now that I’m thinking about it, if I want to do some really blue sky thinking about digital archives, they would do something like that. They would, if you’ve got a historical text, if you’ve got a text and you’re digitising something from, I don’t know, 1801, why not trace its wider kind of history, why has it ended up in certain libraries for example? What’s been its provenance history to enable that edition to end up where it is? That’s part of its, arguably, part of its metadata. And indeed, you know, in my own history I also include how it got from the library to a digital archive as well so it’s how I, my own situatedness in relation to…that’s going beyond what a digital archive could do but it seems to me there might be a wider conception of a book’s history and how we might build that into a digital edition. That’s getting quite abstract I guess, but…</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned your book, which I’m conscious I haven’t read, but I’m at least aware that you have written it and I thought it was a curious topic to write on the history of the ECCO collections, the history of an online collection. What was the motivation behind focusing on a history of a collection as opposed to the history that’s in it, the history of the content, or is that something you do touch on?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	The content is part of its history; yes indeed, the choices have been made on what to include and what not to include, that’s part of its history indeed but I don’t actually discuss its content except in terms of remediation, how these books have been remediated the way they are. So, yes how I got there, again from the students, you know, the frustration of trying to teach students the difference between Project Gutenberg and something like ECCO and something like the Blake Archive and you know you go to the sites and you think it’s a real deterrent to try to teach students to rip apart FAQ’s and go into the ‘About’ sections and you know does this documentation tell you anything about why these texts look the way they look and of course ECCO is something I’ve been using for many years now and I’ve always been slightly interested in knowing that question, you know why is it I can search it in this way, why is it that the books look this way and I realised that there wasn’t any information to tell me that. So, it’s a long history of ECCO, it goes back to it’s the invention of the Eighteenth-Century Short Title Catalogue in the mid 70’s and how that forms the basis of what you see on ECCO as well as the technical and commercial decisions that have gone into the database. So yeah, I thought it was good, a really interesting…I thought it would be really useful as a case study of how… what kind of information we need about our collections and I think the only thing that comes close to that is probably the variety of articles that trace for example EEBO.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	By studying the archive, the collection itself as opposed to its content, you were trying to get at something in particular? Why study a collection in itself?</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	I mean why study this one is more because I knew where to start but as I said, I kind of, so you know in a sense it’s a great study of ECCO in particular but I guess I think what I hoped was that it’s also a study in how we might, how other people might study other collections in a similar manner. It’s kind of information I think we all need to use our collections properly and in an informed way and again that comes from my experience of trying to teach students you know ok you use Project Gutenberg to access this text, how come that’s different from Google Books? Do you know it’s different from Google Books?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s interesting. I do think it is a novel idea, it’s hard to find books like that…</p></sp><sp who="#SG"><speaker>SG</speaker><p>	The closest one is the book by Schonfeld called ‘JSTOR: A History’ and that’s the closest book length study that I’ve come across. It’s hugely detailed and it has access to JSOR’s extensive records and did something slightly different but that would be the nearest parallel I can think of and I guess, you know, this does relate to your questions or any questions about what a scholarly edition should do and if you think about collecting editions then it should give a similar overview it seems to me to the user about the large-scale curatorial decisions that have gone into individual editions.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>