<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Eimear Ryan</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on October 1st, 2021</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_ER.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>Eimear Ryan is the author of a novel, Holding Her Breath (Sandycove 2021) and a memoir, The Grass Ceiling (Sandycove 2023). She is a co-founder of the literary journal Banshee and its publishing imprint, Banshee Press. She lives in Cork.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Why doesn’t Banshee do a huge amount of digital stuff?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	A lack of knowledge and resources I would say, like, we love print, we love books as objects it’s… certainly when we were setting up it made sense to make it a print publication because we always wanted to have something that people could buy, you know. And back then I suppose 2014/2015 setting up a digital subscription was maybe not as easy as it is now with platforms like Squarespace and all like that, you know, so we kind of wanted print from the get-go but we’ve kind of changed over the years. I suppose the first version of our website was a Tumblr which is kind of a sign of the times because Tumblr was very cool in 2014 but that became very inflexible and not very user friendly as the years went by. So, I think in 2020, in lockdown, we had a bit of extra time because we actually delayed our spring print issue so we kind of said we have a bit of extra time and resources, we can refresh the website essentially. So, we moved over to Squarespace and we found that a much better platform and our general policy is to… if a print issue sells out we’ll kind of gradually put that material on the website for people to read for free and that kind of gives us a steady stream of content as well I suppose for the website and also if an issue has just been released we will pick usually six or seven pieces from that issue to put online for free to act as like a taster for that issue and encourage people to buy it so that has been the extent of our digital publishing so far.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Why did you choose that particular, print first, model? </p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	I suppose when we set up, you know, there’s probably a bias among writers towards print and they’re seen as… print is nearly seen as being more prestigious in a way even though like obviously that’s not the case, there are so many huge digital publishers in the world now that if you get something online at the New Yorker, that’s better than getting in print anywhere else you know like. But I suppose, as I said, we wanted the idea of having a physical object to sell because from the start we wanted to pay writers so a big part of that is having an income and the only way that we could see to charging for this material was to have a kind of a physical object. We also wanted I suppose, we wanted to… we envisioned having events and launches and things like that and having a physical object to sell at those events is handy, it kind of gives something to orient the event around. And I suppose as well we… a huge part of our motivation for setting up the magazine was we loved the Stinging Fly, the Dublin Review and Gorse and all these other physical magazines and we wanted ours to be in company with and in conversation with those print magazines. But yeah, we had this idea, I suppose, that writers prefer print and it’s seen as more prestigious but I don’t think that’s actually borne out because writers also love have something that is widely available and shareable on social media; like, I think that has become more and more important to writers in the last couple of years to have something they can throw up on their Instagram or on their Twitter. And so, as I said, when an issue sells out, we kind of upload all the contents to the website so there’s a sense of the issue, the object, becomes a collector’s item but the content doesn’t. The content is… we don’t hoard the writing itself but even when the print issue kind of runs out and I suppose that’s the advantage of digital publishing is that it’s not finite you know.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	On digital publishing, you mention a lack of knowledge and resources; what resources are you lacking?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	I mean a huge thing that we are talking about at the moment is we really… particularly with our books, we have three Banshee Press books, we have two coming down the line and we only have them in print at the moment. Actually, one of ours, Deirdre Sullivan’s ‘I Want to Know That I Will Be Okay’ we have that in audio format as well but that’s solely because Deirdre’s agent sold the audio rights to Bolinda which is an audio book company and they handled everything, we didn’t have to do anything on that front. We would love to do audio books of our other books, but we don’t have the know-how, the resources to book a studio and get it recorded and then package the files so they’re easily downloadable across a range of different platforms and providers. It all seems like an overwhelming ask if you’re not already embedded in that industry. And equally with Kindle, I know myself, I listen to audio books all the time, I read books on Kindle, our books are not available on Kindle and we really want to change that but again, it’s knowing how to take an InDesign file or a PDF, repackage it in the correct format, get it up on Amazon or various places where you can – BorrowBox you know, where you can download audio or eBooks, that’s just knowledge that we don’t have and I suppose we’re focused on the print production cycle and finding time for figuring out how to make eBooks, it’s never a kind of an urgent thing even though it’s something that we all really want to make happen. I think ultimately, we’ll probably end up calling in some kind of consultant or specialist on eBooks to do a job for us essentially because I do feel it’s something that is lacking in our repertoire.	 Banshee Press titles are now available as e-books. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Can you envisage a future where you are doing things with digital technologies beyond remediation, so beyond say the transfer of content from print to Kindle or audio book? Are there other things you think could be done with the digital, or do remediation and distribution remain the priority in terms of what digital publishing can provide right now?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	I mean probably the only thing that we’ve done in that sense is we did an online only issue in the spring of 2020 because we had an issue almost ready to go but there were so many uncertainties at that time in terms of like the post and, you know, book shops – would they be open, would they be able to stock a book, things like that and we just said ‘this is too uncertain, this is too difficult, we’ll postpone the print issue till the autumn and we’ll do an online issue’. So, we took, I think it was maybe five stories and five poems and just published them on our Squarespace website but presented almost as if it was another issue in our shop that you could kind of click into even though all the contents were free. But that’s probably the only time that we’ve done digital first and it was because we felt that we could circumnavigate the issues that come with print and Covid. Thinking back now, even at the time, we didn’t know if our printers would be open to print the issues, you know, we didn’t know if they could deliver to us that kind of thing. So, there was just so many complications and doing a digital only issue seemed to be a way to circumnavigate all of that, but I think at the moment anyway any digital things that we do will be alongside our print but we’re very aware that there is now an expectation of like those digital formats I think. Even since we’ve started Banshee, podcasts have just exploded and audio books right alongside them. Both the Stinging Fly and the Dublin Review which are two publications that we would always kind of look to for standards in Ireland, they both have podcasts. And even when… as a contributor to the Stinging Fly and the Dublin Review, they would get in touch with me to say can we put your story online and that kind of got me thinking ‘oh this is something that we should be doing as well’, putting material from the magazine online as well not just kind of keeping it locked away in the issue itself.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned the importance of social media content, that authors want digital content because they want to be able to put things on social media. One of this project’s other participants is a philosopher, and a few years ago he was writing a book on dialogue. He wanted to mimic the book’s topic, dialogue, in his authorial practice, so he put a draft online and allowed readers to make comments and then he responded and so on – the sort of thing we sometimes see with open review processes in academia. As both a publisher and an author, do you think that authors are ready for this sort of dialogue with readers, dialogue beyond simple post-publication exchanges on social media? And do you think readers are ready for dialogue with authors in such a fashion? Do you think that any of us might be ready for fundamental change to our dominant habits of reading, or do we just want to publish and comment? Do we really want real dialogue with real consequences? Or do we just want to talk about stuff after it has already been published?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	So, a kind of collaborative format, almost?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yeah, I mean I don’t want to say participatory writing, but could you envision a situation where all of your submissions are, say for example, made publicly available and then you arrive at the canonical issue through some kind of participatory public selection process? So, I suppose just like open review, but for the publishing industry more generally.</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	That would be cool.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Are we ready for that? Do we want that kind of relationship? </p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	Yeah, it’s really interesting. I was reading on the Bookseller an article about Substack and how they’re now looking to enter the UK market. So, they’re reaching out to all these literary agents and saying ‘ok you’re Salman Rushdie’s agent, how about he commits to writing a Substack newsletter for a year?’ And people are kind of seeing it almost as a return to like a serialised novel, you know, like the kind of Dickensian thing of putting out a chapter every week or a chapter every month and you can see how it could work that way where feedback from readers could inform where the novel is going, you know. Definitely in my youth when I used to write fan fiction that would be a part of it as well, you’d put up a chapter and you’d get instant feedback from people who knew the characters intimately and that feedback would very often inform where you would go next. But yeah, it is interesting that combination of the old school serial novel and these very modern technologies and the potential there, that kind of mix of old and new is compelling you know.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I think publishing is still, to a degree, a very closed loop in the sense that the call for submission goes out and the next thing you see is the finished book and whatever happens in between is very much opaque. I don’t know if you’ve seen the Bloodaxe Archive that was built by Newcastle University? They have made a lot of the editorial remarks and draft materials – the stuff that usually stays hidden – available for public consumption, making explicit the connection between the publishing process and the products of that process. Is that that kind of thing that you think would be valuable to a press like Banshee or is there value to opaqueness, of having the finished thing as the only visible thing?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	Yeah I think that is interesting and I was even in a class the other day and it is a question that we get a lot ‘how do you make your decisions?’ and people are really interested in the process you know and I suppose we’re just describing a process of reading a lot and putting a label on things as to whether we like it or not and gradually whittling and whittling until we get to maybe a hundred submissions that we all love and then it becomes really painful in terms of what we cut and what we don’t, you know. So, it is opaque but it’s also really mundane as well, there’s no great mystery to it, I think, you know. But I do like that idea of bonus material, almost like DVD extras but for books and I could see that down the line as something that ye might get in a digital archive, some insight into the making of the book like you would on a DVD. I agree with you and it’s something that has really struck me in the process of my own book which is that so many people impact on what the book is. So many people make it what it is the finished product and yet only my name is on the cover and yes, I have acknowledgements but that’s totally at my discretion who I want to acknowledge, and I think it seems somehow weirdly wrong. You know that tall narrow text at the bottom of a movie poster, I feel like books should have those because like my editor has had such a profound effect on the book, my agent has as well, you know, the cover designer has such a profound effect on the book. There are so many people that contribute to what it ends up becoming, that it just feels weird to assign one author to it.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You’re an accomplished author, do you think about the various ways in which your texts are mediated?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	Yeah like, I like reading on Kindle mostly because it’s lightweight, you can read in the dark, so I’ll often read in bed if I wake up at like 5am, I’d rather read the Kindle than look at my phone and so I read a lot on Kindle. I’ve never really thought about this before my own book came out but I think the Kindle format kind of just strips the book of its beauty in a way like you know. I’m so delighted with the cover that I ended up with and you don’t really… and the packaging and the feel of the cover and everything and you just don’t get that experience with the Kindle but of course this never bothered me until my own book came out you know. So, I do think that nice sensory experience is a little bit lacking from the Kindle. The audio book was good fun, I actually got to pick the reader, I was given a shortlist of three voices and I got to pick the one to read the book, so that was fun. But yeah, I mean I love audio books as well and I definitely think there’s just a general expectation among readers that not only can you pick up the book itself and read it, you can read it on Kindle when you go to bed and then the next morning when you get up and you’re making your coffee you can switch to audio book. I think particularly because Amazon have such a stranglehold on all of this but they also like kind of optimise the whole experience where like you can finish reading on your Kindle and pick up on your audio book at the exact same spot, you, know which is kind of a cool feature but yeah I definitely think about… and you see it on Instagram as well, you see all the book bloggers on Instagram posting images of the book and some of them will post a picture of their phone with their audio book app open some of them will post a picture of their Kindle with the cover on the Kindle in black &amp; white and then some will obviously post the book itself, but yeah I’m definitely aware of all the different ways people are consuming it.,</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And what about remediation of a different form, like an adaptation? I know you’ve already had your essay, The Fear of Winning, adapted into The Grass Ceiling for screen.</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	Oh, I’d love it yeah. I mean, I’d be really happy if anybody wanted to adapt it for screen, yeah.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do you think about that process of adaptation, seeing your words changed into some completely other form? Do you even see it as a completely other form?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	It was hard for me. I think I wrote a treatment for the Grass Ceiling but at a certain point it was really helpful for me to step away and just let Iseult [Howlett, the director] shape it the way she wanted to shape it because I think adapting your own work is difficult, particularly when, like me, you have such a… I don’t really have a great visual brain; my sensibility is very much based in words whereas Iseult was able to take the words and see what it could be on the screen. Once I kind of stepped back from that aspect of it and let her transform it, I was much happier actually because I felt like she knew, she understood the medium that we were going towards and I didn’t, you know, so I think she was much better placed to do that. I love adaptations actually, a lot of my favourite tv properties are adaptations, you know like, Game of Thrones, Hannibal, Wolf Hall like I love all those shows. But I think in terms of like Sally Rooney adapting her own novel to screen, I think that’s incredible, like I don’t think I’d ever be able to adapt my own work because in my head it’s in this format, you know, but I’d be very happy to hand it over to somebody else and have them transform it I suppose into a new property.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What is a treatment?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	So, it’s kind of like a novel synopsis but for a film. So, I kind of wrote an outline of ‘here’s some lines in voice over’ and ‘here’s a montage that we’re seeing on the screen’. This was to help to get funding for the documentary and it was to convey what the finished product would be like through words and descriptions of images. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And then you give that to the director and they use that to inform their vision?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	Yeah, but I had trouble deviating from the essay itself whereas I think Iseult was much better placed to take inspiration from the essay and then run with it, you know, and make it its own entity. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Thank you. When you think of digital tools and platforms that are changing literary publishing, what comes to mind? Any specific practices or specific tools?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	I suppose things like Wattpad comes to mind and you know there was that trend I’d say particularly in the early 20-teens of people writing directly for platforms like Wattpad or even self-publishing for Kindle and just totally catching on and then being picked up by a traditional publisher. Or you think of like the Instagram poets like the Rupi Kaurs who again it’s almost like a reversal where they explode on a digital platform initially and then their work reverts back to traditional publishing. It’s interesting in terms of the stuff that Banshee shares on social media, like it’s interesting to look at the different platforms because we have a Facebook, a Twitter and an Instagram. Facebook is for our audience, for some reason, it’s very quiet, we get very little engagement there. Instagram gets a lot of likes but not a lot of click throughs I’ve noticed, whereas Twitter gets the most clicks by far and directs by far the most traffic to our website. I suppose I’d also think about things like Goodreads that has become such a practice I think for readers just to automatically record what they’ve read on Goodreads and to rate it on a kind of a blunt 1-5 star scale and it has become really influential I suppose and a weird kind of measure of how a book is doing is to see how it’s doing on Goodreads. So that I suppose is some of that immediate reception I suppose that you were talking about before… or immediate feedback that you might have got on fan fiction back in the day, you’re now getting that immediate feedback on Goodreads. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And what about the future?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	Yeah, I don’t know. I’m just kind of hoping that it becomes easier to access. Like ecommerce, I’ve noticed, has become way easier since we started Banshee. We’ve been selling online since 2014 but it was quite creaky previously, we had just PayPal buttons but sometimes they wouldn’t work and things like that whereas I feel like Squarespace has provided this really seamless, easy to use ecommerce platform where, even if you don’t know much about websites or whatever you can still sell things pretty easily. And, do you know what, these technologies might already exist, and I just don’t know about them. I would love for there to be a way to just easily create and sell an eBook or like easily create and sell an audio book, you know, but what we found is that, you know, Amazon has such a stranglehold on these things and as a small press it’s very hard to deal with Amazon. It can be expensive to deal with Amazon. So, while we want to access these technologies, there’s also barriers in place, you know, and there’s difficulties so, I would love for it to become more like open source and not as dominated by one or two companies.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	When you say “easy to create an e-book”, what would you like to be easier?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	Just that when you convert the file that the formatting doesn’t go haywire and things like that and that it becomes… I suppose that the customer experience becomes easy as well that they don’t have to jump through a million hoops to like if they already have a Kindle or an iPad that they don’t have to jump through a load of hoops to get this file onto their Kindle or iPad. I suppose that’s the thing about Apple and Amazon they do make the process of buying very easy and very seamless, you know, which is why people use those platforms, which is why I use those platforms but if it was possible for smaller presses to have that same ease of use for the customer but in a more independent way.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think about the need to archive the Banshee materials? Do you think about the digital preservation of Banshee’s publications?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	Yeah, and I mean I think because since we started, we’ve all been living in different places, so all of our work has been done online so like our emails, our Google docs, our Google drive that’s… if you’re looking for a history of Banshee, it’s all in there. So yeah, if we were compile or sell or archive it would be mostly digital material I would say. We do have printed material as well but the vast, vast majority of it is digital.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that, in the wider literary community, there’s a common set of digital tools and practices or are people are just using a variety of things?</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	Yeah, I think it’s a variety of things. I definitely think I see Squarespace being used quite a lot; I could be wrong about that, but I think a lot of the websites use that as their platform. Obviously, everybody is on social media as well. The podcast thing, I would love to get on the podcast front as well just because I love podcasts and literary podcasts in particular, you know, like the New Yorker Fiction Podcast is probably the original, the OG. But the iterations of that the Fly and the Dublin Review have are also just really enjoyable and it is cool to hear work read by the author or by somebody who really loves that story and it is a different way to experience the story. I think that would be a really valuable addition to our output but again it’s kind of time and money and know-how, you know, you need all those things to do something like that, to take on a project like that. Just a really random practical thing that is another small barrier to us moving into the eBook space is there is VAT on eBooks which complicates us selling eBooks a little bit. There’s no VAT on regular books obviously and I think the UK just eliminated VAT on eBooks, but the EU hasn’t done so yet. So, we’re kind of hoping they will eliminate that because it doesn’t really make sense you know if a printed book has no VAT, then why should a digital book, you know, but it does make it more complicated for us in terms of selling eBooks so we’re kind of hoping that that barrier will not be there in the future.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And finally, do you think we’ll ever see our literary community doing more born-digital literature, by which I mean digital in that is computational in the aesthetic sense? You know, hypertextual fiction, literary video games, or even quite linear forms of digital literature, like the film poem, which is quite popular in Ireland.</p></sp><sp who="#ER"><speaker>ER</speaker><p>	That would be cool actually. So, when I broke my ankle, I treated myself to a Switch and I found that the games that I’m drawn to are these narrative exploration games like ‘Gone Home’ is probably the classic of the genre and there’s another brilliant one called ‘What Remains of Edith Finch’ and they’re like, they’re essentially just like visual novels, visual mystery novels, like even the game play aspect is quite minimal because you’re not really affecting what’s happening, you’re just going around picking things up, exploring, hearing a voiceover every now and then, you know, you’re not really affecting the action but you’re experiencing the action in a way that feels really immersive and those are the kind of games that I like. I’m not one for being shot at or shooting at people or anything like that, I find that really stressful but these kinds of quiet spooky games where you just walk around houses learning stories, I really like them. So, like if I ever got the opportunity to do something like that, I would love to script something like that you know whereas before if you’d asked me ‘would you write a video game?’ I’d be like ‘oh God no’ you know, but there are really interesting sub-genres that do mirror the novel in a way.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>