<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Sara Mansutti</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on January 25th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_SM.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>SARA MANSUTTI is a PhD candidate in Digital Humanities at University College Cork. She completed a master’s degree in Italian Philology and Literature at the University of Udine in 2017. Her PhD project, in connection with the EURONEWS project funded by the Irish Research Council, focuses on the letters and newsletters sent by Cosimo Bartoli, Florentine agent in Venice, to the Medici between 1562 and 1572. She is exploring how the combination of Handwritten Text Recognition and crowdsourcing could help to publish primary historical sources in digital format.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	When I offer the terms digital edition or digital scholarly editing, what comes to mind? </p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	I mainly think about manuscript or historical sources made digital and available online. I don’t think of eBooks when I refer to a digital edition but much more of scholars working on them to publish the text. I see it in continuity with the work of previous scholars: previous scholars did it with manuscripts, especially with philologists. They published editions in a printed form, writing all the notes and comparing sources, comparing different manuscripts. My idea of digital edition is probably influenced by my background in Italian philology, so I have this type of understanding and the first image that came to my mind when speaking about digital edition is this type of scholarly edition. I see the digital not only as transporting the printed edition in a digital format but being able to enrich the edition on two different levels. On one side, it is easier for the readers to search and to compare different sources, for example, you can see two different texts and compare them, while in the printed format it is impossible. On the other side, you can tag the words and make the edition more interactive for the users and at the same time I think it’s more accessible because if it is free and open, everyone with an internet connection can access it. With the printed edition, it could happen that the library doesn’t have this edition.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned there a few things that digital editions do well; what are the things that digital editions could do better?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	I think the main problem is that all the digital editions are singular projects scattered around the web while with a library catalogue, it is easier to find the printed edition you are looking for. The national catalogues enables you to see which libraries are holding that edition, you can see where this book is, if it’s not in Cork , you can go to Dublin and see it, or you can find it in another country. With digital editions, I think there is not a collection of digital editions so it is difficult to find them. The main problem is that they are not catalogued in library catalogues. There are probably some collectors of digital projects for example, I don’t remember if in Austria there is one, but they are not omni comprehensive as a library catalogue. Cataloguing digital edition as library sources could be a good starting point. And then another problem is the sustainability of these sources because a printed edition can last forever, while a digital one has two problems: maintaining the software and finding the money to pay the domain. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Talk to me about sustainability…</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	I think they are more fragile than classical editions but there are some options. I think, for example, if you create a text, an XML file of a digital edition, you can store it in some long-term repositories like the digital repository of Ireland and at least you know that the edition is preserved somewhere. Maybe it’s not the nice digital edition with images and the search bar and other options but at least the text with the tags is preserved. The problem is if you want to show the digital edition and maintain the software to visualise this.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I’m detecting something of a distinction between the underlying data and the frontend interfaces and software; do you think there is too much emphasis on the frontend?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	I think the main value is in the backend, not in the interface because the interface will change with the development of technology while the plain TEI or XML text file will remain and can be later used, so I think this is the most important part. At the same time it is not enough, for example, if I present just these plain texts for my thesis or for a project for which I received a grant or funding, probably it wouldn’t be enough because there is not the option to make it readable and presentable. It is available but not in a user-friendly way. The main work I think is on the intellectual part, the backend, but the front end is necessary to make it useful to all.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Going back to sustainability, are there ways in which we could make digital editions more sustainable beyond just separating the data and storing that in dedicated repositories? Do you think there are ways we could generally make the products and practices of digital editing more sustainable?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	Yes, I think that probably we need to have a protocol to create a digital edition in accordance to the digital repositories so that they can be stored in a digital repository. From the beginning it is important to understand which software can be used for this and which ones are not sustainable. For example, I’m thinking about using an open-source program created by the University of Pisa and Torino which is written only in HTML: it is not so fancy but it is difficult that it will be corrupted or become old because it is a very simple front end digital edition and all with HTML, it’s very simple and doesn’t have plugins or other things.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	For context, could you tell me a little bit about your research?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	Yes, I’m trying to create a digital edition, I don’t know if it will be digital edition or maybe a digital archive of this sources because at the end, I am not following all the TEI rules. I want to create a digital edition of letters and newsletters sent by a Medici agent in the second half of the 16th Century and I’m trying to combine different digital tools. As a first step, I applied handwritten text recognition with Transkribus to have a rough transcription of all the documents and I obtained 94% of correctness. Then, since I have 9 volumes of documents, I set up a crowdsourcing project asking volunteers/participants to help me correcting the documents and tagging the documents. So there are two different types of tags, one is for abbreviations and because with hand written text recognition it is better to transcribe the text as it is, with the abbreviation, I asked people to tag the abbreviations and write the expansion as a property. Then I asked them to add three different tags, people, places and dates. This is much more for my research because I want to understand who this agent met in Venice and his network in Venice. So, there are two different levels and I’m using Transkribus to tag the transcription because I think it’s easier for the volunteers to see the text and the image at the same time and correct it, they just need to add the tag without using XML. I know for example that in the Transcribe Bentham project they asked the volunteers to write the tag with the brackets using XML. My approach is easier for the volunteers, and also for me because in the end I can download each transcription in different formats and I can choose also the TEI format. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>  	So right now you’re actually in the process of building a digital edition. With your background in philology, I appreciate you have an intellectual foundation in the practices of scholarly editing but in terms of the digital side of things, what has been your experience of the relevant tools, platforms, and techniques?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	So for Transkribus I followed some online tutorials and then I tried it. I also attended an online workshop about the software I want to use for showing my digital edition but I tried it with just one or two pages, I haven’t tested it deeply. For TEI, I read some stuff, heard about it during some DH couses and I also followed a short asynchronous course, it was online with Elena Pierazzo. However, I struggle with TEI because a lot of it is theoretical and I understand the general idea of TEI and how it works but then I miss the practical part on my project.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And how have you found working with TEI?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	I’m not working directly right now with TEI. I have Oxygen to use it but my idea is to tag the elements within Transkribus because in this way I can just add the tag without writing it in XML and then download it in the TEI format and see if it is the work with the visualisation programme.</p><p>I know this is probably a weakness of my project because I am not applying TEI in a strict way, For example I have letters and I should add all the tags about sender, recipient and date. I’m not doing that for now but yeah, I think it will take too long and I have too many documents. Because of this I don’t know if we will define it a digital edition or maybe a digital archive of these documents.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned Transkribus, which has worked very well for you, and you mentioned network analysis. Your ultimate aim, if I understand it, is to use the materials you’re working on to do network analysis. Do you think there should be more integration between digital editions and analytical tools like network analysis? Right now we have this situation where people create, collate, download or retrieve the resource or the data, and then they do the analysis. The edition and the analysis, in the sense of quantitative tools and platforms, are quite separate. Can you see a future wherein analytical tools are built into digital editions?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	I think it could be very helpful because you don’t need to extract all the people for example and use Gephi to visualise the network. I’m not able to code or Python, so my workflow would be take the tags, create a CSV or Excel file and put it into Getty. A digital tool built on the digital edition for visualising places, dates and people could be really useful. I don’t know, maybe with Palladio you can do something like that but only with places I think, not with people.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And why do you think that hasn’t been done, then? Katherine Bode describes DH as having a curatorial side and the statistical side; why don’t we just merge these two cultures?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	Probably because different scholars work on them. The digital philologists are more interested in the text and understanding how the text was transmitted through the centuries, while other scholars like historians are more interested in the content and in applying this type of analysis and visualisation. They would probably search for or look at only some elements and not the whole edition, they use only the text or the data and they are not interested in the tradition behind, so I think there are two different types of scholarship.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s interesting. So you are in the middle of doing this work right now; if I gave you a magic wand scenario, unlimited resources, technologies both real and imagined, what would the ideal edition of the future look like?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	So the digital edition would be the text, I imagine it as a user, the text with the possibility to surf all the digital copies, manuscript or archival sources with links to all the people and the places mentioned. I think it could be useful to have links to Wikipedia or Wikidata to help to contextualise the text and also have the possibility to download it, maybe not the images because there could be rights issues but the possibility to download the text in different formats, depending on the work that the scholars would like to do. It would also be nice to have a place where all these digital editions can be stored and preserved and also found, something like a world-wide catalogue of digital editions where one can select the Century or the author and find all the digital editions falling within their search.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned the resources you have been using, and how you found some of them quite useful. Is there enough training available for someone who wants to learn how to build digital editions?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	No, I think… there are many resources but it’s always difficult for me to understand how it works really in a practical way, how can I start to create my digital edition, what I have to do with it and I think the problem with TEI is that it is so big and there are so many variants and tags that, at the beginning, if you don’t have an introduction with somebody else, it is difficult to understand how it works because the guidelines are one thousand pages, and also the website is not clear at first sight to me.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I agree with that.</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	Another thing I probably mentioned when we talked about digital edition when I was I Cork is the cost of the edition because in my case it would be impossible to print all of these transcriptions in a printed edition, it would probably be a lot of volumes. Creating huge printed editions was possible in the 18th, 19th and 20th Century, many archival sources or manuscripts were published at that time. Now we don’t have the funding to do it, nobody will fund one project to print an edition of 16th century letters. The digital edition is less expensive but also more fragile as I told you before.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is that the great affordance of digital editions, that they are much more cost effective?</p></sp><sp who="#SM"><speaker>SM</speaker><p>	Yeah also much more accessible and I think especially for PhD students and early career researchers. If I go to a publisher and I say I want to publish my edition of these sources, they wouldn’t say yes because a printed edition has many costs and few readers. I think research has changed so this type work, a printed edition, especially of archival sources, is just seen a transcription, it is not seen as a research product as before. We are asked to find other ways to make it appear as research and at the same time I think there are beginning to be ways to make a digital edition count as a publication, there are some journals which review digital editions or the digital projects, you can add a DOI so it becomes a publication but I always believe that for committee a book, a printed book on one topic, I don’t know, the information in Venice in the second half of the 16th Century, always counts more than a digital edition so there is also this problem. Another small example I have to face with my thesis: I have to do the digital edition and also write the thesis, the digital edition is not enough, it is not enough to write a small explanation of it, I need to write a thesis. The same happens in the following steps of the career, it is not enough to have digital projects, you need to have also published traditional printed books or publications.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>