<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Mehdy Sedaghat Payam</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on January 13th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_MSP.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>MEHDY PAYAM is Graduate Assistant at the University of Maryland</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Could you tell me what the terms scholarly edition means to you?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	I think my definition of a scholarly edition is the same as a classic one which is a copy that has been edited with more academic vigour so it has more potential to either closest one to the one that the writer has had in mind or has written. In other words, a copy in which the editor has explained about the certain choices that they have made to construct this text and the rationale beyond them.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Are there enough scholarly editions of electronic literature? Are there any exemplars out there?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	Yes. I think ELO volumes can be good examples of scholarly editions, there is three of them and the next one I guess is going to come up in 2026, is it?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yes. Is it 2026? It’s sometime in the next few years.</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	The works included in those volumes are really good but there are so many other works of electronic Literature out there which at least need to be sort of pointed at or have a directory for so that those who want to study the works which have not been in the ELO, they can have access to these kinds of things too and at the moment there is not enough scholarly editions for these kinds of things.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And do you think that the ELO collections are ideal representations of what a scholarly edition of born-digital writing should be?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	Both yes and no. What I really like about ELO collections is that they are forwarded by the writer and there is especially in the earlier volumes there was a guide to how to read these works I appreciate the effort and the hard work that goes into getting these. I think ELO’s collections have become more diverse especially in the latest edition, as far as I remember there are more works in languages other English, including Spanish, Arabic, Portuguese, etc I really appreciate the whole effort to create this kind of diversity but still I think there are any kind of selection there are so many works that are left out so I think even if we could see those works or say well we have included these works in the collections but these are the addresses or the websites of the works which have not been included here so in case you want to see them you can refer to those, I mean that would be great.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Would you see a large catalogue like ELMCIP then as a scholarly edition? </p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	I think ELMCIP is a good catalogue , it introduces the works and the people in charge have been indexing works there, so when you go through that website, you can see that people in charge are showing you that we have searched the web and we have found these works and created this database for them with a very short introduction and the author’s perspective. To get back to your original question, I believe ELO is a good example of scholarly edition, it is also user-friendly and whenever I have had a chance to have a talk about electronic literature obviously I have shown works of ELO because for the people that are first coming into learn about these, ELO is very useful for navigating them towards how they should read this, what the author says and you know stuff like this.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	This idea of the author offering some perspective is something you’ve returned to a few times. I don’t know if you’re familiar with the Pathfinders project led by Dene Grigar and Stuart Moulthrop? They’ve shown in that project how valuable it can be to connect directly with authors, to use authorial perspective as an inherent part of one’s methodology, as means of preserving a sense of a work that can’t otherwise be reliably preserved. See as most of them are still with us, do you think that’s something that should be privileged in scholarly editions of electronic literature, the perspective of the author?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	Oh yes, I’ve seen the book. The thing is, I prefer minimal input from the author like one paragraph or two at most like there is one on ELO, not more than that because I think anything more than that would be sort of strong arming the audience to read it in this way, but here you have just introduction, the author says this, this these two paragraphs and then that’s it.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So why aren’t there more scholarly editions of electronic literature? There are very few.</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	That’s my question too! Since I started researching in this area, which is over ten years ago, I was surprised that there’s only ELO and there’s only like fifty/sixty works which are chosen every five years which was too little for me and I was surprised why there is not even more. I can arguably claim that recently electronic literature is resurfacing and more books are being published about it, we definitely need more scholarly editions and more selections, I mean, like the selections of poetry so see, for example , Norton Anthology has its own selection, Oxford Anthology is different, there are overlaps but they have different collections of poetry and there are some poems that you might find in one that you might not find in another so I think in the same way we may need more scholarly editions of work of electronic literature. I don’t know, maybe it’s the cost, does ELO have to pay the authors to include their works in their collection?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I don’t know.</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	Probably a user database that anyone can contribute to that and include their own works would be a great idea to have. I’m not sure whether we already have this or not because in the last three to five years my research has become more digital humanities than electronic literature but if we have a database that allows users can contribute to and sort of add their own works, could be a great way for at least having something which may not be a scholarly edition but is something that you can chose works from and create scholarly editions out of it.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Would you be worried in a situation like that that we’d lose the editorial intervention that makes an edition scholarly? Or is that a very antiquated way of looking at things?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	I think it is antiquated because these writers are alive and we do not necessarily need the authority of an organization or a prominent scholar to create those scholarly editions. The point of scholarly editions for classical works was that because the work has gone through so many hands and copywriters, there might have been some mistakes in re-writing it or copying it and correct me if I’m wrong but here we have these things which are more like NFT’s right, you have them, you have the original one created by something which is very unique but at the same time you can copy that and then you can recreate it. Something which bothers me is the problem of obsolescence, for example, Flash is not supported on the web anymore and many works which were on Flash you cannot see them anymore. I think this could be a thing that a scholarly edition would sort of help with, with migrating or porting those works onto different platforms so you could actually see them again and interact with them. I think the modern scholarly edition would be more like making these works accessible regardless of the supporting technologies behind them rather than editing them and offering a sort of a scholarly guide.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	In the volume Advances in Digital Scholarly Editing, you contributed a media specific analysis of the first and last editions of Michael Joyce’s ‘afternoon, a story’, obviously one of the most famous first generation works of electronic literature – I wonder if you could speak to that work a little bit?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	That’s a long time ago as part of my PhD dissertation which I definitely need to revisit because I’d like to publish it as a book but let’s see, what I had done in that work was basically showing how the media specificity of the work had changed though the times for example when I first started in 2009 the work was still sold on floppy disks or at least that’s what our university had. But then I went back like three months later to the library and I looked for this and I couldn’t find it and they said ‘oh we have dumped them because you know you couldn’t read them anymore’ which was very unfortunate, I wish I had them… so I had set up a very old Macintosh from 1993 and I started to study that novel on this Macintosh and then I bought the CD, it was sold on CD at the time, and then I read that on a Windows computer and I saw that the materiality had changed, of course, but the capabilities of the novel had changed too so there were some features in the CD version that you could not see in the floppy version and my floppy version was I think 1991 and now it is being sold on flash drives so I don’t know how different these flash drives are going to be from the CD. Anyway, what I was doing at the time was comparing these two, showing their similarities and their differences and how they’re materiality had changed over this and over that and how that had influenced the work itself.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	To what extent do you think that digital editions can account for materiality?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	I think they are absolutely dependent on it because, you know, as soon as the materiality changes, the whole work changes and the work that comes to my mind is 10: 01 by Lance Olsen because it was Flash-based and now you can’t read it anymore. If and when they start to re-port it into a new multimedia platform, whatever it is, Olsen’s work is definitely going to be different from the one which we saw on flash before. So, I think each time the materiality changes, the work itself changes with it too, and this is something that digital editions and scholarly editions should address.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	When you take something that was originally written to be experienced on a specific digital platform, it is very difficult to reliably reproduce it for another digital platform. I appreciate this is a huge issue, and that it’s not specific to the digital, but should we just accept that, when it comes to creating digital editions of born-digital works, that we’re going to lose something, possibly even a lot, as far as the materiality of the work is concerned? </p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	Yeah I think that’s an opportunity because, you know print is print after all, as Katherine Hayles says print is flat, even though we have had various developments in print technology and we have these amazing books like ‘House of Leaves’ and other books like this but print remains print after all but electronic materiality changes, you know, every time every step of the way and new things come around and at the same time these developments offer us new opportunities, even though we lose something, we gain something too. So, I think it’s better to looks at these works as evolving over different evolutions of work so, you know, Michael Joyce’s work ‘afternoon, a story’ started on one platform which was obviously floppy disk, now it’s morphing and getting more complex, gaining something more and losing something by moving into a new materiality. The other day I was trying Meta Quest 2 VR headset and at the same time I was thinking about how different would it be for ‘afternoon’ to be seen in 3D on Meta Quest so I think these are all opportunities but, books, what is the most you can do, you can add footnotes, you can do other lots of other things as well and I’m not sort of saying that print cannot do much but at the same time there is limited capabilities of that even to a writer like Danielewski would say print can do a lot of things and I totally agree with these people but still when you compare it with electronic materiality you see that there are things that electronic materiality can do better and I think these works are evolving and I’m sure someday we will see more works in 3D, I mean works which are specifically designed for VR headset and from then there will be other works that, you know, will be so more dependent on their materiality that you cannot even think about them in print. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What about digital editions for other forms of born digital content, like Twitter? </p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	I think the works in the emerging media are still very young but there are so many things which these works can do that I think they have not yet got the full potential of them. In 2007 Penguin had this wiki-novel collaborative project to see whether users can work together to write a story or not, strangely enough I don’t think anybody has read those stories, but I have read them. I mean I basically printed them out and I read all of them because I wanted to see where it’s going to work and although it took me a very long time but that was a very interesting experience by Penguin which failed but I think Twitter and others are doing it better now, they are re-deploying this example and let’s say experiment and hopefully someday we will have a major trend for Twitter fiction or other emerging media which creates stories and poetry in very non-conventional ways.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And how do we preserve that for future literary historians?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	That’s my question too, have you been to MITH here?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	No, I haven’t, though I obviously know of the lab and the wonderful work being done there.</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	Yeah so they have a host of old computers that are working and they keep them working because that’s one way to experience the materiality and that is what I also did. I was lucky enough that my supervisor in New Zealand had this very old Macintosh and he kept it at his home and he brought it to me so I could read it over there but I think it’s a challenge and I do not have an answer for it. At some point ‘afternoon’ was ported into the internet on the Norton website and I don’t know whether it is there anymore but the experience of reading afternoon on Macintosh was very different than reading it on the web, I mean the old Macintosh, so I think one possible solution would be something like MITH, you know, somewhere where they keep the old media which I think can be impractical as well because the more I think about it, imagine for hundred years from now how many computers there are going to be and you need to have a huge storeroom to have all these old computers. So, yeah, I’ve no idea for it. Yeah, what Stuart Moulthrop is doing in that book would be a good idea to record it to show how it's going but still it is not the way that… I mean it won’t be your first-hand experience with that yeah.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What are you working on now?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	I am working with Matt Miller and a group of other scholars here at University of Maryland to develop an OCR engine for right to left languages like Persian and as well as other languages like Ottoman Turkish and even Urdu. So when we finish this project it will be useful for other languages as well. It’s a Mellon funded project and I’m now a graduate assistant at UMD, doing my second PhD. It is in comparative literature and I am working on that for my thesis I am working on 650 Persian novels, I will do topic modelling and stylometry to analyze the trends in that corpus. In addition to storing and indexing them, I have had to convert them into plain text though this OCR engine and then I can start the computational analysis. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think digital editions should have machine learning and analytical techniques built into them?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	I think that would be a good idea to integrate them but at the moment I don’t think this separation is necessarily bad. Obviously this is one area that people are working in, they are curating works, they have gained expertise in this area. Scholars in the other camp have also gained expertise in their own field as well, and these two groups are now working together. what you suggested could be the future direction of DH.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Imagine I gave you a magic wand, how would you envisage the future digital scholarly edition, what would that look like?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	Well that’s a tough one but I think that it would be more, I mean, this might seem like a contradiction but I think more future scholarly editions would have more user input into them, for example, what I mean by that is when you are reading the work obviously your path in that work is different from another person and if there is a thing that the other person wants to share with the people who are reading this they can sort of have the ability to submit it and of course it needs to be moderated but at the same time if there is something relevant add it to that work and I think something like a forum that you know people talk about these works so something scholarly edition would have more user input, a democratic scholarly edition, which at the moment seems like a contradiction, but might be realized in the future.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, like a social edition?</p></sp><sp who="#MSP"><speaker>MSP</speaker><p>	Yes.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>