<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Gerard Caruthers</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on Date: February 17th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_GC.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>GERARD CARUTHERS is Francis Hutcheson Professor of Scottish Literature at the University of Glasgow and General Editor of the multi-volume edition of the Oxford University Press Complete Works of Robert Burns. He has been in receipt of two major grants from the AHRC under the rubric of ‘Editing Robert Burns for the 21st Century’.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I want to talk to you about your work with the Editing Robert Burns for the 21st Century project. But before we get on to that, I wonder if you could tell me what the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	I think in some ways James what we’ve got with the Oxford University Press edition of Burns under Redden of course but the two AHRC grants is to begin with quite a traditional print edition, the thing we’re discovering though, quite clearly although we can’t necessarily do a lot about this, is that as we do the print edition we’re discovering digital possibilities that might represent a subsequent phase. So, for instance we now realise that previous bibliographies of Burns, previous editions which are really, really complicated, in the past there have been print bibliographies of Burns, the way forward now, we’ve done some work on this, is an online version of that with all the digital possibilities that that allows. So, we need a new digital bibliography of Burns for the future of scholarship and our edition is pointing towards that in some ways and we’ve got an article coming out in the British Academy volume about Editing Burns and the digital archive and we’re beginning to point to that. I’ll maybe send you a copy of that and as I say James it’s just beginning to point towards possibilities that we can’t quite yet grasp but it’s almost like the next generation will be able to do things there and with other material. There’s a very basic digital thing obviously where the AHRC grant has allowed us to have quite sophisticated websites with documentaries with performance, some performance, other things, blog, lots of kinds of secondary digital materials that back up the print edition, already in my head ten or twenty years down the line beyond my time I see the print edition becoming more fully digital and of course our edition does become part of the Oxford editions online about eighteen months after each of the volumes, we have produced four of eleven volumes at the moment and we hope in the future at some point where the Oxford platform becomes much more digitally agile, at the moment its more or less just a digital version of the print stuff but that I think will become more sophisticated if that makes sense.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Can you talk me through some of those digital possibilities?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	Sure, so again quite a general example but you know three of the volumes so far we have edited the songs of Robert Burns and in the print volumes we’ve got notes with previous sources, I’ve factual notes etc. etc., the future clearly will have embedded links to song performances in a digital version and much more extensive pathways of notes for people that want to follow through. So although I’m not particularly digitally literate even as I now work on the print edition, I know in the future this is going to be much more people will much more want to access things online and digitally and there are much greater possibilities although I don’t want to say the print book edition of Burns or anything else is superseded because I don’t think that’s entirely true none the less the limitations of the print book are now very apparent to me I think.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Future possibilities?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	What we will need at some point is some kind of grant funding to develop the bibliography of Robert Burns so we’ve done online on our website one of my R.A.’s Dr Craig Lamont has begun to do a digital bibliography of Robert Burns and that might be worth a look at and the kind of collations and the descriptions on that even with the short version are way in advance of anything that a publisher would print and a big project in the future we’d have that as a huge digital project where you would have more information than ever before, probably about a thousand previous editions of Burns and obviously the digital online possibility would allow you to search that and format that in all kinds of different ways that you can’t with a print book so its just as simple as that and also as complicated as that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that this model, coupling traditional print editions with the online complementary materials, is something that should be pursued more?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	I think it has to be pursued more James I think it’s happening naturally for projects like ours and probably other ones, I think it’s just an inevitable evolution and also again quite a simple point where we’re collating text and variance and all kinds of supporting material, a lot of that simply can’t go in to a five hundred page edition but in future and the likes of the AHRC wants this material very transparently stored/curated again the digital possibility of just showing all the working is just much more expansive and also allows more teaching possibilities, the print book is the essential stuff at the moment but in the future if I was teaching how to edit I don’t know Burns’ To a Louse or something a digital version of that with much more extensive material would allow access for anyone who was interested but it would also allow me to say to students I want you to go in and do a project via that in a way that they couldn’t with the three pages of notes in the print version so I do see the digital footprint of editing is a much bigger footprint is a much more complete one.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Your project has a lot of interactive maps…</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	Yes, huge possibilities there James and so let’s take the example that we’re just beginning to formulate this now, at the moment we’re editing the three volumes of Burns’ correspondence we’ll finish two of those at some point this year and we’re planning an interactive map of Burns’ associates, his correspondence where you can click on place, you can click on verse and obviously dates and you know you can say well let’s look at all the people he knows in London or all the people he knows in Edinburgh so extracting that information, it’s obviously something you can sort of do in a print book but we’d be able to do that with just clicking a couple of buttons online so that very much excites me because it’s that map of Burns’ associations will be much more readily apparent than the print book can do and if you mention we’ve got the maps the first volume includes Tour Journals and Commonplace Books and a geographic sense that again you can get from the book but the map you can literally follow the places etc so all these possibilities adds to the print book. I suppose I was almost on the verge of implying that you know the print book is sort of weak in some ways but actually I suppose a better way of putting that might be to say the print book with all these digital ancillary possibilities it does become complimentary but as I say I do see a future where I do wonder actually if, you know, the print book clearly has got some decades left in it yet but I really do wonder if you know I’ll be long dead then but a hundred years will anyone be doing a print book plus digital, I kind of imagine that it will be a kind of expansive digital package but who knows I can’t see into the future but there’s certainly a direction of travel James and I’m a traditional scholar in many ways old school to a large extent but even I’m excited by the digital possibilities, you know, and I see them quite clearly even if I don’t entirely understand the nuts and bolts which I’ve got a team of R.A.’s twenty years younger than me because let them do that thinking and that development.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you see the print book and the online component as being appealing to different audiences?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	I think that’s certainly true and certainly in the case of Robert Burns you might realise this, there’s a kind of large amateur or lay Burns movement who are interested and many of them, sixties, seventies and even older they’re at the stage and I kind of get this, they would not want to do without the print book even though some of them would go online. So the print books still at this point plays to a public in the context of Burns in some ways more than the digital thing but that will change in the coming years when your generations come up and I suppose I wonder about this occasionally will publishers like Oxford University Press and others still value the print book while libraries are still more or less taking them that is working and of course what we’ve got very often is online versions of the print book. So in some ways the print book has maybe begun to break down naturally, I don’t think we need to be fearful of that, we still make copies of the print book but almost immediately it’s becoming something digital.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And more generally then, what do you think digital editions might do better?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	Well, I do think that digital editions will simply allow users to reconfigure material. The print book, obviously when I’m editing Burns’ poems, here’s my version of the text, here’s my supporting apparatuses that go with that you can work it out but the digital thing, someone in future will be able to go in and say well I’m actually going to pull up the first and the second edition, I’m even going to do my own text potentially so I think interactivity reception editing is going to be a much bigger thing where those who are interested can unpick stuff and try out different models the way they can’t with the print book and again from the teaching possibility that’s hugely exciting.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It’s interesting that you raise the pedagogical aspect of it; could you speak to your experiences of teaching with and how to create digital editions?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	Only in a very limited way, we have one course at honours level James called Textual Editing and were developing a new Postgraduate Certificate in Book History and Textual Editing and what we’ve got at the moment more or less in the honours course we’ve got one week of twelve that looks at future possibilities in digital editing and again it’s R.A. Craig Lamont who teaches that who’s done the bibliography so at the moment we’re very much kind of at the foothills, we know that this is happening but it’s a small component I think in future and there’s some signs of this in our PG Cert thing there is more space for digital editing and what we’re going to try and build is some kind of even not hugely sophisticated digital platform where students can build their own text and play around with it. So that’s the way it’s going already and of course the two things here about skills yes traditional editing skills but in the online digital context so the whole skills mix is much richer and that quite clearly is speaking to the needs that undergraduates and postgraduates have in terms of employability, skills, all of that kind of stuff so we are very aware of that and we’re looking to develop that but we’re at the start of it. I’ve been to a few symposia on digital editing and I was quite disappointed because always seemed to get what I’ve had too often is that people just putting, I suppose I’ve alluded to this myself but it’s just like here’s the book that we’ve put online and I don’t think that’s what digital editing actually is but no one yet has really articulated for me although I can see some of the possibilities exactly what digital editing is and it’s fair enough I remember when computers were just coming in we kind of knew that practices and attitudes and all kinds of things were going to be changed but we didn’t quite understand how and why and that’s kind of the way I feel about digital editing, I know it’s the future but the details of that future, well by definition it's the future, it’s not as clear as it will be.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Have you noticed any generational trends in terms of how current students come to editing?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	I think the newer generation James are much more used to online experimentation, messing around with things and they’re very happy, I mean (a) they’ve got the facility, you know I look at my 5 year old niece who can outrun me in terms of digital stuff, the newer generation of student are really turned on if you give them something to do that makes them think about online and also makes them do some stuff online a wee bit so you know we’ve had exercises in the past where we’ve got them to go online to look at texts and to get them to do more or less copy and paste jobs but nonetheless they feel they’re doing an online exercise, it’s not as sophisticated yet as it might be but they very much enjoy it and they have that natural aptitude now, people under 30 they take to it like a duck to water so that is something that’s clearly here to stay and will become more sophisticated. Also they’re much more used to the notion of non-fixity so you give them something that says we’re moving away from the book here to another model that’s more provisional, more fluid, more to do with maybe you at the readers end taking this material and playing around with it like they’re very happy with that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Going back to the Burns project, have you thought about the preservation of the digital component?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	Yes well we’re committed with the AHRC to preserve all our working and we’ll be doing that in fairly standard ways but actually the thing I’ve been discussing with the team recently curating that isn’t just a matter of storing it ideally, it’s storing it and allowing it to be available for other people to use so we haven’t quite worked out yet what that means and as always there are issues with storage etc but the university has more or less committed to storing our working sort of in perpetuity but I think there’ll be a generation, my R.A.’s and other people that will need to come along and say we’ve got this material how do we develop it for them and I know the AHRC and other funding bodies will be interested in discussions about how that’s [inaudible] this material is going to become deeper I’ve no doubt.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Your publication record makes for intriguing reading, and you’ve done some really interesting interdisciplinary work, from subjects like mass spectrometry and to psychological assessments of the content of Burns’ correspondence. On interdisciplinary in general, do you think it will be an increasingly important part of the future humanities?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	Yes well at the university James we’ve got the new Advanced Research Centre (ARC) and we’re getting a textual editing lab in there and along with the textual editing lab we’re working with Polyomics or chemistry were working with already mass spec chromatographic signatures, we’ve got, you know Burns had one particularly notorious forger a hundred years after Burns, Antique Smith and we’ve got the chemistry of his ink and we’ve got the chemistry of Burns’ inks and we’ve been speaking to Sotheby’s and other people who are developing this and of course that’s about Polyomics is about chemistry but clearly there will be, in terms of repositories and tools, there will be a clear digital possibility there. So the team at the moment are preparing a grant that’s based on the testing of authenticity in manuscripts and what we’ll need to get our heads round is the kind of digital context in which that operates whether that’s just databases, whether it’s something interactive etc but that’s something we’re developing. So that is interdisciplinarity and as you say we’ve got several bits of interdisciplinarity is something that’s happened naturally because I think sometimes the worst of science stuff is art’s envy of science whereas this stuff has happened quite naturally in fact it was Polyomics who approached me some years back and said, you know, ‘we realise that Burns has got some forgers can we talk about possibilities’ and we’ve worked quite hard on that to develop tools and to publish the article that I think you’ve illuded to and again we’re just at the beginning of that. One of the things we’re looking to do also apropos forgery is we’re going to have a Burns alphabet and an Antique Smith alphabet so we isolate letters, numbers, other features, ornaments etc, etc in different periods of Burns’ life because his handwriting changes at different stages and speaking to colleagues in computing science about how we could maybe develop some digital recognition of sizes and things like that now I’m not entirely sure I know where we’re going with that but I think my computer colleagues will, so a database of handwriting features where we can bring to bear on that computing analysis I think there are big possibilities there but again the early stages of that and it’s probably where many of my younger colleagues thank God can take forward rather than me.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that future digital editions will have next-generation analytical techniques built into them?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	Absolutely, I think they will James because for instance Antique Smith who I’ve mentioned there’s still a lot of Antique Smith out there, the record is quite polluted and sadly there are some people and even some institutions that have Antique Smith manuscripts and they think it’s Robert Burns now if they can be brave enough in future they go on to some of the ancillary materials in an edition like ours they can look and compare and etc, etc so editions in the future will have much more in terms of, most at the moment and I suppose I’ve described them as secondary features I think they won’t be secondary features for future editions, the kinds of students I’ve got now in their 20’s or even 30’s in future will be much more used to an interactive digital experience so in other words we’re not just reading Burns’ poetry or studying Burns’ poetry in that traditional fashion we’re utilising the poetry in a much more multimedia context I suppose in some ways.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Have you experienced colleagues in the wider field who have been resistant to this kind of work?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	Not really James I think you know people around my age you know in my 50’s so my dear friend and colleague Ali Lumsden at Aberdeen who’s overseeing the new edition of Scots Poetry, Ali also sees these possibilities and is very open so I think that the kind of people who might have been resistant or even snooty or whatever, I think those are kind of about twenty years in the past now because I never hear or see anyone who’s resistant to the new terrain and they see it like me they see the new terrain, they don’t entirely understand it less than most but I’m not hearing resistance, you might as you go and speak to different people but I’m genuinely getting no sign of that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	One final question if I may; if I gave you unlimited resources and technologies both real and imagined, what, to you, would the future edition look like?</p></sp><sp who="#GC"><speaker>GC</speaker><p>	The future edition would somehow be able to call up every previous edition and you’d be able to compare and contrast and do all kinds of experimental things with collations with different versions of text. It would just be absolutely almost a multiverse of all the editions that you could conjugate anywhere you chose by imputing, compare and contrast the 1888 edition with the 1920 edition and all the material would come up. Now, that would be technically possible but at the moment James that would be hugely expensive and even now the person hours would be off the scale but one assumes that in future as the digital thing progresses that information would just be much easier just to call up without having been imputed manually. So it’s that kind of thing, right now if I wanted to compare all the previous editions, it wouldn’t be worth the effort but in the future if all those previous editions are digitally available and easily retrievable in different formats then questions that would be interesting in terms of the answers you’d get it would be worth the time going onto the computer for ten minutes and saying I want to do this whereas at the moment trying to answer some of those questions it wouldn’t be worth the time, the manual time, I don’t know if that makes sense but…</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	No, it certainly does. The multiverse of editions, I like that idea, very much. </p></sp></body></text></TEI>