<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Arianna Ciula</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on January 27th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_AC.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>ARIANNA CIULA is Director and Senior Research Software Analyst at King’s Digital Lab, King’s College London (UK). She has broad experience in digital humanities research and teaching, research management, and digital research infrastructures. She holds a PhD in Manuscript and Book Studies, an MA in Applied Computing in the Humanities and a BA Hons in Communication sciences (computational linguistics). She worked at King’s in the past as Research Associate (Centre for Computing in the Humanities) and as Science officer at the European Science Foundation (Humanities), where her primary responsibilities included the supervision of instruments to fund collaborative research in the humanities and the coordination of strategic activities. She also worked as Research Facilitator at the University of Roehampton, where she expanded the research funding portfolio and supported research strategies across the Humanities and beyond. She was appointed Director of KDL in 2022. Her personal research interests focus on modelling and worked on modelling of scholarly digital resources related to primary sources. She lectured and published on humanities computing, in particular on digital manuscript studies and editing; she has organised conferences and workshops in digital humanities, and is an active member of its international community. She was co-PI in the project ‘Modelling between Digital and Humanities: Thinking in Practice’ funded by the Volkswagen Foundation.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you, in the broadest sense?</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Yes because obviously if I relate it to the work I do, scholarly editions mainly have to do with the process of creating digital resources around primary sources and in the case of a scholarly editions we specifically refer to the fact that these were part of the tradition of critical editing; so rather than indeed taking a text and simply… - we know there are scholarly activities there as well - transcribing it, for example, the idea is instead to critically annotate it and generate or create a text that is supposed to take into account all the sources, the tradition, the connections with previous textual contexts and so on; so that’s the generic understanding I have of scholarly editing. But you mentioned something else, scholarly editing and scholarly editions…? </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yeah, that’s perfect, digital editing and digital editions. </p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Digital editions yeah. That said maybe I can add that already from the beginning, well my beginning, I’ve obviously been working in digital humanities for a while now, it’s been clear from at least early projects that the spectrum of what can be considered digital editions within a digital environment is actually quite wide; so it goes from, if you like, what for example in information studies are normally referred to as access resources that might include indexes or other ways to access the material (not just the reading text) to indeed annotated digital editions with very detailed information about a critical tradition or maybe even the palaeographical analysis to other type of collections that could be considered rather under the label of thematic collections, where you have the text but the text is one element among many others. In this case you may for example have a focus on the entities, historical entities in that textual world, let’s say. So to me it emerged quite early on in the practice of digital editing that with the digital environment you could in a way reappropriate the genre in multiple ways - it’s an interesting opportunity even if sometimes it generates a confusion in terms of conventions and standards associated to scholarly editing and so on, but it definitely opened up that box a bit; yeah maybe that’s an answer for that.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Is that spectrum too wide?</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	I don’t know any more whether the community maybe uses the term, how they use the term, I know for a fact that when I explain… so for example when I do presentations about the lab and the kind of projects we are involved in, I feel, especially if it’s a humanities audience, I feel the need to specify a bit; so yes potentially all of these collections, all these materials, all these resources could generally be qualified as digital editions but, I would add, “let me explain” and then I can go into the different functionalities of this material and explain a bit better; sometimes the focus might be more on the sustainability of a certain project architecture and sometimes it might be more on the actual presentation features, such as particularly rich critical apparatus and how that is being created. So I do realise that I tend to distinguish in principle the digital edition as something where the text is core compared to say, for example, yes, an access resource where you might also have bits of text to support that resource or that you can zoom in but the actual focus of that resource is more on the search and access via indexes, for example, glossaries, dictionaries, biographies. These components might also have an element related to digital editing with respect to the text that they use as evidence or support but yeah I tend to call them access resources. I’m thinking if there is something else that I missed and that I didn’t mention, but those two are definitely the most prominent… oh yeah of course - this point mainly relates to the tradition at King’s [College London, UK] and the fact that I did my humanities computing studies here and that I have a kind of link to the tradition of DH here – there is the fact that historical sources obviously always rely on texts, right, but they rely on texts in different ways and at King’s there has been for example quite a big tradition on data modelling for prosopographies…</p><p>	[disconnected]</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You were speaking about prosopography…</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	So, I was saying there has been a long tradition at King’s about working on data modelling around people and especially for prosopography, can you hear me now?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yes, perfect…</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	What I was saying is that in those contexts as well, obviously the main entry point for those historical resources are not the texts themselves but the specific historical information which then links to the text that supports historical evidence. I would not call those digital editions but it might be that if a project gets expanded the editing on those texts can become more prominent than the original purpose; so this is just to say that again there might be an element of digital editing in other resources as well, that I wouldn’t normally call digital editions.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Those things that you do count as digital editions, what do they well and what might they do better?</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	So, what do they do well, it’s a bit difficult to apply in general terms, I mean in principle I know that some of the best digital edition projects that were funded tend to have teams, editorial teams that are scholarly strong and aware of the text they’re working on so the scholarly work behind that editing is solid. In terms of what digital environment offers that maybe a print one doesn’t, I still fail to see sometimes a really big progress in the sense that, as I think you state in the statement of your project, more often than not the tendency is to stick to some of the conventions of the printed format. Now, that said, there have been some really interesting experiments whether using design and visualisation to allow for, I don’t know, alignment across texts or searching, as I was saying before, detailed apparatus and so on or developing data models that were particularly rich in scope, the availability of the primary sources as images or as facsimiles. We know that in the printed world not only space is an issue but also the possibility of aligning the access and availability of the different manifestations if you like of an edition and the different sources and evidence is an issue. So the digital environment channels that but, that said, it hasn’t been done very systematically across digital editions and what I see as the main blocker is also still this focus on producing and publishing that one digital edition without really, usually, any investment on the infrastructures that support the systems so we tend to then work on a project, maybe do something quite innovative for that digital edition but then there is no funding to support infrastructural components across all those projects. So advancement in digital editing either relies on the expertise that is then able to apply that work say onto yet another project and so kind of build on and refine work previously done, but in terms of the infrastructural investment I think we haven’t really made massive steps. Does that make sense?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	What are the projects that you would point to as exemplars of the practice?</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	This is where I wanted to say before in a way when I replied to your email, I wouldn’t think I’m an expert on digital editions, I’m not up to date with the most recent exemplars but for example one of the… if I think of the moments when digital editing was still one of the focus of my research or at least my horizons more than it is now, I remember being impressed by the Van Gogh digital edition for example, the letters of Van Gogh the painter … I actually did a review for DHQ [Digital Humanities Quarterly] on that. Why was I impressed? Well obviously I was interested in the content - outside my academic interest as a hobby if you like or an interest in that painter in particular - so the content was interesting for me and it was an edition that had a printed and a digital version. To me in general the fact that the same matrix is used to create these two quite different formats is a massive achievement and to see the very high quality products that came in the printed version - because I have that too - and then to see the difference with the digital version and what the digital version could provide was impressive. There were things of course the digital version couldn’t provide - you don’t have the book in front of you, you can’t browse it while sitting on the sofa in the same way and so on, we’re all aware of those things - but for example indeed you could use the digital edition in a very modular way so combining pieces in different ways that you couldn’t obviously do with the printed volumes. All these if you like, these modular elements, the modularity of the edition is made very visible and is very easy for the user to manipulate this modularity. Now you could say these are outdated products in the sense there are now maybe better interfaces that could be implemented and we could have visualisations and so on and we have advanced in some of those areas but to me at the time it was a very novel product and also very cognisant both of the complexity of the editorial model behind it but also of the users in terms of the operations you could do as a user, the kind of awareness you had as a user of the functionalities of the edition. You wouldn’t get lost in the functionalities which is I think more often than not a problem in many of the early digital editions in digital humanities resulting in very niche products where if you know the text and you know the ins and outs you can use it and understand it but if you come as a, I don’t want to say a DH user but maybe another scholar, can’t really get around it, because the interface is very obscure, opaque or very tailored to the scholars that created it without design process in mind. So I think this example struck me as very different in addition to the infrastructure investment put into it. I think that’s another area where things are improving but it would be really good to see more editions that are really user centred if you like. 	So yeah, the Van Gogh and then I could mention some examples I guess from KCL but I don’t know whether, I mean, that’s in a way… I don’t know whether… did Paul talk to you about 'The Values of French’ project for example? I could add the link if he hasn’t.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	No, I don’t believe so…</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	I haven’t worked on this project myself but I know that some of the functionalities especially in this specific project are more focused on the linguistic analysis and how the tools behind the edition supported that analysis and therefore also gave access to the user to explore some of the linguistic elements of it. So now I’m talking more about the, I guess the scholarly elements of what digital editing can support in that sense. And then another interesting recent example is the ‘Community of the Realm of Scotland’. Let me add that too; it has some interesting elements again not only in terms of the data model but also of the interface. So let me have a look here as well so you have it in case you’re interested to look at the details and as I said I haven’t worked on these projects so I know at the high-level what strengths they have and you might want to browse it and have a look to see more in detail.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Thank you, and how do you think we can better sustain projects like these?</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	To me there are two important issues. One is what I mentioned before and so is if you like the mentality of funding and it’s something that I, you as single individuals can’t really do much about except having a kind of political conscience and be ambassadors for our field but it’s about really the type of funding that tends to be, in the digital humanities, very project based and very focused on the specific research case. Well we know obviously that as soon as you move into the digital environment, obviously you have to tailor the architecture, the models to the specific research case study, but you also need to create something that works and is sustainable and therefore that is also scalable to a certain extent. If we continue creating these really nice boutique editions but that after 5 years they become obsolete - because the upgrade for the applications haven’t been made or because, I don’t know, some new exciting visualisation breaks because that specific software is not supported anymore and so on - it becomes very difficult not only to sustain the field in itself but also to acknowledge the contribution we make to these works because there is still a contribution even if the actual public interface might become obsolete. So there is that element of the funding. I think at least in the UK it seems that things are changing a bit, so there is this a sense of urgency for more infrastructural funding and support for teams like ours, for example, or the institutions you come from and Sheffield as well as your project. They aim to support that expertise that creates those environments and is therefore able to sustain them. But yeah, I think there is still a lot to do and maybe again some of these infrastructure projects have been a failure in the past, but I think there is more of an understanding now also from the funders that there is the need of that kind of support that looks beyond the single digital editing project. And then the other element is the people; again it’s kind of related, so the investment to sustain “things” doesn’t rely so much on the most innovative technology or the most innovative tools or the innovative type of libraries and so on but on the expertise and the people that are able to take care of some of those products, they’re able to unpack, retro-engineer sometimes and identify paths to sustainability. Obviously the goal can never be ‘we are going to preserve this thing forever in the state that it is now’ but, with the right experts, we can think of strategies. These vary from, I don’t know, data models that rely on specific standards to, I don’t know, making an archival first approach so that rather than creating a fantastic site which you know in two years you cannot maintain, you maybe go for a static first approach. Other options include complementing these strategies with collections-as-data approaches whereby data deposit and in general making the data available and documented for reuse is key rather than a second thought. So these are some examples but I’m sure they’re could be others to mention but to me the key here is again not so much the technical systems but the people that work with the technical systems, that are aware of those technical systems, if that makes sense.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Yes, perfect sense, thank you. You’re one of the leading scholars on modelling in the digital humanities and you’ve published much on the subject, as well as leading a relevant Volkswagen Foundation project – I wonder if you could speak to your interpretation of the term modelling and give me a sense of the state of the art?</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	It's very flattering what you say, I don’t consider myself such an expert, I definitely think that I maybe played with the term enough to either have become tired of it or for it to actually continue to be a bit of a frustration in a way, because it’s very slippery, but it’s still because of that that it continues to be fascinating to me. So we are now at the stage of actually finishing, well hopefully delivering the manuscript of that project for a book around modelling and I think the core idea is that, basically, it’s more beneficial for a digital humanities context to think of modelling in wide terms. By wide I don’t mean a vague activity; we do modelling anyway in life and all the time- the idea is about seeing this continuum. So modelling applies across those phases in scholarship especially where you take inspiration to structure a space in research - whether it’s a text, a phenomenon, a series of texts, whatever object in the humanities - so from that idea of ok, there may be a concept in the humanities already around, I don’t know what, a certain… I’m not explaining this very well but let me see if I can think of an example… say for example in philology, right, there are concepts in philology that have been studied, discussed and so on and there is already a representation of them, concepts, whether they are diagrams, whether they are descriptions and so on; so modelling, as we intended it in that book and in that work starts already from that conceptualisation - whether such conceptualisations are also available in computational forms or not, it starts from that idea of structuring a certain research space and reducing it. Obviously computational processing is part of some of those activities of reduction, so of taking a complex space of research and identifying, abstracting out some elements of interest, selecting, organising and so on. So operationalisation, computational data models, computational models are part of that process of reduction. What we say is that there are several external representations, several artifacts that are then produced in that process of reduction, in that process of modelling, some are digital, some aren’t and they are still part of the modelling activities. We say also that there is another space where models are… another moment within this act of modelling, where models are produced; so one moment is this production phase and the other one is what, in experimental terms, sometimes is called expansion so when you reintegrate those reductions, say for example of the computational model, into the interpretative framework to understand it. So an example in a digital humanities context may be how you then explain a data visualisation and you interpret it – in doing so you’re re-expanding that space. On one end you reduce, you abstract and you select and then on the other you reintegrate whatever you created in that computational activity, in that specific case, by trying to make sense of it. So I know it sounds very abstract represented this way but we are trying to chart then an idea whereby data modelling is one of the things you do in modelling, but it is inspired and it complements other modelling activities - whether it is sketching, for example, when you’re working on your data models, whether it’s more formal diagrams like entity relations, whether you’re implementing with some code those models, whether you are actually discussing simply with colleagues, with collaborators and creating a new language around that project. So there can be very different types of activity to support this wider container of modelling. I hope that didn’t confuse and made sense.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Complete sense! Do you think that we need to bring modelling processes into edition making in a more explicit manner?</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Yeah I mean this is where again if I refer a little bit to the work of the lab, I know that a concern for the lab, for the engineers and designers especially is that in a way there is a lot of that work that happens anyway. When, for example, if a digital edition is developed, some modelling activity tends to be documented, obviously within that project - might be more or less visible on the digital edition itself - you might have technical overviews or some information about how the data was processed and created and so on, what standards were used and so on but it kind of stays contained there. I think the idea of foregrounding the modelling process would mean actually to look again beyond those single cases and also to reuse or enhance models that are created for one edition into another edition. In our case may be it’s more visible than in another cases because we tend to work on many projects like for example Sheffield as well, so we have these, in a way, opportunities to see the crossings but the infrastructure that our work is based on is still very much linked to a single project workflow. What we would like instead is to be able to have an environment within which we are not only making that modelling process more visible and better documented but also indeed make it shared better across different products or different editions in this case. Just to give you an example, the other day when we were discussing, because we were looking actually at… maybe I shouldn’t publicise that yet until its actually out… but we’re looking at ways to create and to test an environment that would be shared across projects that way and one of the examples that was mentioned was persons models. So again in a digital edition how you model a person might not be the crucial object to model, but in general when you have a digital edition there are entities there and so even if minimal you’d need a model for persons. Obviously, you cannot have the same standard across all projects and so on but in terms then of how that standard is translated into code and so on, these modelling activities tailored to single projects tend to remain a separate development if you see what I mean. The idea of having an integrated environment for you to share those models becomes quite crucial at the level of making that modelling process visible but also indeed with the aim of scaling it up, critiquing it, changing it, adapting it, forking it in more engineering terms and so on.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	If you could cast your mind back to 2009, you published a reflection on the Henry III Fine Rolls Project which produced a digital and printed edition of the Fine Rolls English Monarch’s Reign in the 13th Century. You referred to this project as one that sought to be realised in both print and digital forms as a dual publication. I wonder if you could, a decade later, share some thoughts on the idea of dual publication, on digital editions that exist simultaneously as print and digital?</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	I think I did say; it’s interesting that the example I did mention about Van Gogh is also a dual/hybrid publication. I don’t know; to me there is still a value in doing that (I might be old fashioned though) because I come from a background in book and manuscript studies whereby I’m very aware of the fact that the book is a technology with its strengths and that it still serves a certain purpose, so I’m still a bit reluctant to say ‘oh well, you know, if you have it in digital form why do you actually need the book as well’. I am, yeah, at the moment where I stand now, I am still reluctant to let it go and that’s why I said before, to me, a good digital edition is an edition that also potentially takes into account the possibility of being delivered across different media obviously with again an awareness that you are then not only making a model that needs to be flexible enough to serve very different productions – well, these days, there tend to be more and more convergent production schedules and production processes, but still, different - but also serving different audiences, different users, different conventions and so on. To me it’s still a great value of the digital that it could support that delivery across media. In terms of whether it’s still adopted in a way as a… I’m actually, l must say I don’t know if there have been any statistics or surveys that report on that and how widespread it is. I know that for that specific project it’s definitely something we couldn’t have negotiated - it was there as a requirement from the outset; the historians wanted to have both and I think at the time as well it seemed a really good decision to have made. It was tricky because obviously the requirements are different in different media. In that case there was a publisher that had their own, as I said, production process so we had to adapt to that. It was interesting as well because obviously it affected the way the edition was developed and actually having it from the start was also very good rather than having it at the end. What was interesting in that project was that the historians were mainly thinking in printed form so it was very much, if you like, a epistemological exercise in trying to first of all make the historians reflect on the fact that some of the artifacts of the printed world were not as self-explanatory as they thought they were. So when they would say for example ‘oh yes we just want an index of persons’, we would say ‘ok sorry what do you mean by that?’, ‘oh you know an index of persons’ – ‘but how is that structured? how is that organised? what kind of information?’ Again, for a historian who has made other editions before, who has worked on the material before, these are things that might be kind of self-evident but as soon as you have to - as you know… because I know you also work in this area… - to unpack that and to discuss it and then to potentially change also the way how the printed edition was then proposed after I don’t know how many centuries of using the same format, it was also a fascinating process. We would then see how in the digital environment we could support the connections much better or the richness of those indices and so on was; it was a very interesting process. But yeah, I don’t know about your question whether that’s still really adopted and whether it will still be… I must admit I don’t know. I know that what’s happening more and more and I see it as a good outcome is the fact that, as I said also before, there is now much more the tendency of publishing the data. So for example the Fine Rolls is a great example of ‘great, we have a printed edition, great, we have a good website’ that we are still by the way maintaining ‘but the data wasn’t published’ even if the, let’s say, the digital humanities branch of the project insisted on that. It didn’t seem such a priority nor something that the historians themselves were interested in and it’s only recently in fact after the Kings Digital Lab took that project under its care that the datasets have been made available in a second repository. Now it's much more common to see a digital edition with the downloaded data here and the licences and so on, so that’s definitely a big step forward I think.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	If you were given a magic wand scenario, what would the ideal digital edition of the future look like to you?</p></sp><sp who="#AC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Ah, well definitely ideally it would be interconnected and I know it might sound like a very postmodern term but what I mean here is that it would have the possibility to talk to different kinds of resources and ideally in a dynamic manner. In terms of architecture that might mean a very different thing, it might be a modular approach, I don’t know, but the idea that you are creating an edition that is still siloed and relies on simply that information that you have is I think becoming more and more obsolete. The edition of the future ideally will have no issue, no problem similarly to the IIIF technology to get things from different places and recognising the provenance of those places and those sources and still being able to merge them together in a way or bring them together under the same space while keeping that federation if you like. So I think it will be federated and ideally yes make use of different authorities and therefore also present, even in this space of interconnectedness, present if you like a layered perspective on that text rather than the authorial one. That would always be the challenge, right. So you would be creating a digital edition; ideally you would want to present an authoritative text but we all know that in that digital editing processes the more interesting and innovative part of the work is to bring together multiple pieces – and you know we mean lots of things by pieces, but you know what I mean. So the fact that the digital edition of the future could still bring together all those things and still present if you like an argument, a narrative, a unified environment but at the same time being able to trace these connections and make use of the technical environment in the best way to bring them together rather than to flatten or to lose their specificity and so on would be ideal. But again maybe I have been too abstract in the way I have expressed that.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>