<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Roopika Risam</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan		 on February 9th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_RR.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>ROOPIKA RISAM is Associate Professor of Film and Media Studies and of Comparative Literature at Dartmouth College, where she is part of the Digital Humanities and Social Engagement Cluster. Formerly, Risam was Chair of Secondary and Higher Education and Associate Professor of Education and English at Salem State University. There, she also served as the Faculty Fellow for Digital Library Initiatives, Co-Director of the Viking OER and Textbook Affordability Initiative, Coordinator of the Graduate Certificate in Digital Studies, and Coordinator of the Combined B.A./M.Ed. in English Education. Her research interests lie at the intersections of postcolonial and African diaspora studies, humanities knowledge infrastructures, and digital humanities. Her first monograph, New Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis, and Pedagogy, was published by Northwestern University Press in 2018.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	The terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing, what do they mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	Are you specifically talking about digital or both?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s entirely up to you; if it means explicitly digital then that’s fine…</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	Well it doesn’t, I mean I do believe scholarly editing is not just digital it’s just that digital is the place where I’ve focused because I’m really interested in questions of open access and broad emanation of knowledge and you know the way I think about it also is there are a lot of different philosophies about how one should go about this, this is something that we were encountering recently with my work on Reanimate when we were preparing an edition of the Fredi Washington Reader you know in that case it’s a recovery project I think scholarly editing is very useful for recovery projects in that people don’t necessarily know about the work of this black actress who was also a writer and an activist who wrote columns for many newspapers but the one we focused on was The People’s Voice, a Harlem newspaper and so when we were dealing with editorial process we were dealing with microfilms and scans that were really poor quality we couldn’t even OCR them, we had to manually transcribe them and then she was writing her column for the newspaper from its inception till about five years into its production process and so they didn’t have style guidelines, they didn’t have much consistency so there were a lot of these choices that we were having to make as editors to communicate with the multiple audiences that we were interested in because the scholarly audiences will want one thing, the general reader, the K12 school teacher will want something else and so when we think about the kinds of editorial interventions that we’re making with the text we wanted to preserve her language and her rich voice but at the same time balance that with flagging for a reader where there are infelicities that are largely coming in from their editorial side not necessarily her writing so balancing between that, right and sort of trying to find and construct a philosophy of how you approach a text when editing.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You mentioned framing and you mentioned how you were intentionally thinking about general audiences, do you think that editors in general think enough about the wider public as an audience?</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	I don’t, no, I don’t. I think approaching my work through the fields like African diaspora and post-colonial studies I think those areas tend to probably think a little bit more about, you know, connecting with communities than someone who is doing the edition of Henry James and publishing it with Oxford and they’re really thinking about a different kind of reader. Along those lines you know I was a peer reviewer for the Modern Language Association’s Committee on Scholarly Editing and I did one of the first digital edition reviews for them and they sent me their criteria and they had this, you know maybe it was like four or five pages of a check list wanting comments on everything from face tags, editorial process, framing and just this really extensive list so much of it did not feel like it even applied to the project that I was reviewing and it turned out that they had asked me to review it precisely because they had wanted me to give them feedback on the applicability of the guidelines to a digital edition and when you read their guidelines in particular it’s clear that they’re not thinking about public audiences, they’re only thinking about other researchers.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So, I mean that kind of ties nicely into the politics of knowledge that you write about in your book. I wonder if you could speak to the politics of knowledge that we currently live in, you know, in the context of the world that we live in and the role then that you feel digital editions and publishing play in that politics.</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	Yeah you know I’ve been having conversations in the US, there’s the national archives NARA, they have an arm it’s called NHPRC but it’s basically for historical papers so they got an executive order from the president saying make sure you’re thinking about diversity and because obviously an executive order from the President of the United States is how this works, right so they didn’t know what to do so they set out on a listening tour where they asked me and people who are working in Latino studies, Black studies for our perspective particularly on scholarly editing of historical documents and historical papers and you know what really came out of that was that often the people who are being attracted to their grant programmes and their institutes are people who are already working on canonical figures, right so they have a big partnership with the George Washington Papers who is the first president of the United States and out of that project they’re trying to run a course on scholarly editing and so they came to me and asked if I would consult for them because they wanted to know how do we make our curriculum feel relevant to people working in the areas of research that you care about because I really do think that scholarly editing has a huge role to play in the dissemination of voices that aren’t represented in McKennan but often what happens in the production of texts is that people produce texts about people they already know about and so it’s really this missed opportunity for recovery and so one of the things that I said to them was ‘well let’s think about the kinds of projects you’re using as examples’ and you know, if you want to speak to a broader audience of scholars in fields that are underrepresented in scholarly editing, often they are doing that work but they may not identify with scholarly editing as the term for what they are doing and this is very much like digital humanities right there are people who do the work but they don’t call it digital humanities and so I’ve tried to work with them on how do you talk about what you do in terms of scholarly editing in a way that speaks to people who are interested in Black writing, in Asian writing and in other fields and then relatedly with publishing I think this gets at the core of why Carol Stabile and I started Reanimate which is that when Carol Stabile was writing her book The Broadcast 41 which is about women who are blacklisted under the anti-communist politics of the 1930, ‘40’s and ‘50’s in the United States she had gotten the rights to some writing some of it unpublished in archives by women and women of colour who had been blacklisted and when she published her book she wanted to publish the archival writing by the women and the publishers she spoke to said well there’s no market and there was no market for that because they don’t have a self-evident value because they are people that aren’t really well known and so our project was very much and I said well we could just do it right we could edit it ourselves and just create open access editions and you know we launched the first one last week and we have two more manuscripts already prepared and more ready in the pipeline and so that’s an area where the economies of publishing and I’m sympathetic to that I mean academic presses is what we’re looking at and they operate on shoe string budgets but they very much have to make decisions on what they think is going to be marketable and that pressure of the market ends up being most like it ends up reinforcing whose voices are heard and whose aren’t.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	How do we overcome these inequalities, I mean I know that obviously your work and writing has made significant contributions to the post-colonial digital humanities as a means of reacting to inequalities in digital production the type of which you’re describing, I mean to what extent as I said can we overcome these?</p><p>	Yeah, I mean I think if people are willing to do small projects like the ones we’re doing with Reanimate and get people to know who figures are get people to start teaching them because we’ve made them available, I think that’s a way to potentially generate interest and generate demand. And you know I think two examples in say African American literature where a novel like ‘Their Eyes are watching God’ by Zora Neale Hurston was largely out of print from its publication during the Harlem Renaissance until, I want to say like the late ‘70’s and it was recovered as part of that wave of recovery writing by Black women, scholars in that time period and now that novel is… I mean I read it in High School, right and I taught it in High School for that matter too in both of the schools where I taught and so it has become a staple at the secondary level. And I think that’s often the last time students read novels and so thinking about how we can engage those techniques of recovery and do so using digital tools and connecting with teachers and connecting with the people who are in the position to actually use those texts, that’s the hardest part though, right. I mean it’s not super easy to create an edition, right and I mean I’ve done like the Harlem Shadows project was a TEI edition which was very different than doing Reanimate which is not TEI on purpose but at the same time once you have it out there you know and somebody is paying for the hosting and the server then you know people can access the text and we can generate interest that way because I think the problem is that we can’t necessarily rely on being able to make an argument to publishers that they should invest in something that they don’t think that there’s a potential market for so very much it’s a grass roots approach, right. But then the other side of that is of course there’s material that you know we’re not going to recover that’s not going to be recoverable that isn’t even accident there are limitations to recovery is what I’m saying and there’s also finite amounts of time and labour.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Reanimate isn’t TEI by choice, why is that?</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	I don’t know, I have mixed feelings about TEI, when Chris Forster and I did the Harlem Shadows project it was very much, you know, we were graduate students and in Digital Humanities and knew TEI is a thing you had to do and we wanted to see if there was a way to create… wait for this one… quick TEI editions and we concluded… two years later like… So we made this edition, it gets used, it gets taught, it’s a good edition so when Carol and I were working on Reanimate we really had a lot of conversations about whether we wanted to do TEI or not and you know we decided when we thought about the readership we were trying to reach both the scholarly audience, but the scholarly audience is essentially looking for archival sources and K12 teachers or High school teachers particularly in the US who are looking to diversify their curriculum it was additional labour without real pay off. I think on the side of the scholarly audience in many ways I think it would have been easier to have TEI as an edition because then we could really deal with some of the challenges that we were encountering with the editing of the text but largely because it was already print and we weren’t working with manuscripts with handwritten emendations we just decided ‘do you know what, we’re not going to bother’ which does limit usability, right, so there’s a trade-off but again there’s also a finite amount of time and labour. But I’m not anti-TEI I think there’s a lot of value in it, I feel like Elisa Beshero-Bondar who does the Digital Mitford has really shown me the value of TEI particularly in terms of tagging so that you could then query the document but I mean thinking about our audience it’s not really what the audience who’s going to be looking at the Fredi Washington Reader is going to want to do, you know, so it just felt like if we were going to do TEI it was performative to do TEI and not because that was what the audiences were looking for or really needing.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You’ve worked on a staggering number of digital projects, many of which might be considered editions – I’m thinking about things like The Global Du Bois, your Caribbean keywords project and of course Torn Apart / Separados – do you see these as digital editions?</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	I don’t, maybe I have a limited definition of digital edition I think of Harlem Shadows, I think of Reanimates projects as digital editions, I’m trying to think about anything else I think about as digital editions, I think if you were to ask me about what I have done that are digital editions those are the two projects that I would mention. I wouldn’t with the others which is actually really interesting about why, right, I suppose in a way they’re a digital rendering of knowledge but I think I really connect digital edition with the textual editing tradition right and I mean Global Du Bois is a data visualisation project and so I very much think of that differently Torn Apart / Separados is data visualisation and I very much think about the digital edition as a project that’s about working with text and representation of texts and access to the text as created by someone else versus these other projects where there’s a lot of kind of like data aggregation, data collection, data generation, curation and that for me is a pretty hard and fast boundary in my thinking.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That’s interesting. When you’re developing a project like Torn Apart / Separados, what are the key things that you as a lead investigator think about in terms of how the project is structured, how it’s designed, are there key aspects that you always look to?</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	Yeah I would actually say so in my thinking regardless of what the outcome is, whether it’s a digital edition or a data visualisation project my thinking is largely always the same which is what’s the problem, what’s the research, what’s the question, you know, what’s the intervention that there is to be made there and it doesn’t mean that whatever the question or problem or intervention that is articulated at the beginning of a project is actually ends up being the focus of the project but that’s sort of the starting point in the thinking. So with Reanimate it was, well the publishers don’t want to publish these texts - how can we do it ourselves with Torn Apart / Separados it was, you know, what can we do to intervene in this governmental policy and these separated families and children and so then the methodologic choices come out of the question of then what methods help get closer towards answers or modelling representation of the problem. And so in the case of Torn Apart / Separados its data visualisation and it’s obviously also not as linear as that, right, it’s a lot more recursive and iterative because with Torn Apart it was like well what’s the data then, is data the right way to go, turns out it was, great, like let’s go forward and then we hit a problem, let’s go back a little and so that’s my process and so really for me the method is not predetermined, the method comes out of what do we need to solve the problem or further explore the research question.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you feel that that project had an impact, that it made an intervention?</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	Oh yeah on multiple levels I mean I think one which was our immediate goal which was try and get the word out that we have this data about the locations of the children so that we can actually give it to social workers and lawyers who were working with families who were separated and we were able to do that and that was great. Then the other impact I think it had was to show that there are other ways that digital humanities’ methods can respond to current events and you know part of that, it was part of the Nimble Tents Toolkit which included the mapathon in response to hurricane Maria in Puerto Rico and then there are some other methods in that tool kit as well so you know it was very much about expanding that repertoire of ways that we can use our methods to respond to crises. And then I think another impact that was unintended was that often in the US people think about immigrant detention as something that happens at the border or at points of entry as opposed to something that is so all around us and when you actually see for example that you know and this is a colleague had an experience finding out from looking at the data visualisation that she was biking past an immigrant detention centre on her way to work and she had no idea, right and so that kind of awareness of you know how immigrant detention is really part of the full landscape and not just geographically localised to the borders or to points of entry was also I think a big impact. So it was really these multiple measures right it was the people we were intending to reach, it was people we weren’t intending to reach and it was also this trying, which we wanted to do, which was show look we have all these skills and maybe we can think about how we can mobilise them to respond in times of crisis.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I know you’re part of the Global Outlook::Digital Humanities group on minimal computing, what role do you think minimal computing can play in the future of digital editing and publishing?</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	You know I think for example that Ed a Jekyll theme that Alex Hill developed is a good example of minimal computing or minimal edition and I think this goes back to the question of the tension between TEI or no TEI because Ed is definitely not TEI friendly and that’s not its intention right it’s very much about the visual, the quote unquote clean reading and also the many ways about trying to avoid a database, trying to think about accessibility in low bandwidth environments through static texts and I mean it’s interesting you know, we’re working on a special issue of minimal computing right now that should be out this year. I’m trying to think how many of the projects were really digital editions, a couple of them were and I think that there’s… I’m of two minds about it because on the one hand I think that minimal computing has a lot of possibilities in terms of access and also using existing technologies and repurposing them in ways that avoid having to reinvent the wheel or making a large capital investment in the development of a new platform, on the other hand the amount of technical knowledge one has to acquire to be able to actually work in say something like Jekyll is not insignificant and so for me that was really the first time minimal computing was really the first time I was working command line, fortunately I had really strong knowledge of CSS and so really it was about… like I understood the directory structures and things like that, the fundamentals of computation I understood and so it was really about what are the commands I need to put in the command line, ok fine, it’s not hard for me knowing CSS but if you’re someone coming to it not understanding directory structures, not understanding fundamentals of computation, not having any knowledge of CSS or SASS, I can imagine that it would be very difficult and there are also people who have really strong technical skills who find this really hard, it just so happens that I don’t but I don’t have a lot of other technical skills that they have so it’s really about the challenge being the investment and the start-up learning curve for technologies for people who don’t know them. It works best and this is what we’ve been arguing is that the person who really benefits from these technologies is actually not necessarily the individual scholar creating the edition but the person in a staff or administrative position who is managing multiple projects with multiple scholars right and so if you are charged with supporting fifty projects and they’re all on WordPress then it’s fifty projects where you’re constantly dealing with security issues, updates, updates breaking the theme or breaking the plugins and really with something like Ed as a digital edition with Jekyll all you need to worry about is are your RubyGems up to date and then occasionally there are conflicts to deal with but if you’re dealing with multiple projects it actually ends up being a labour saving but that only comes on that back of a start-up learning curve investment in the first place.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	That all makes sense. So, magic wand scenario, what would the future of digital editing and publishing look like to you?</p></sp><sp who="#RR"><speaker>RR</speaker><p>	A giant bag of money?! I mean really it’s the time and the labour right and the cost of the time and labour that to me is what gets in the way of seeing a future in which we have greater access to texts by women, by women of colour, by men of colour whose writing is there but is just not well known, isn’t read, being part of scholarly conversations, isn’t being taught, you know, if we’re really going to realise these lofty goals of the democratisation of the internet, of building a digital cultural record of humanity then… and I mean I’m sure you know my work so you know what I’m going to say which is that the danger here is that if we aren’t thinking about strategies for increasing editorial work in those areas then we’re just going to have 9,000 editions of William Blake and Walt Whitman, right.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>