<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Patrizia Rebulla</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  Michael Kurzmeier	 on March 11th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_MK_PR.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>Patrizia Rebulla is editor/project manager of Mozartiana.org, an online, annotated edition of Mozart’s letters. She is the former creator and editor of The Letters of Casa Ricordi.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	What do the terms scholarly edition and scholarly editing mean to you?</p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	I mean mainly annotated editions, offering the user, besides the notes, a robust searching apparatus, across different sources of information and in different formats, such as written, visual, maps, dictionaries, etc.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. And in that context, do you see anything that digital editions do well? </p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	They allow users to go beyond linear form. I mean you read a book from cover to cover and so the direction of information, the structure of the information is totally determined by the author of the book, while in a digital edition there is no such thing like the centre of information, and each user can get through a website according to where and how one delves into a given page, and from there continue to surf.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. And then I’ve seen that you are the Project Manager for The Letters of ‘Casa Ricordi’. And I was wondering if you could tell us a little bit about that project?</p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	Yes. I left the project since, but it was just one month so I am still familiar with the project. Casa Ricordi has an impressive archive of some 600,000 letters. They are not all digitised, but some 34,000 originals are completely digitised. I say originals because the others are copy letters. The originals are mainly received letters with a few sent letters from and to different composers, publishers, theatre managers, librettists. They let people have a first-hand feeling about what was the relation between a publisher, who is a cultural organiser but also a commercial entrepreneur and his network of relations. Some 10,000 letters are now transcribed because we launched a call and volunteers responded with unbelievable enthusiasm. The text is fully searchable and people, places and musical works - if and where possible- are identified and linked to the data base. The database itself is connected to Wikidata. This will give an impressive power of information to the whole thing because the letters mention a number of less known persons and works that are not commonly found around as a first-hand source.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	You just mentioned the enormous scope of the project with 600, 000 letters...</p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	Which is so enormous that no one can imagine they will be all digitised. Also, it would be a waste of money and time because many of them are invoices or complaint letters or whatever but, yes, it remains true that they are held in the vaults. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Was there an initial scoping or at least a rough categorisation of materials and then the decision to focus on maybe only transcribing letters first and invoices second?</p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	No. Imagine that what is in the vaults are the copybooks, as I said, so the copy letters of what for more than a hundred years had been sent from the publishing house to the rest of the world. This is why we focused on the original letters received from composers, authors, politicians, journalists, critics, entrepreneurs or whatever. These 34,000 had been completely digitised and these are the object of transcription. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you. And then maybe to broaden that question, so when you think back to the origins of the project, are there key design decisions that come to mind? </p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	To put at the user’s disposal the real text of transactions: Ricordi was founded in 1808, thus in a period where you didn’t have telephones and all the businesses were run by written pieces of paper and these could make people understand how the business was run. Ricordi was a commercial firm in the cultural field, and because you cannot order by decree to have success this is a complicate and delicate business. I mean that you cannot order someone to write a Traviata and for that Traviata to be a success. Sometimes it is and sometimes it is a flop such as – say – Jurassic Park – so you spend a lot of money and nevertheless can get a terrible fiasco, as it happened at the beginning of Puccini’s career, of all the people and to name only one. Our goal was to give scholars and users the opportunity to read, face-to-face, directly, without intermediaries what were the discussions between Guilio Ricordi and Puccini or Verdi or other artists, and also give them a view of the balance sheet, since we published also the full transcription of the proceedings of the Board Committee. the Ricordi archive is pretty rare, I mean there are not so many archives of this kind around, this is why we thought it was very useful for the cultural world to see the business from behind the stage. The transcriptions are fully part of this project, because you need to be able to follow the conversations. This is the same principle behind another project I’m running, which is the complete annotated edition of Mozart’s letters, still in its infancy.</p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Thank you and is there anything that you would do differently if you were to do the project again? </p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	Not really, I mean the users tell us they find it simple, which is good, I like simple websites. Users say they find things, they find a good trove of information, although the Ricordi team still need to add details about persons, places and musical works or annotations, but this is simply due to the lack of resources.  These are long projects, that demand a lot of time and resources. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	That’s great, thank you and maybe one more question about the project then, you mentioned a lot of the transcription was done by the public. Did you expect that to go so well?</p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	No. We were overwhelmed by the response. As usual 10% of people do 90% of the work, so now there is this small group of people, very loyal, very trustable, that transcribed an impressive number of letters. They were not necessarily experts in the field, so when they started, some errors occurred but very quickly they improved their performance, and the transcriptions are now usually extremely well done. What could be critical is to recognise the name of an unknown soprano or an orchestra conductor. Also, the letters are usually in Italian and so the response came from Italians (or at least Italian speakers). At some point, we tried to join Zooniverse, a project run by the University of Oxford. The test went extremely well, since the pilot was found well done, well described and whatever, but in the end, it was impossible to run it because of the language. This is of course a problem. The letters are manuscripts and very often they are horrible manuscripts, really horrible to read. This is why we are so admirative of our volunteers, they in not much more than one year, say a year and a half transcribed 10,000 letters! And this happened without any particular advertising or publicity or whatever. We simply added a caption next to each holograph ‘do you want to transcribe this?’ and this was the end of it. We barely advertised it so that means that people discovered the website by chance, and they answered simply because they like to transcribe, this is really amazing. We discovered through a poll that they were not particularly interested into music or into the topic nor the history or whatever, they simply like to transcribe, which is amazing. This was a surprise. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Great to hear. Thinking about the wider field of digital scholarly editing and publishing, is there something that you believe the field is missing at the moment? Is there some development that you would really like to see in terms of digital editions?</p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	Maybe we are in a moment of crisis, aren’t we? One of the main problems I see is that many funded projects ask you to find a new technical development that would be reused by anyone. And since this is the rationale of each call, no project reuses anything already done, although they are well done and could perfectly serve your purpose, so you have to slightly reinvent the wheel in technical terms to get funded, but you are never funded for the substance of work, I mean to annotate and/or transcribe the letters and create a robust database. Let’s consider the new project of Mozart’s letters I’m running:  the letters are annotated by the musicologist with whom I’m running the project, and I put them online and create the database of persons, places and musical works. To do that you would virtually need infinite resources. I mean either you are funded, or you need to have time. I say that without joking, we are doing this because I’m 70, my scholar is 71, we are both retired, we have a lot of passion, and we are doing that mostly out of passion. In our old days we would have never had the time to undertake such a project. It’s so detailed, it’s fully annotated such as a normal scholar book, but on top of this it is linked to a large, crowded database, full of details and titbits of information, each of which needs to be carefully checked and cross referenced with all the others. This is not a thing that people your age have time and resources and money to do. To run a good scholar project you need a lot of time and resources and I have the impression that universities are getting through a big crisis because they need funds to go ahead with ordinary teaching and research, and you cannot have fundings for the content on all the projects, transcribing lots of letters, translating lots of letters, adding information, adding the notes, adding visualisations, adding topographical maps or whatever, and yeah this is a big problem. </p><p>  As you see this website <!--[Mozartiana.org]--> again is very simple but please consider the kind of information you can access to, persons, senders, receivers, places, Mozart’s works in different orders, other people works, iconography, sources, bibliography. If you get through chronology and take a given letter, you can see where the plus of a digital edition is: where for example the text says ‘we arrived at our hotel, at our inn’, if we know what hotel it was, we can not only mention it – as we would do in a normally printed edition in a footnote – but we can also link it to the real place, and if we know who the owner was of the inn we can also connect the text to  this guy. This creates a network of searchable annotations that greatly increases the ease and clarity of reading. The letters are (well: will be, in the near future) completely annotated, and persons, places and musical words are all identified. They are also cross referenced to other letters or to bibliography or to places, that also say where this place was, was it under the Holy Roman Empire, or elsewhere etc., and if you get through persons and follow the thread of cross-referencing you can get a picture of the relations’ network. Say you get through London and see that someone is mentioned because he gave a concert there, and following his thread you land to another place etc etc etc., and again you can have a picture of the relations between persons, musical works, letters, places, and then – of course – you can connect your data with Wikidata, use linked data and other tools. This is in my opinion a scholarly, annotated edition. </p></sp><sp who="#MK"><speaker>MK</speaker><p>	Maybe just to throw it in there, is there any thought about the long-term preservation of these projects? Because they do need better infrastructure and maintenance. </p></sp><sp who="#PR"><speaker>PR</speaker><p>	Yes, you are right, this is a big problem and probably it’s also due to the form of funding because when funding is finished nothing will assure that you can get your project up and running, updated, that you can migrate it to a new platform so that it may be read also in the future, and this is a big problem. While of course, we know that book is a book, so preservation of a book is much simpler. This is probably one of the biggest problem.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>