<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>C21 Editions:  Andy Campbell</title><title type="sub">Interview conducted by  James O’Sullivan	 on January 20th, 2022</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Unpublished working draft</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl> O'Sullivan, J., M. Pidd, M. Kurzmeier, O. Murphy, and B. Wessels.
                            (2023). <title>Interviews about the future of scholarly digital editions
                                [Data files].</title> Available from <ref target="https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions">https://www.dhi.ac.uk/data/c21editions</ref> (File C21_JOS_AnC.xml downloaded: 8th June 2023).</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>Retagged in TEI P5 from RTF (via soffice and docxtotei) </p></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>$today</date>Header added</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div><head>Interviewee bio</head><p>ANDY CAMPBELL is the Founder, Co-Director, and Lead Developer of Dreaming Methods. His work as a digital artist combines literature, gaming and immersive technologies spanning over 20 years and has won many international awards. He is the Digital Director of arts organisation One to One Development Trust. Andy speaks and presents about Digital Fiction internationally but is equally experienced in working with hard-to-reach communities including with young people.</p></div></front><body><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	You might just talk us through the work that you do? Do you see your work as digital fiction, video game development, both of these, something else?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	That’s an interesting one. I don’t know. I think at one point it bothered me that I didn’t know what that was called or exactly what it was called but it doesn’t bother me anymore because I sort of cross over so many different things, so I’d say that in terms of the literature stuff that I do I tend to use the term digital fiction. Digital fiction is something that I’ve been using since the late 90’s, I actually registered digitalfiction.co.uk in about 1999 and it just seemed to be the most appropriate thing to what I felt I was doing particularly at the time but that’s quite a long time ago now and I think things have changed.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And do you see the things that you create as texts? Do you appreciate how other people, be they scholars, readers, or critics, might see them as texts?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	I think that they tend to have a text element so I don’t know, I mean, if you imagine somebody coming at it they might describe it as a reading experience or something that they would read so ‘have you read this work?’ or ‘I’m going to read this work’ even if there is actually not that much text in it or text is just part of the mix but I don’t know I’ve ceased to worry about what exactly these things are and that’s eased my conscience on them, it’s sort of made me less worried about making them, it just doesn’t matter to me what they are exactly whether they’re literature or not, they’re just digital works that incorporate all kinds of different elements to varying degrees.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	One of the things that you mentioned there was this idea of reading experience… As a practitioner, do you think explicitly about how your work might be accessed or read? Do you think about it from an interface perspective, from a reader’s perspective?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Well, I mean that’s interesting and that ties into where I started developing work from which was basically publishing through Flash and on the web and I think since Flash has disappeared, I feel personally like my work has gone over the place in lots of different directions in order to try to find new audiences or reach new audiences. I think we’re starting to get back in the last few years I feel like there’s a return to that sort of route to publish work out there that to me Flash was always … obviously you had to have the Flash plug in but it was installed on most browsers and you sort of got that ubiquitous experience mostly across the board during the early days but I think we’re sort of slightly returning to that a little bit now with technologies like WebGL where you can have an experience that loads up fairly quickly and it’s accessible on browsers and it strips out that need to know is it a mobile device, is it a Mac, is it a PC, as long as it’s a browser and it’s a fairly modern browser then whatever it is, it should work.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I’m glad you mentioned Flash, we’ll come back to that in a moment, but I wonder if first you might describe your Curios project?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Digital Fiction Curios is an experimental project, it was born out of an idea to try and kind of restore some old Flash works at a time when we knew that Flash was going to disappear from most modern browsers but also to try to find a way to make it interesting to audiences who were used to much more modern tech and you know find a unique way to archive it as opposed to just putting up a website that perhaps emulated Flash or had a sort of search box and key words and little thumbnails and stuff, you know, how could we make it exciting, how could we make older Flash work some of which were about two decades old actually quite interesting and younger audiences. We’ve also been doing a lot of work outside of digital fiction on virtual spaces and virtual museums so this idea of combing that technology with preserving Flash works in VR was a very interesting discussion. So, we talked about that several years ago with Alice Bell from Sheffield Hallam who co-curated Curios and she found some funding for us from Sheffield Hallam, it wasn’t a massive amount but it was enough to just get Curios off the ground and to prototype whether we could do it and yeah that was enough to allow us to make a very small space where we could test whether we could get Flash working in VR. And we were trying to come up with a concept because in our wider work a lot of the sort of virtual museum stuff that we’d done was kind of like trying to mimic physical spaces I guess at the time, you know, so if you imagine what a virtual gallery or a virtual museum might look like it was very much mirrored on the physical sense of the gallery or a museum space and we thought that was a bit out of scope for Curios so we came up with the idea of a Curiosity shop so keeping it all very limited so that very much fits in with Dreaming Methods quite quirky projects certainly the early stuff is very quirky and quite dreamlike and weird and fitting it into that kind of environment just seemed really appropriate so we sort of made a lot out of the environment as well as the restoration of the works. But of course, this was done when VR was evolving so it was a PC based VR experience and I mean things have shifted on with VR since then even though obviously PC experiences are among the best because you’ve got the power of the PC. But yeah, it was a very interesting experience, and it was a very interesting project in the fact that we weren’t sure whether it would happen or not whether we could actually do it. </p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think of Curios as a critical or a scholarly edition?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Not particularly no. I think of it as a sort of digital archive because that’s what it is, there is a lot of material on there that’s old, you know, it’s based on old stuff and it’s in a way it’s a bit like accessing any other type of archive but in a different way, in a slightly different way where you can actually pick objects up and examine them in your hands, you can interact with Flash works really close up as if they’re huge, it’s like experiencing Flash in IMAX or something they’re massive, you know, huge works and I think one of the most interesting things or exciting things for me which we’ve not really had the chance to explore was the fact that we were putting Flash inside a sort of a wrapper of another technology and seeing Flash in a very different light. So, for instance you could apply Flash effects or Flash movies to three dimensional objects or apply different kinds of lights modes and things to them to make them do spectacular things and it was just like taking the seed of something from the past and reigniting it, you know, and that was really exciting but like I mean that’s the part of it in a way that we didn’t really get the chance to explore because it was just a prototype.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I wonder if you could talk through why it is that you chose the methodology that you did? I think it’s interesting that you have constructed this archive as something creative – it is an archive, but it is also a creative thing in itself.</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Yeah, that was a very deliberate thing. I mean, the idea was to make a kind of digital fiction out of all digital fiction, so it is a little bit of a story in itself. I mean there’s a few things in there that we planted purposely to give that little prototype as much scope as we could. So, for instance there’s a VR Headset in there which is quite strange because you’re already wearing one but if you pick the VR Headset up and put it on it takes you into like mini-interpretations of all the Flash works as if we’d made them today sort of thing and that was quite a fun idea so we went down lots of different routes really and milked it as much as possible, I guess. But yeah, I mean the whole thing was designed to be a little experience in itself an atmospheric, you know, tiny piece of storytelling was sort of meta in a way, you know, sort of very self-reflective of where we’ve come from, I guess.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And is this a methodology – thinking about archives in a more creative way – one which should be replicated elsewhere?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Well, I mean it was quite interesting actually putting that project out I mean a lot of people probably couldn’t access it that well because it was PC and VR only so particularly at the time it was released that was quite a difficult to set up for a lot of people to have but there was a very, very positive reaction places like Facebook and a lot of people were saying this is a really unique take on an archive we’ve not seen anything like this before, you know, is this something that might happen more in the future and we had a really, really good response from the British Library who were very interested in what we were doing and actually invited us to do a talk to their staff about how we were doing it. So it had a lot of different sort of mini bits of impact when it was, I say released, I mean it’s sort of released, I mean it is a prototype so it’s not exactly a commercial bit of kit, bit of software but you know it didn’t do too bad I mean it certainly opened our eyes to a lot of options that we had, a lot of different directions.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think that as VR tech and these things become more accessible, particularly from an economic perspective, these models become more scalable? You mentioned you were able to build a prototype from funding from Sheffield Hallam and my understanding is that you’re currently trying to get funding to roll this into something bigger. Not everyone would have access to high end VR tech and the PCs and hardware required to run something like this – do you think that’s changing? Can you see a future where a methodology like this is more scalable, more sustainable, more reproduceable, more accessible?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Yeah, I think that VR is one of those things that you could put into the mix of platforms rather than it being an end point. I mean our approach as an organisation is never really just designed for one platform or it certainly isn’t since just before Curios, we were always very interested in trying to target lots of different platforms so if we were to create something like Curios in the future, we would not just be targeting VR, we would not just be targeting PC, we would also be looking to getting that onto mobile phones and having it as a mobile experience so you could access it from lots of different points. That’s the technology that we’ve really been looking at and have developed our own path through since Curios so if I was to come at Curios again, I would be doing it very, very differently. But I think VR is an important part of the mix I think obviously immersive tech is serious you know so it’s one of the paths that we’re definitely very interested in and working a lot in at the moment but we never think of it as the end point really or a unique just the one place to put things.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	And of course you mirrored a physical space, a curiosity shop – what was the thinking behind that?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	That’s interesting, I mean one of the things about VR is it’s very easy to… I think particularly for people who are new to VR if you go into an experience that’s very abstract or very out there it can be very disorientating. If you suddenly put a headset on and you’ve got no ground beneath you for instance or you’ve got all these floating bits around you, you’ve got no sense of where you are and what you’re supposed to be doing so the idea was to ground people at first in something that felt like they were stepping into another dimension so it was like another room that existed in the same space, so they’d put their headset on and it would just be like ‘I’ve just stepped into another different room’ except it's got these odd physical properties in it that can’t really exist. So you introduce these tiny little bits of kind of almost like mini impossible things, I don’t know, there’s a glass bottle with floating words in it, little lost words, there’s crystal spheres with kind of like floating bits of text in that would be very difficult to make in real life as it were, so you’re grounding somebody and then once you’ve grounded them then you can start taking them to places that are a little bit more… remove the walls I guess is one way to put it and start getting a bit more ambitious. So that was the idea then of the headset in the shop in the Curiosity shop there’s a headset you put that on and it’s almost as if you’re stepping one layer deeper and we started to sort of, you know, transport the reader or the user into like different spaces that were a little more ambitious so big, wide-open spaces with all sorts of crazy things going on, so I think that first step into something that just isn’t mega disorientating was a really important one.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	A lot of your earlier work would have been in Flash. As a practitioner, do you think about how scholars may want to create critical editions of your work?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Not really.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I’m guessing that you try to keep pace with the general feel of digital fiction and what’s going on in the community, what your contemporaries might be creating?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	I try to do; I think that’s an interesting one though because I feel like in a way there are lots of overlaps where this sort of work is happening and actually when you say electronic literature community, I see a hell of a lot of stuff happening in the games industry areas that you know overlap into this where there’s individuals and teams and organisation creating all sorts of incredible stuff that never even goes anywhere near the electronic literature organisation or groups you know. So, it’s odd, I don’t think just being aware of this kind of community, assuming we’re talking about the same one, you know is where to keep your eye, you need to keep your eye much wider you know there’s all kinds of bits of work happening all over the place but yes, I’d like to think that I try to stay aware of what is happening generally.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Why do you think there aren’t more scholarly and critical editions of born digital fiction?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	I’m not sure really, I think it’s probably quite a tricky thing to analyse or to talk about sometimes, it can be difficult to categorise, you might wonder which field you’re actually writing about because it’s a meld of quite a few. I’ve never actually thought that there was particularly a shortage of articles and stuff about this type of work, I always feel in a way to be honest that there’s more talk about this work than there are actually bits of work.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	I’d agree, yes...</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	There’s too much talking and not enough doing you know.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	But in terms of critical editions, sorry, I should have clarified what I meant… Take for example, your piece, All the Delicate Duplicates. I teach that piece in my Digital Fiction class, and I often think it would be wonderful to have a critical edition of it, that is, an edition that makes the work available to students, to readers, to other scholars, but is also accompanied with the kind of things that you would get from a critical edition, things like critical introductions, commentary, basically things that make the text more intellectually accessible. Why is no one creating critical editions of the works of Andy Campbell or anybody else in your space for that matter?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	So are you saying that why is nobody doing that outside of academic institutions because I’m sure… isn’t Dene Grigar doing that kind of thing? Or wasn’t she doing that sort of thing… collecting?</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Quite true, she and Stuart Moulthrop have done some wonderful work, but they are the exception…</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Yeah, I mean I don’t know, that could be again to do with you know the relative sort of... like way that this work can be thought of as a bit obscure or perhaps a little bit too towards the fringes. I mean if you think of something like, I don’t know, a mainstream game like Half-Life: Alyx for instance, mega big VR game, there is on STEAM an electronic book about that game that you can download and there’s interviews with people, there’s articles, there’s 3D models, it’s all the sort of construction work of how that’s been put together and it’s on sale and that’s being commented on STEAM by people who just really love the game who are very, very interested at looking at something that represents a deconstruction of that game in a very interesting and interactive way and we’re talking about people who probably wouldn’t have a clue what electronic literature was or digital fiction was, they don’t think about that they think it’s a book by Valve and it’s going to be awesome because it’s by Valve you know and it’s about something that they like and that they can understand and they’ve played and it is storytelling, that’s exactly what’s going on, so I think it’s to do with perception maybe or accessibility or those sort of… I mean it does help having those sort of amazing production standards as well, that polished you know exciting something or other to hook onto and I think sometimes with this type of work it doesn’t feel very exciting, to the average Joe it probably isn’t that exciting really.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you worry that your Flash works will be lost to future generations?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	No because 90% of them are actually now accessible on the website so there’s only about 3 or 4 works that don’t work and I’m just waiting for the technology to arrive to be able to just power a few extra things behind the scenes that will bring them back, so I think I’m not too worried about it at all. I think that it’s very disappointing that Flash disappeared under such unpleasant circumstances I think, it was a bit scapegoated I’d say really, Flash, and also, I think it was a bit stupid of Adobe not to actually come up with a proper sort of emulation or replacement or fund something like that which they could have done quite easily. I think, I don’t know, I mean there’s lots of reasons why that didn’t happen and they’re mostly to do with money and different industries than what we’re talking about now but I’m not too worried about the work being lost because like I said I’ve restored practically every bit of it I just don’t talk about it much I just do it quietly because I consider that to be part of what I should be doing, keeping up with the technology, you know, if my platform is suddenly whipped out from under me that’s tough shit there’s nothing I can do about it I just need to find a solution to it and get it back again in whatever way.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	It's refreshing to see that you, as a digital artist, are very conscious of sustainability and preservation in that way which I would suggest isn’t the norm…</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Right.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Would you agree?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	I think Flash was a bit of sort of a plateau for a lot of artists because Flash was quite an accessible platform for artists to be able to create work and I think there was a little bit of a sort of ‘ooh we’re going to have to move to HTML5 or something like that to get out of this’ and I think people like Alan Bigelow got there very well, there are a lot of other people that got there very well Jason Nelson, I mean I could spout lots of names from the community but it was a shift and I think it was a muddled shift for a lot of people at first and I certainly flayed around a little when that happened thinking where do I go, what do I do now? I’ve got this amazing freedom to do all these projects, lots of different media and I feel like I can realise what I want to realise but if that disappears how am I going to do that anymore? So yeah I think it befuddled quite a lot of writers and artists in the field and I think it is very, very important that it is taken on board that that is part of what you’re going to have to do, keep up with the tech in a way or keep your work… almost like keep your work never finished, it’s never actually finished it’s always just a constant flow and to think of it that way and to not necessarily think that that’s a bad thing, so be prepared to go back even if it’s I mean we’ve been working with stuff twenty-one, twenty-two years old, we’re still willing to go back to make sure that still runs even though we might be using Flash pro on a 4K monitor that you need a magnifying glass… I’ve got a new prescription because of that (laughs). Do you know what I mean though, you’re dealing with old software that’s like microscopic now, very cumbersome, really annoying, hasn’t been updated for like a decade but you know, if you have to do it, you have to do it and it’s worth it in the end because your work gets out there and you can still view it.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	Do you think about that from a material perspective? What are the consequences of that kind of remediation on your work, the fact that something designed to be experienced on a legacy system changes as you remediate it across different screens and platforms?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Well it depends what you consider to be emulation, if I was wanting to look at something in a very pure way and actually play something through Flash Player then I would be looking at one of these technologies that superimposes you into an older computer or a Sandbox machine or conifer or something like that whereas I think technologies like Ruffle there’s a couple of others as well that convert pretty much or interpret a shockwave Flash file, they’re in some ways not really emulating it, they’re actually enhancing it. There are things you can do with Flash files through technologies like Ruffle that you couldn’t do very easily with Flash, there are lots of layers underneath that you can access. So it’s quite interesting, I wouldn’t in a way class that as emulation, I mean it sort of is but it’s also with benefits.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	So given a magic wand scenario, unlimited resources, technologies both real and imagined, what would the future Curios look like?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	Well I mean if the larger Flash virtual museum project comes off we’ll be able to find out and I think that will be partly a journey to be honest so I’m not sure I can exactly answer the question off the bat because a lot of the time when we do stuff we don’t exactly know what the end result is going to be because the technology moves so fast it’s not worth making those decisions now, make it when you’ve got the money and timescale and you know what’s coming out, you know the road map of various technologies and where they’re going to be a the time but saying that, I could project and say that basically Curios would be something you would be able to access off a QR code, you would be able to run it on your smartphone and you would use the gyroscope to look around that virtual space and you would be able to look at Flash works that are knocking’ on a little bit now and play them and view them, experience them and you’d be able to do that on practically any platform I think really. Might miss out Chromebooks because I don’t like Chromebooks but maybe not.</p></sp><sp who="#JOS"><speaker>JOS</speaker><p>	This idea that technology moves so fast, do we just need to accept that we’re going to lose an awful lot of this work?</p></sp><sp who="#ANC"><speaker>AC</speaker><p>	I don’t know whether we would lose it, I think that’s not necessarily about things moving so fast it’s more probably about conversations not happening to be honest. I mean one of the things about this new project that we’re putting in for is to work with other writers who may not have a clue how to restore their work or get it working again and I think it’s just about opening up that dialogue. It annoys me sometimes, certainly with this community that there’s not enough talking to other artists that are actually doing stuff, you know, I personally feel pretty remote in that I just get on with my stuff and just do my own thing but it would be nice to have those conversations to join things up a little bit more, you know, they’ve got a lot of expertise to give, I’m sure there’s a lot of expertise out there that I could benefit from, it would be nice to have a bit more sense of inclusion and I don’t know, friendliness or sort of, I don’t know what it is, there’s something to me just a little bit missing there and I think that would restore the works, it's not necessarily about the technology shifting that fast, it’s about sharing a little bit more.</p></sp></body></text></TEI>